<!DOCTYPE article
PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.2 20190208//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-mathml3.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="review-article"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">3D Print Med</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">3D Print Med</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>3D Printing in Medicine</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2365-6271</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Springer International Publishing</publisher-name><publisher-loc>Cham</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">33079298</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">7574578</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">82</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s41205-020-00082-5</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Review</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>3D printed bone models in oral and cranio-maxillofacial surgery: a systematic review</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Meglioli</surname><given-names>Matteo</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Naveau</surname><given-names>Adrien</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff4">4</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Macaluso</surname><given-names>Guido Maria</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff5">5</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-3419-3467</contrib-id><name><surname>Catros</surname><given-names>Sylvain</given-names></name><address><email>sylvain.catros@u-bordeaux.fr</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff4">4</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff6">6</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff7">7</xref></contrib><aff id="Aff1"><label>1</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.10383.39</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0004 1758 0937</institution-id><institution>University Center of Dentistry, Department of Medicine and Surgery, University of Parma, </institution></institution-wrap>Via Gramsci 14, 43126 Parma, Italy </aff><aff id="Aff2"><label>2</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.412041.2</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0001 2106 639X</institution-id><institution>Department of Prosthodontics, Dental Science Faculty, </institution><institution>University of Bordeaux, </institution></institution-wrap>46 rue L&#x000e9;o-Saignat, 33076 Bordeaux, France </aff><aff id="Aff3"><label>3</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.414339.8</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0001 2200 1651</institution-id><institution>Dental and Periodontal Rehabilitation Unit, </institution><institution>Saint Andre Hospital, Bordeaux University Hospital, </institution></institution-wrap>46 rue L&#x000e9;o-Saignat, 33076 Bordeaux, France </aff><aff id="Aff4"><label>4</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.412041.2</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0001 2106 639X</institution-id><institution>Biotis Laboratory, Inserm U1026, </institution><institution>University of Bordeaux, </institution></institution-wrap>46 rue L&#x000e9;o-Saignat, 33076 Bordeaux, France </aff><aff id="Aff5"><label>5</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.473331.1</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0004 1789 9243</institution-id><institution>IMEM-CNR, Parco Area delle Scienze 37/A, </institution></institution-wrap>43124 Parma, Italy </aff><aff id="Aff6"><label>6</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.412041.2</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0001 2106 639X</institution-id><institution>Department of Oral Surgery, UFR d&#x02019;Odontologie, </institution><institution>University of Bordeaux, </institution></institution-wrap>46 rue L&#x000e9;o-Saignat, 33076 Bordeaux, France </aff><aff id="Aff7"><label>7</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.42399.35</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0004 0593 7118</institution-id><institution>Service de Chirurgie Orale, CHU de Bordeaux, </institution></institution-wrap>46 rue L&#x000e9;o-Saignat, 33076 Bordeaux, France </aff></contrib-group><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>20</day><month>10</month><year>2020</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>20</day><month>10</month><year>2020</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><month>12</month><year>2020</year></pub-date><volume>6</volume><elocation-id>30</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>14</day><month>4</month><year>2020</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>18</day><month>9</month><year>2020</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; The Author(s) 2020</copyright-statement><license license-type="OpenAccess"><license-p><bold>Open Access</bold>This article is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License, which permits use, sharing, adaptation, distribution and reproduction in any medium or format, as long as you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons licence, and indicate if changes were made. The images or other third party material in this article are included in the article's Creative Commons licence, unless indicated otherwise in a credit line to the material. If material is not included in the article's Creative Commons licence and your intended use is not permitted by statutory regulation or exceeds the permitted use, you will need to obtain permission directly from the copyright holder. To view a copy of this licence, visit <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>. The Creative Commons Public Domain Dedication waiver (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</ext-link>) applies to the data made available in this article, unless otherwise stated in a credit line to the data.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract id="Abs1"><sec><title>Aim</title><p id="Par1">This systematic review aimed to evaluate the use of three-dimensional (3D) printed bone models for training, simulating and/or planning interventions in oral and cranio-maxillofacial surgery.</p></sec><sec><title>Materials and methods</title><p id="Par2">A systematic search was conducted using PubMed&#x000ae; and SCOPUS&#x000ae; databases, up to March 10, 2019, by following the Preferred Reporting Items for Systematic reviews and Meta-Analysis (PRISMA) protocol. Study selection, quality assessment (modified Critical Appraisal Skills Program tool) and data extraction were performed by two independent reviewers. All original full papers written in English/French/Italian and dealing with the fabrication of 3D printed models of head bone structures, designed from 3D radiological data were included.</p><p id="Par3">Multiple parameters and data were investigated, such as author&#x02019;s purpose, data acquisition systems, printing technologies and materials, accuracy, haptic feedback, variations in treatment time, differences in clinical outcomes, costs, production time and cost-effectiveness.</p></sec><sec><title>Results</title><p id="Par4">Among the 1157 retrieved abstracts, only 69 met the inclusion criteria. 3D printed bone models were mainly used as training or simulation models for tumor removal, or bone reconstruction. Material jetting printers showed best performance but the highest cost. Stereolithographic, laser sintering and binder jetting printers allowed to create accurate models with adequate haptic feedback. The cheap fused deposition modeling printers exhibited satisfactory results for creating training models.</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusion</title><p id="Par5">Patient-specific 3D printed models are known to be useful surgical and educational tools. Faced with the large diversity of software, printing technologies and materials, the clinical team should invest in a 3D printer specifically adapted to the final application.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group xml:lang="en"><title>Keywords</title><kwd>3D printing</kwd><kwd>Additive manufacturing, Bone model</kwd><kwd>Surgical training</kwd><kwd>Preoperative planning</kwd><kwd>Simulation</kwd></kwd-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name><meta-value>&#x000a9; The Author(s) 2020</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="Sec1"><title>Introduction</title><p id="Par25">Technological development strongly drives the evolution of oral and cranio-maxillofacial surgery [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>]. Among all the additive manufacturing (AM) processes, &#x0201c;three-dimensional printing&#x0201d; (3DP), often used synonymously with additive manufacturing, is playing an ever-growing role. This technology involves the fabrication of objects through the deposition of material using a print head, nozzle, or other printing technology [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>]. It allows creating objects layer-by-layer through computer-aided design/computer-aided manufacturing (CAD/CAM). It was originally developed in the 1980s to accelerate the production of small and custom-designed objects, but it revolutionized the prototyping concepts and embraced many applications in manufacturing industries. Later on, AM&#x02019;s applications started to be integrated in several medical techniques and procedures, giving some important inputs to various domains, such as dentistry, maxillofacial surgery, orthopedics and neurosurgery. Frequent clinical applications of 3D printing in everyday practice include the fabrication of surgical templates employed to improve the accuracy of the surgery and reduce the duration and morbidity of surgical interventions. It is now applied in routine in oral and craniofacial surgery [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>]. More recently, the progress made in the 3D-printing of implantable biomaterials were applied to the fabrication of custom implants, based on patients&#x02019; radiological data: even if a large amount of these commercial custom implants are milled, 3D-printing technologies can be employed for large bone defects reconstruction like cranioplasty [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>] or Temporo-mandibular joint replacement [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>].</p><p id="Par26">Three-dimensional printing techniques involve creation of accurate physical 3D models from the patient&#x02019;s radiological data. The first step consists in obtaining the Digital Imaging and COmmunications in Medicine (DICOM) files from patient&#x02019;s imaging exams, such as computed tomography (CT) or magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) scans. Then software is used to transform them into a digital 3D object file, such as standard tessellation language (STL), among other formats. For surgical model fabrication, this new file can be printed with different techniques, such as vat photopolymerization (VP), material extrusion (ME) or binder jetting (BJ). 3D printing encompasses different techniques, each of them having its own benefits and drawbacks (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>). Several printing materials can be used, each with specific mechanical and accuracy properties. Sometimes, a post-curing step is required to obtain the finished product [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>]. The obtained surgical models can fulfill three different purposes: training, planning and simulating. An example of three different models is shown in Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>.
<fig id="Fig1"><label>Fig. 1</label><caption><p>Schematic representation of rapid prototyping techniques for surgery applications: (<bold>a</bold>) Powder bed fusion (<bold>b</bold>) Vat photopolymeration (<bold>c</bold>) Material extrusion (<bold>d</bold>) Binder jetting (<bold>e</bold>) Material jetting</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41205_2020_82_Fig1_HTML" id="MO1"/></fig><fig id="Fig2"><label>Fig. 2</label><caption><p>Examples of anatomical models fabricated by Additive manufacturing. A: A mandible model fabricated using SLA to serve as a template for bone allograft preparation during surgery. B: A model fabricated using SLA to visualize the extent of a bone defect (cleft) for planning the bone reconstructive surgery. C: A model representing a section of a mandible. It was used for training students in dental implant surgery</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41205_2020_82_Fig2_HTML" id="MO2"/></fig></p><p id="Par27">A training model is produced to enhance the quality of the teaching, by allowing students and clinicians to perform high-quality surgical training. Adequate haptic feedback and moderate cost are the most important characteristic of training models. Instead of training on cadaver or animal models, students can enhance their skills on accurate 3DP models that reproduce the haptic feedback of the patient&#x02019;s bone [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>]. Although cadaveric specimens have high anatomical and physical validity, they are often challenging to obtain, lack patient-specific pathologic features, and are associated with costs that may be prohibitive to repetitive training [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>]. Several authors described temporal bone surgeries [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>], implant treatment or maxillary sinus floor augmentation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>] training in realistic in vitro conditions using these 3D-printed models. Thus, one of the most important characteristics of a training model is the low cost.</p><p id="Par28">Secondly, a 3DP model could be made for planning complex surgeries and to fully understand the patient&#x02019;s conditions. The manipulation of the patient anatomical structures helps to get a better understanding of his specific condition and to plan the required surgical interventions [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>]. These models are often used in orthognathic and reconstructive surgeries, giving the possibility of a better comprehension and more predictable results [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>]. Measurements and surgical pre-operative evaluations can be performed on these models. Thus, the most important characteristic of a planning model is accuracy.</p><p id="Par29">Finally, a simulating model is produced to perform a surgery before it is done in clinics. This type of models must be accurate with a patient-like haptic feedback. Users can act on these models like they are working on patients. Simulating models are used by clinicians before preforming important surgical interventions, such as tumor excisions [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>] and pediatric mastoidectomy [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>]. The right mechanical properties, such as the elastic modulus, the stiffness or the drilling force, are fundamental parameters that allow the operator to experience haptic feedback similar to that encountered during actual surgery. Thus, one of the most important characteristic of a simulating model is related to its mechanical properties.</p><p id="Par30">A surgeon wanting to invest in a printer can be overwhelmed in his choice by the numerous options available, between printing materials and technologies. Moreover, the cost-benefit ratio must be taken into consideration, as cheap technologies can be sufficient for some applications. Our hypothesis was that each application of the surgical model could be correlated with a specific 3D printing technology. This systematic review investigated the state of the art of printing materials and techniques proposed to create models for training, simulating and planning interventions in oral and craniofacial surgery. The research focused on the regions of head and neck, scanning articles that belong to different fields: dentistry and oral surgery, maxillofacial surgery, ear-nose-throat surgery and cranial surgery. These results also provided practical suggestions for choosing the optimal 3D printing technique and material for each application objective.</p></sec><sec id="Sec2"><title>Methods</title><sec id="Sec3"><title>Study protocol</title><p id="Par31">The protocol of this systematic review was registered in &#x02018;PROSPERO: International prospective register of systematic reviews&#x02019; (CRD42019117468) and followed the PRISMA guidelines.</p><p id="Par32">The main question, that was not PICO compliant, was: &#x02018;What are the existing printed bone models currently used for training, planning and simulating interventions in oral and cranio-maxillofacial surgery?&#x02019; The impossibility of using a PICO question and performing a meta-analysis are two missing points of PRISMA checklist.</p></sec><sec id="Sec4"><title>Search strategy</title><p id="Par33">Medline (PubMed) database and Scopus database were searched up to March 10, 2019 with the following equation:<disp-quote><p><italic>(additive manufacturing OR rapid prototyping OR bone model OR bone models OR anatomical models OR anatomical model OR phantom OR phantoms OR simulation model OR simulation models OR 3D&#x02212;printed models OR 3D printed models OR 3D&#x02212;printed model OR 3D printed model) AND (planning OR hands&#x02212;on OR train OR training OR simulation) AND (surgery OR surgical OR dentistry OR dental OR teaching OR pre&#x02212;operative) AND (maxillofacial OR oral OR skull base OR jaw bones OR jaw OR sinus OR mandible OR temporal bone OR teeth OR maxilla OR human bone OR implant) NOT biology NOT cartilage NOT mathematical</italic></p></disp-quote></p><p id="Par34">This process only selected articles that had search terms in the title or in the abstract without any restriction on language.</p><p id="Par35">The search was also launched with the following MeSH (PubMed) terms: <italic>(&#x0201c;Surgical Procedures, Operative&#x0201d; OR &#x0201c;Teaching&#x0201d;) AND &#x0201c;Printing, Three-Dimensional&#x0201d; AND &#x0201c;Models, Anatomic&#x0201d; AND &#x0201c;Head&#x0201d;.</italic></p><p id="Par36">Other interesting original research articles were added through manual search.</p></sec><sec id="Sec5"><title>Science mapping</title><p id="Par37">A science mapping analysis of subject domains was performed by using keyword co-occurrence networking on VOSviewer (free software, version 1.6.15, Centre for Science and Technology Studies, Leiden University, The Netherlands, 2017). A network analysis of the Pubmed MeSH keywords was generated from the matrix of retrieved papers (threshold value at 90). The MeSH terms-document matrix allowed to measure document similarities between clusters of topics.</p></sec><sec id="Sec6"><title>Study selection</title><p id="Par38">All original full papers written in English/French/Italian and dealing with the fabrication of 3D printed models of head bone structures obtained from 3D imaging data were considered as potentially eligible. Case report, case series, pilot studies and comparative studies were included in this research.</p><p id="Par39">Literature reviews, conference abstracts, articles employing animal tissues or cadaver models or models not aimed to the head region were excluded.</p></sec><sec id="Sec7"><title>Study analysis</title><p id="Par40">All the retrieved references, after launching the search algorithm, were managed using Endnote&#x000ae; Abstracts of studies retrieved using the search strategy and those from additional sources were screened independently by three authors (M.M, A.N. and S.C) to identify studies that potentially met the inclusion criteria. Papers fulfilling the inclusion criteria, and those presenting insufficient data in the title and the abstract to make a decision, were selected for full analysis. After reading the full texts, the proper articles were included in an evidence table. Any disagreement over the eligibility of studies was resolved through discussion and consensus among the authors.</p></sec><sec id="Sec8"><title>Quality assessment</title><p id="Par41">The quality of the included studies was assessed using a modified version of the Critical Appraisal Skills Programme (CASP) tool [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>]. For each of the 10 questions of this tool, there were three possible answers: &#x02018;Yes&#x02019;, &#x02018;Can&#x02019;t tell&#x02019; or &#x02018;No&#x02019;. Every &#x02018;Yes&#x02019; scored 1 point, while &#x02018;No&#x02019; or &#x02018;Can&#x02019;t tell&#x02019; scored 0 points. Total scores were converted to percentages and studies were allocated to one of three categories; &#x02018;Good quality&#x02019; for a score of 67&#x02013;100%, &#x02018;Average quality&#x02019; for 34&#x02013;66% and &#x02018;Poor quality&#x02019; for 0&#x02013;33%.</p></sec><sec id="Sec9"><title>Data extraction</title><p id="Par42">The data were extracted and critically appraised by two independent authors (M.M and G.M.M.).</p><p id="Par43">Using a standardized data extraction form, the authors extracted the following data: year of publication, data acquisition system, type of printing technique involved, material, accuracy, production time, haptic feedback, treatment time, clinical outcomes, cost and purpose of the publication: training, planning, simulation (multiple possibilities for each paper).</p></sec><sec id="Sec10"><title>Data analysis</title><p id="Par44">A narrative synthesis of the data was conducted due to the heterogeneity of study designs and methods. For the same reason it was not possible to perform a meta-analysis.</p><p id="Par45">In order to address the general question of defining the state of the art of 3D printing to address the surgical planning, simulation and training needs, the authors identified as crucial these characteristics: accuracy, haptic feedback and cost.</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec11"><title>Results</title><sec id="Sec12"><title>Search general results</title><p id="Par46">After database screening and removal of duplicates using Endnote&#x000ae; [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>], 1157 articles were identified. After abstract screening, 119 studies were selected. After full text reading, 64 articles were selected, plus 5 other articles found among the related ones found by additional manual search (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>). The main reason for excluding articles was a content not addressing AM models issues. Many excluded articles dealt with analogic models, virtual models or perfusion-based models, or related to the orthopedic and veterinary fields. Six articles were not written in English/French/Italian.
<fig id="Fig3"><label>Fig. 3</label><caption><p>PRISMA flow chart</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41205_2020_82_Fig3_HTML" id="MO3"/></fig></p><p id="Par47">Eight articles were excluded after reviewers&#x02019; discussion: three authors involved commercial models [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>], one article dealt with papercraft models [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>], one article dealt with a silicon model molded on a 3D printed mold [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref>] and 3 articles dealt with other surgical fields (orthopedics [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>] and veterinary sciences [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref>]).</p><p id="Par48">The spatial representation of the relationships between the Mesh keywords was displayed through a science map (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>). The networks noticeably highlighted the interest for modelling human patients from imaging data through a computer assisted procedure. Bone surgery, prosthetic rehabilitation and radiotherapy were among the most represented families of clinical applications. &#x0201c;Mandible&#x0201d; was the most co-occurring bone keywords. &#x0201c;Material testing&#x0201d;, &#x0201c;treatment outcome&#x0201d; and &#x0201c;clinical competence&#x0201d; were often studied. These graphic references did not show any Mesh keywords regarding the 3D printing technologies themselves (under the threshold).
<fig id="Fig4"><label>Fig. 4</label><caption><p>Mesh keyword co-occurrence networks among the retrieved articles. The size of each node is proportionate to its degree and the thickness of the links represents the tie strength</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41205_2020_82_Fig4_HTML" id="MO4"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="Sec13"><title>Quality assessment (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>)</title><p id="Par49">With the modified Critical Appraisals Skills Programme (CASP) tool [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>] the reviewers have identified as &#x0201c;high-quality studies&#x0201d; only 8 original researches. The authors classified as &#x0201c;average quality studies&#x0201d; and &#x0201c;poor quality studies&#x0201d; 46 and 15 articles respectively. The lack of quantitative or rigorous tests and appropriate study designs were found in most of the selected studies.
<table-wrap id="Tab1"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>CASP questions and results of the quality assessment</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th>CASP Questions</th><th>Results</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>Was there a clear statement of the aims of this research?</td><td>High Quality</td></tr><tr><td>Is a qualitative methodology appropriate?</td><td>8 Articles</td></tr><tr><td colspan="2">The research was designed appropriate to address the aims of this research?</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;Was the recruitment strategy appropriate tothe aims of the research?</td><td>Average Quality</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;Was the data collected in a way that adressed the research issue?</td><td>46 Articles</td></tr><tr><td colspan="2">Has the relationship between researcher and participants been adequately considered?</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;Have ethical issues been taken into consideration?</td><td>Low Quality</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;Was the data analysis sufficiently rigorous?</td><td>15 Articles</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;Is there a clear statement of findings?</td><td/></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;How valuable is the research?</td><td/></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></p></sec><sec id="Sec14"><title>General information (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref>)</title><p id="Par50">Only 5 articles (6%) were published before 2008. Ten articles (18%) were published between 2009 and 2014. Forty-two articles (78%) were published between 2015 and March 10, 2019.
<table-wrap id="Tab2"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>General Information of the included studies</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th>Year</th><th>Author</th><th>Study Design</th><th>Country</th><th>Domain</th><th>Treatment</th><th>Target</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>2019</td><td>Lanis A et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>]</td><td>Case Report</td><td>Chile</td><td>Dentistry</td><td>Implant treatment</td><td>Planning</td></tr><tr><td>2019</td><td>Freiser ME et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref>]</td><td>Validation Study</td><td>USA</td><td>ENT Surgery</td><td>Temporal bone access</td><td>Planning, Simulation, Training</td></tr><tr><td>2019</td><td>Zhuo C et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref>]</td><td>Validation Study</td><td>China</td><td>ENT Surgery</td><td>Endoscopic sinus surgery</td><td>Training, Simulation</td></tr><tr><td>2018</td><td>Bhadra D et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref>]</td><td>Case Report</td><td>India</td><td>Dentistry</td><td>Endodontic retreatment</td><td>Planning</td></tr><tr><td>2018</td><td>Lin B et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref>]</td><td>Validation Study</td><td>China</td><td>Cranial Surgery</td><td>Tumor removal surgery</td><td>Planning, Simulation, Training</td></tr><tr><td>2018</td><td>Probst R et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>]</td><td>Validation Study</td><td>Switzerland - Germany</td><td>Cranial Surgery</td><td>Temporal pediatric surgery, coclear implantation</td><td>Training</td></tr><tr><td>2018</td><td>Hsieh TY et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>]</td><td>Validation Study</td><td>USA</td><td>ENT Surgery</td><td>Endoscopic skull base surgery</td><td>Planning, Simulation, Training</td></tr><tr><td>2018</td><td>Reymus M et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref>]</td><td>Validation Study</td><td>Germany</td><td>Dentistry</td><td>Dental traumatology</td><td>Training,</td></tr><tr><td>2018</td><td>Sugahara K et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref>]</td><td>Pilot Study</td><td>Japan</td><td>Maxillofacial Surgery</td><td>Reconstruction and orthognathic surgery</td><td>Planning</td></tr><tr><td>2018</td><td>Werz SM et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref>]</td><td>Validation Study</td><td>Germany</td><td>Dentistry</td><td>General dentistry</td><td>Training</td></tr><tr><td>2018</td><td>Chou PY et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>]</td><td>Validation Study</td><td>USA</td><td>Maxillofacial Surgery</td><td>Cleft lip and palate surgery</td><td>Simulation</td></tr><tr><td>2018</td><td>Arce K et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>]</td><td>Case Report</td><td>USA</td><td>Maxillofacial Surgery</td><td>Mandibular reconstruction</td><td>Planning</td></tr><tr><td>2018</td><td>Lin WJ et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">38</xref>]</td><td>Validation Study</td><td>China</td><td>ENT Surgery</td><td>Sinus and skull base anatomical study</td><td>Training</td></tr><tr><td>2018</td><td>Haffner M et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref>]</td><td>Comparative Study</td><td>USA</td><td>ENT Surgery</td><td>Mastoidectomy</td><td>Training</td></tr><tr><td>2018</td><td>Jacek B et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref>]</td><td>Comparative Study</td><td>Poland</td><td>Maxillofacial Surgery</td><td>Mandibular reconstruction with bony free flap</td><td>Planning</td></tr><tr><td>2018</td><td>Alodadi A et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref>]</td><td>Case Report</td><td>Saudi</td><td>Dentistry</td><td>Implantology</td><td>Planning</td></tr><tr><td>2018</td><td>Reddy GV et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">42</xref>]</td><td>Validation Study</td><td>India</td><td>Maxillofacial Surgery</td><td>Orthognathic surgery</td><td>Training</td></tr><tr><td>2017</td><td>Favier V et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">43</xref>]</td><td>Comparative Study</td><td>France</td><td>Cranial Surgery</td><td>Skull base endoscopic surgery</td><td>Planning, Simulation, Training</td></tr><tr><td>2017</td><td>Somji SH et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>]</td><td>Case Report</td><td>USA</td><td>Dentistry</td><td>Sinus augmentation</td><td>Planning, Simulation, Training</td></tr><tr><td>2017</td><td>Gargiulo P et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>]</td><td>Case Report</td><td>Iceland</td><td>Cranial Surgery</td><td>Tumor removal surgery</td><td>Planning, Simulation</td></tr><tr><td>2017</td><td>Alrasheed AS et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44">44</xref>]</td><td>Validation Study</td><td>Canada</td><td>Maxillofacial Surgery</td><td>Endoscopic sinus surgery</td><td>Training</td></tr><tr><td>2017</td><td>Wang L et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">45</xref>]</td><td>Comparative Study</td><td>China</td><td>Maxillofacial Surgery</td><td>Aneurysm surgery</td><td>Planning, Simulation, Training</td></tr><tr><td>2017</td><td>Javan R et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46">46</xref>]</td><td>Pilot Study</td><td>USA</td><td>Maxillofacial Surgery</td><td>Cranial nerve anatomy</td><td>Training</td></tr><tr><td>2017</td><td>Legocki AT et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47">47</xref>]</td><td>Case Series</td><td>USA</td><td>Maxillofacial Surgery</td><td>Craniofacial reconstruction</td><td>Planning, Simulation, Training</td></tr><tr><td>2017</td><td>Takahashi K et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>]</td><td>Validation Study</td><td>Japan</td><td>ENT Surgery</td><td>Temporal bone dissection</td><td>Training</td></tr><tr><td>2017</td><td>Yusa K et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>]</td><td>Case Report</td><td>Japan</td><td>Maxillofacial Surgery</td><td>Tumor removal</td><td>Planning, Simulation</td></tr><tr><td>2017</td><td>Ghizoni E et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48">48</xref>]</td><td>Validation Study</td><td>Brazil</td><td>Maxillofacial Surgery</td><td>Craniostenosis</td><td>Training</td></tr><tr><td>2017</td><td>Wiedermann JP et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49">49</xref>]</td><td>Case Report</td><td>USA</td><td>Maxillofacial Surgery</td><td>Cranio-cervicofacial teratoma</td><td>Planning</td></tr><tr><td>2017</td><td>Oscar Mario Jacobo et Al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50">50</xref>]</td><td>Validation Study</td><td>Uruguay</td><td>Maxillofacial Surgery</td><td>Mandible and orbita recostruction</td><td>Planning, Training</td></tr><tr><td>2016</td><td>Wanibuchi M et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51">51</xref>]</td><td>Validation Study</td><td>Japan</td><td>Maxillofacial Surgery</td><td>Mastoidectomy</td><td>Training</td></tr><tr><td>2016</td><td>Bone TM et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR52">52</xref>]</td><td>Validation Study</td><td>USA</td><td>ENT Surgery</td><td>Temporal bone surgery</td><td>Training</td></tr><tr><td>2016</td><td>Florentino VGB et Al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR53">53</xref>]</td><td>Case Report</td><td>Brazil</td><td>Maxillofacial Surger</td><td>Reconstruction of temporal bone</td><td>Planning</td></tr><tr><td>2016</td><td>Kondo K et Al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR54">54</xref>]</td><td>Validation Study</td><td>Japan</td><td>Cranial Surgery</td><td>Craniotomy</td><td>Training, Simulation</td></tr><tr><td>2016</td><td>Lim SH et Al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55">55</xref>]</td><td>Validation Study</td><td>Korea</td><td>Macillo-Facial Surgery</td><td>Mandible reconstruction</td><td>Planning</td></tr><tr><td>2015</td><td>Pacione D et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR56">56</xref>]</td><td>Pilot Study</td><td>USA</td><td>Maxillofacial Surgery</td><td>Deformity of the skull base and craniovertebral junction</td><td>Planning</td></tr><tr><td>2015</td><td>Chan HHL et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR57">57</xref>]</td><td>Case Series</td><td>Canada</td><td>Maxillofacial Surgery</td><td>Head and neck surgery</td><td>Training, Simulation</td></tr><tr><td>2015</td><td>Dickinson KJ et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR58">58</xref>]</td><td>Case Report</td><td>USA</td><td>Maxillofacial Surgery</td><td>Endoscopic resection in esophagus</td><td>Planning</td></tr><tr><td>2015</td><td>Hochman JB et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR59">59</xref>]</td><td>Comparative Study</td><td>Canada</td><td>Maxillofacial Surgery</td><td>Mastoidectomy and skull base surgery</td><td>Training</td></tr><tr><td>2015</td><td>Cohen J et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR60">60</xref>]</td><td>Validation Study</td><td>USA</td><td>Maxillofacial Surgery</td><td>Mastoidectomy</td><td>Training</td></tr><tr><td>2015</td><td>Lim C et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>]</td><td>Case Series</td><td>Australia - New Zealand</td><td>Maxillofacial Surgery</td><td>Orbital reconstruction</td><td>Planning</td></tr><tr><td>2015</td><td>Rose AS et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR61">61</xref>]</td><td>Case Report</td><td>USA</td><td>ENT Surgery</td><td>Mastoidectomy</td><td>Planning, Simulation</td></tr><tr><td>2015</td><td>Ernoult C. et Al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR62">62</xref>]</td><td>Case Series</td><td>France</td><td>Maxillofacial Surgery</td><td>Reconstructive surgery</td><td>Simulation</td></tr><tr><td>2015</td><td>Mowry SE. et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR63">63</xref>]</td><td>Validation Study</td><td>USA</td><td>ENT Surgery</td><td>Temporal bone access</td><td>Training</td></tr><tr><td>2015</td><td>Hochman JB et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR64">64</xref>]</td><td>Validation Study</td><td>Canada</td><td>ENT Surgery</td><td>Temporal bone surgery</td><td>Training</td></tr><tr><td>2015</td><td>Longfield EA et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR65">65</xref>]</td><td>Validation Study</td><td>USA</td><td>ENT Surgery</td><td>Temporal pediatric surgery</td><td>Training</td></tr><tr><td>2015</td><td>Rose AS et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR66">66</xref>]</td><td>Validation Study</td><td>USA</td><td>ENT Surgery</td><td>Temporal bone surgery</td><td>Training</td></tr><tr><td>2014</td><td>Hochman JB et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR67">67</xref>]</td><td>Case Report</td><td>Canada</td><td>ENT Surgery</td><td>Temporal bone surgery</td><td>Training</td></tr><tr><td>2014</td><td>Chenebaux M et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR68">68</xref>]</td><td>Validation Study</td><td>France</td><td>ENT Surgery</td><td>Temporal bone surgery</td><td>Training</td></tr><tr><td>2014</td><td>Narayanan V et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR69">69</xref>]</td><td>Validation Study</td><td>Malaysia</td><td>ENT Surgery</td><td>Skull base surgery</td><td>Training</td></tr><tr><td>2014</td><td>Cui J et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR70">70</xref>]</td><td>Validation Study</td><td>China</td><td>Maxillofacial Surgery</td><td>Cranial trauma</td><td>Planning</td></tr><tr><td>2014</td><td>Gil RS et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR71">71</xref>]</td><td>Validation Study</td><td>Spain</td><td>Maxillofacial Surgery</td><td>Mandible reconstruction</td><td>Planning</td></tr><tr><td>2014</td><td>Jardini AL et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR72">72</xref>]</td><td>Case Report</td><td>Brasil</td><td>Cranial Surgery</td><td>Cranial reconstruction</td><td>Planning</td></tr><tr><td>2013</td><td>Jabbour P et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR73">73</xref>]</td><td>Validation Study</td><td>USA</td><td>Cranial Surgery</td><td>Presigmoid access</td><td>Training</td></tr><tr><td>2013</td><td>Li J et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR74">74</xref>]</td><td>Case Series</td><td>China</td><td>Maxillofacial Surgery</td><td>Orbital reconstruction</td><td>Planning</td></tr><tr><td>2012</td><td>Ciocca L et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR75">75</xref>]</td><td>Case Report</td><td>Italy</td><td>Maxillofacial Surgery</td><td>Mandible reconstruction</td><td>Planning</td></tr><tr><td>2011</td><td>Mori K et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR76">76</xref>]</td><td>Validation Study</td><td>Japan</td><td>Cranial Surgery</td><td>Cerebral revascularization via skull approaches</td><td>Training, Simulation</td></tr><tr><td>2011</td><td>Morrison D et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR77">77</xref>]</td><td>Case Report</td><td>Australia</td><td>Cranial Surgery</td><td>Cranial reconstruction</td><td>Planning</td></tr><tr><td>2010</td><td>Nikzad S et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR78">78</xref>]</td><td>Case Report</td><td>Iran</td><td>Dentistry</td><td>Sinus lift and implant treatment</td><td>Planning</td></tr><tr><td>2010</td><td>Katatny IE et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR79">79</xref>]</td><td>Validation Study</td><td>Australia</td><td>Maxillofacial Surgery</td><td>Mandibular surgery</td><td>Planning</td></tr><tr><td>2010</td><td>Lambrecht JTH et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR80">80</xref>]</td><td>Case Series</td><td>Switzerland</td><td>Dentistry</td><td>Oral surgery</td><td>Training</td></tr><tr><td>2009</td><td>Sohmura T et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR81">81</xref>]</td><td>Case Series</td><td>Japan</td><td>Dentistry</td><td>Implant treatment</td><td>Planning, Training</td></tr><tr><td>2009</td><td>Mori K et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR82">82</xref>]</td><td>Validation Study</td><td>Japan</td><td>ENT Surgery</td><td>Skull base surgery</td><td>Training</td></tr><tr><td>2009</td><td>Radley GJ et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR83">83</xref>]</td><td>Comparative</td><td>UK</td><td>ENT Surgery</td><td>Endoscopic sinus surgery</td><td>Training</td></tr><tr><td>2009</td><td>Cohen A et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR84">84</xref>]</td><td>Case Series</td><td>Syria</td><td>Maxillofacial Surgery</td><td>Mandible reconstruction</td><td>Planning</td></tr><tr><td>2007</td><td>Suzuki M et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR85">85</xref>]</td><td>Validation Study</td><td>Japan</td><td>ENT Surgery</td><td>Temporal bone surgery</td><td>Training</td></tr><tr><td>2007</td><td>Mavili ME et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR86">86</xref>]</td><td>Case Series</td><td>Turkey</td><td>Dentistry</td><td>Orthognatic surgery</td><td>Planning, Simulation</td></tr><tr><td>2004</td><td>Suzuki M et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR87">87</xref>]</td><td>Validation Study</td><td>Japan</td><td>ENT Surgery</td><td>Temporal bone access</td><td>Training</td></tr><tr><td>2003</td><td>Muller A et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR88">88</xref>]</td><td>Case Series</td><td>Germany</td><td>Cranial Surgery</td><td>Cranioplasty, tumor removal</td><td>Planning, Simulation</td></tr><tr><td>1997</td><td>L&#x000f6;pponen H et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR89">89</xref>]</td><td>Case Report</td><td>Finland</td><td>ENT Surgery</td><td>Cochlear implant</td><td>Simulation, Training</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></p><p id="Par51">Among all articles, 3 were pilot studies, 12 were case reports, 4 were case series, 29 were validation studies and only 6 were comparative studies. The authors classified as &#x0201c;validation studies&#x0201d; all original researches that had described and eventually evaluated a process to fabricate a printed bone model. The reviewers classified as &#x0201c;comparative studies&#x0201d; all the researches that compared models printed by different techniques or models printed by different printers using the same technique. Lastly, a paper comparing a bone model to a cadaver&#x02019;s bone was also considered as a comparative study [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR59">59</xref>].</p></sec><sec id="Sec15"><title>Purposes of the articles</title><p id="Par52">The models mentioned in the selected articles were used for different purposes (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref>). In 31 articles the models were used to plan a surgery, in 19 they were used to simulate the surgery, and in 32 they were used for training of students or clinicians. This total (82) exceeded the total number of papers, as some models were used for multiple purposes.</p></sec><sec id="Sec16"><title>Surgical field</title><p id="Par53">The reports on 3DP models concerned multiple surgical domains (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref>). Oral and maxillofacial surgery had the largest share with 43% of articles describing the use of AM models, followed by ENT surgery (29%), dentistry (14%), and cranial surgery (14%).</p></sec><sec id="Sec17"><title>Therapy (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref>)</title><p id="Par54">In dentistry, bone models were more frequently used for simulating dental implant placement [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR81">81</xref>]. In oral and maxillofacial surgery, the models were more frequently used for planning a bone reconstruction [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47">47</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50">50</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR53">53</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR72">72</xref>] or a tumor removal [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49">49</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR56">56</xref>]. The models prepared for ENT surgery were mostly used for training surgical temporal access [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR52">52</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR63">63</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR68">68</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR85">85</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR87">87</xref>] and mastoidectomy [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51">51</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR59">59</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR61">61</xref>]. Finally, in the field of cranial surgery, the models were most frequently used for the training of the pre-sigmoid approach [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR73">73</xref>] or craniotomy [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR54">54</xref>].</p></sec><sec id="Sec18"><title>Image acquisition and processing</title><p id="Par55">Image acquisition and processing are the first steps to create a 3DP model (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab3" ref-type="table">3</xref>). The most frequently used radiological exam was the CT, followed by cone beam computed tomography (CBCT) and MRI. Software was used to process the radiological data. The most frequently used were Mimics&#x000ae; (Materialise, Leuven, Belgium), followed by OsiriX&#x000ae; (Pixmeo, Geneva, Switzerland) and 3D Slicer&#x000ae; (Surgical Planning Laboratory, Isomics Incorporated, Cambridge, USA). Most of the authors did not specify entirely their digital work-flow to create the STL printable file, making it difficult to reproduce the procedure properly.
<table-wrap id="Tab3"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p>Workflow&#x02019;s analysis of the included studies</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th>Year</th><th>Author</th><th>Data Acquisition</th><th>Images Processing Software</th><th>Printing Technique</th><th>Material</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>2019</td><td>Lanis A et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>]</td><td>CBCT</td><td>CoDiagnostiX</td><td>Vat photopolymerization</td><td>Photosentitive Resin</td></tr><tr><td>2019</td><td>Freiser ME et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref>]</td><td>CT</td><td>3D Slicer</td><td>Vat photopolymerization</td><td>Photosentitive Resin</td></tr><tr><td>2019</td><td>Zhuo C et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref>]</td><td>CT</td><td>Mimics</td><td>Material Extrusion</td><td>PLA</td></tr><tr><td>2018</td><td>Bhadra D et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref>]</td><td>CBCT</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>Material Extrusion</td><td>&#x02013;</td></tr><tr><td>2018</td><td>Lin B et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref>]</td><td>CT</td><td>Mimics</td><td>Material Jetting</td><td>Photosensitive Resin</td></tr><tr><td>2018</td><td>Probst R et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>]</td><td>&#x003bc;CT</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>Binder Jetting</td><td>Cast Powder and Bonding Agent</td></tr><tr><td>2018</td><td>Hsieh TY et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>]</td><td>CT</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>Material Jetting</td><td>Photosensitive Resin</td></tr><tr><td>2018</td><td>Reymus M et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref>]</td><td>CBCT</td><td>InVesalius</td><td>Vat photopolymerization</td><td>Photosensitive Resin</td></tr><tr><td>2018</td><td>Sugahara K et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref>]</td><td>CT</td><td>Mimics</td><td>Material Jetting</td><td>Photosensitive Resin</td></tr><tr><td>2018</td><td>Werz SM et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref>]</td><td>CT</td><td>3D Slicer</td><td>Material Extrusion</td><td>PLA, ABS</td></tr><tr><td>2018</td><td>Chou PY et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>]</td><td>CT</td><td>Mimics</td><td>Material Extrusion</td><td>ABS</td></tr><tr><td>2018</td><td>Arce K et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>]</td><td>CT</td><td>Mimics</td><td>Vat photopolymerization</td><td>Photosentive Resin</td></tr><tr><td>2018</td><td>Lin WJ et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">38</xref>]</td><td>CT</td><td>Mimics</td><td>Material Extrusion</td><td>PLA</td></tr><tr><td>2018</td><td>Haffner M et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref>]</td><td>CT</td><td>Slicer</td><td>Material Extrusion</td><td>PLA, ABS, Nylon, PETG, PC</td></tr><tr><td>2018</td><td>Jacek B et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref>]</td><td>CT</td><td>Slicer</td><td>Material Extrusion</td><td>ABS</td></tr><tr><td>2018</td><td>Alodadi A et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref>]</td><td>CBCT</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td></tr><tr><td>2018</td><td>Reddy GV et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">42</xref>]</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td></tr><tr><td>2017</td><td>Favier V et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">43</xref>]</td><td>CT</td><td>Medical Image Segmentation Tool</td><td>Binder Jetting, Material Jetting, Powder Bed Fusion, Material Extrusion</td><td>Calcium Sulfate Hemihydrate, Opaque Resin, Polyamide, Polycarbonate</td></tr><tr><td>2017</td><td>Somji SH et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>]</td><td>CBCT</td><td>OsiriX</td><td>Vat photopolymerization</td><td>Photosensitive Resin</td></tr><tr><td>2017</td><td>Gargiulo P et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>]</td><td>CT and MRI</td><td>Mimics</td><td>Material Extrusion</td><td>ABS</td></tr><tr><td>2017</td><td>Alrasheed AS et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44">44</xref>]</td><td>CT</td><td>Mimics</td><td>Material Jetting</td><td>Photosensitive Resin</td></tr><tr><td>2017</td><td>Wang L et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">45</xref>]</td><td>CTA</td><td>Mimics</td><td>Material Jetting</td><td>Photosensitive Resin</td></tr><tr><td>2017</td><td>Javan R et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46">46</xref>]</td><td>MRI</td><td>OsiriX</td><td>Powder Bed Fusion</td><td>Polyamide</td></tr><tr><td>2017</td><td>Legocki AT et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47">47</xref>]</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>OsiriX</td><td>Material Extrusion</td><td>PLA</td></tr><tr><td>2017</td><td>Takahashi K et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>]</td><td>CT</td><td>ZedView</td><td>Binder Jetting</td><td>Plastic Powder and Colored Binders</td></tr><tr><td>2017</td><td>Yusa K et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>]</td><td>CT and MRI</td><td>ZedView</td><td>Binder Jetting</td><td>Composite Powder</td></tr><tr><td>2017</td><td>Ghizoni E et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48">48</xref>]</td><td>CT</td><td>Mimics</td><td>Powder Bed Fusion</td><td>Polyamide</td></tr><tr><td>2017</td><td>Wiedermann JP et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49">49</xref>]</td><td>CT and MRI</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td></tr><tr><td>2017</td><td>Oscar Mario Jacobo et Al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50">50</xref>]</td><td>CT</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>Material Extrusion</td><td>PLA</td></tr><tr><td>2016</td><td>Wanibuchi M et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51">51</xref>]</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>Powder Bed Fusion</td><td>Polyamide and Glass Fiber</td></tr><tr><td>2016</td><td>Bone TM et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR52">52</xref>]</td><td>CT</td><td>OsiriX</td><td>Material Extrusion</td><td>ABS</td></tr><tr><td>2016</td><td>Florentino VGB et Al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR53">53</xref>]</td><td>CT</td><td>InVesalius</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td/></tr><tr><td>2016</td><td>Kondo K et Al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR54">54</xref>]</td><td>CT and MRI</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>Binder Jetting</td><td>Calcium sulfate hydrate</td></tr><tr><td>2016</td><td>Lim SH et Al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55">55</xref>]</td><td>CT</td><td>Mimics</td><td>Material Jetting</td><td>&#x02013;</td></tr><tr><td>2015</td><td>Pacione D et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR56">56</xref>]</td><td>CT</td><td>Philips Intellispace Portal</td><td>Material Jetting</td><td>Photosensitive Resin</td></tr><tr><td>2015</td><td>Chan HHL et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR57">57</xref>]</td><td>CT</td><td>Mimics</td><td>Material Extrusion</td><td>ABS, ABS and Powder, Polycarbonate</td></tr><tr><td>2015</td><td>Dickinson KJ et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR58">58</xref>]</td><td>CT and MRI</td><td>Mimics</td><td>Material Jetting</td><td>Photosensitive Resin</td></tr><tr><td>2015</td><td>Hochman JB et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR59">59</xref>]</td><td>CT</td><td>Mimics</td><td>Binder Jetting</td><td>Composite Powder</td></tr><tr><td>2015</td><td>Cohen J et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR60">60</xref>]</td><td>CT</td><td>ITK-Snap</td><td>Material Extrusion</td><td>ABS</td></tr><tr><td>2015</td><td>Lim C et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>]</td><td>CT</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>Material Extrusion</td><td>&#x02013;</td></tr><tr><td>2015</td><td>Rose AS et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR61">61</xref>]</td><td>CT</td><td>Mimics</td><td>Material Jetting</td><td>Photosensitive Resin</td></tr><tr><td>2015</td><td>Ernoult C. et Al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR62">62</xref>]</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>OsiriX</td><td>Material Extrusion</td><td>ABS</td></tr><tr><td>2015</td><td>Mowry SE. et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR63">63</xref>]</td><td>CT</td><td>OsiriX</td><td>Material Extrusion</td><td>ABS</td></tr><tr><td>2015</td><td>Hochman JB et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR64">64</xref>]</td><td>&#x003bc;CT</td><td>Mimics</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td></tr><tr><td>2015</td><td>Longfield EA et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR65">65</xref>]</td><td>CT</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>Binder Jetting</td><td>&#x02013;</td></tr><tr><td>2015</td><td>Rose AS et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR66">66</xref>]</td><td>CT</td><td>Mimics</td><td>Material Jetting</td><td>Photosensitive Resin</td></tr><tr><td>2014</td><td>Hochman JB et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR67">67</xref>]</td><td>CT</td><td>Mimics</td><td>Binder Jetting</td><td>Composite Powder and Colored Binders</td></tr><tr><td>2014</td><td>Chenebaux M et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR68">68</xref>]</td><td>CT</td><td>Magics</td><td>Vat photopolymerization</td><td>Photosensitive Resin</td></tr><tr><td>2014</td><td>Narayanan V et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR69">69</xref>]</td><td>CT and MRI</td><td>Biomodroid</td><td>Material Jetting</td><td>Photosentive Resin</td></tr><tr><td>2014</td><td>Cui J et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR70">70</xref>]</td><td>CT</td><td>Materialise</td><td>Powder Bed Fusion</td><td>Polystirene</td></tr><tr><td>2014</td><td>Gil RS et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR71">71</xref>]</td><td>CT</td><td>Materialise</td><td>Vat photopolymerization, Powder Bed Fusion</td><td>&#x02013;</td></tr><tr><td>2014</td><td>Jardini AL et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR72">72</xref>]</td><td>CT</td><td>InVesalius</td><td>Binder Jetting</td><td>&#x02013;</td></tr><tr><td>2013</td><td>Jabbour P et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR73">73</xref>]</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td></tr><tr><td>2013</td><td>Li J et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR74">74</xref>]</td><td>CT</td><td>3DMSR</td><td>Powder Bed Fusion</td><td>Polystirene</td></tr><tr><td>2012</td><td>Ciocca L et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR75">75</xref>]</td><td>CT</td><td>CFT</td><td>Material Extrusion</td><td>ABS</td></tr><tr><td>2011</td><td>Mori K et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR76">76</xref>]</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>Powder Bed Fusion</td><td>Polyamide</td></tr><tr><td>2011</td><td>Morrison D et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR77">77</xref>]</td><td>CT</td><td>Mimics</td><td>Material Extrusion</td><td>ABS</td></tr><tr><td>2010</td><td>Nikzad S et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR78">78</xref>]</td><td>CT</td><td>Simplant</td><td>Binder Jetting</td><td>Polyamide</td></tr><tr><td>2010</td><td>Katatny IE et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR79">79</xref>]</td><td>CT</td><td>InVesalius</td><td>Material Extrusion</td><td>ABS</td></tr><tr><td>2010</td><td>Lambrecht JTH et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR80">80</xref>]</td><td>CBCT</td><td>Magics</td><td>Material Jetting</td><td>&#x02013;</td></tr><tr><td>2009</td><td>Sohmura T et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR81">81</xref>]</td><td>CT</td><td>VGStudio Max</td><td>Material Extrusion</td><td>ABS</td></tr><tr><td>2009</td><td>Mori K et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR82">82</xref>]</td><td>CT</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>Powder Bed Fusion</td><td>Polyamide</td></tr><tr><td>2009</td><td>Radley GJ et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR83">83</xref>]</td><td>&#x003bc;CT</td><td>Mimics</td><td>Powder Bed Fusion</td><td>Polyamide</td></tr><tr><td>2009</td><td>Cohen A et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR84">84</xref>]</td><td>CT</td><td>Magics</td><td>Material Jetting</td><td>&#x02013;</td></tr><tr><td>2007</td><td>Suzuki M et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR85">85</xref>]</td><td>CT</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>Vat photopolymerization</td><td>&#x02013;</td></tr><tr><td>2007</td><td>Mavili ME et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR86">86</xref>]</td><td>CT</td><td>Mimics</td><td>Material Jetting</td><td>&#x02013;</td></tr><tr><td>2004</td><td>Suzuki M et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR87">87</xref>]</td><td>CT</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>Powder Bed Fusion</td><td>Polyamide</td></tr><tr><td>2003</td><td>Muller A et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR88">88</xref>]</td><td>CT</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>Vat photopolymerization</td><td>Photosensitive resin</td></tr><tr><td>1997</td><td>L&#x000f6;pponen H et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR89">89</xref>]</td><td>CT</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>Vat photopolymerization</td><td>Photosensitive resin</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></p></sec><sec id="Sec19"><title>Printing systems and materials</title><p id="Par56">Material extrusion (ME) printing was the preferred technique to create models, followed by material jetting (MJ), respectively 32% and 22% of the articles (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab3" ref-type="table">3</xref>). Binder jetting and vat photopolymerization (VP) technique were both involved in 10% of papers. Powder bed fusion printers were used in 16% of articles while 9% did not mentioned the type of 3D printer involved. Among all the references selected, the most frequently used material was acrylonitrile butadiene styrene (ABS), currently only used with material extrusion printers.</p></sec><sec id="Sec20"><title>Quantitative evaluation</title><p id="Par57">Accuracy and mechanical characteristics are strongly dependent on the 3D printer&#x02019;s characteristics, on the involved printer material and the size of the model. Only three authors analyzed the mechanical properties of their models through quantitative tests [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">43</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR67">67</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR83">83</xref>]. Due to the differences in the printing materials and measuring methods, it was not possible to compare their results (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab4" ref-type="table">4</xref>). For the same reason, it is impossible to compare the model accuracy, despite the fact that several authors measured the geometric discrepancy (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab5" ref-type="table">5</xref>) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">43</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51">51</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR61">61</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR79">79</xref>].
<table-wrap id="Tab4"><label>Table 4</label><caption><p>Quantitative evaluations of 3DP models&#x02019; mechanical properties</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th>Year</th><th>Author</th><th>Objective</th><th>Methods</th><th>Results</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>2017</td><td>Favier V et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">43</xref>]</td><td>Evaluation of several consumer-grade materials for creating patient-specific 3D-printed skull base model for anatomical learning and surgical training.</td><td><p>Four different materials were compared to fabricate the models</p><p>Force sensors were used to evaluate:</p><p>- Average force needed to break thin walls with the surgical suction tip</p><p>- Energy spent and reported instantaneous forces during a 6&#x02009;mm depth drill</p></td><td><p>All materials displayed higher mechanical properties than human cadaver bone</p><p>Resin and PA were not adapted because forces exceeded to break thin walls were too high (200&#x02009;N). Using &#x0201c;Multicolor&#x0201d; and PC, the forces applied were 1.6 to 2.5 / 3.5 times higher than bone. Energy spent during drilling was respectively 1.6 and 2.6 times higher on bone than on PC and Multicolor.</p><p>Finally, PC and Multicolor were the more adapted materials for this application.</p></td></tr><tr><td>2014</td><td>Hochman JB et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR67">67</xref>]</td><td>To generate a rapid-prototyped temporal bone model from computed tomography (CT) data with a specific focus on internal anatomic fidelity.</td><td><p>Three point bending tests, using a Texture Analyzer&#x000ae; were performed to determine the elastic modulus and yield point.</p><p>Thanks to a 3-axis accelerometer the drill vibration during the drilling was evaluated on different materials.</p></td><td>The printed bone models were highly realistic. Void space representation was excellent with 88% concordance between cadaveric bone and the resultant rapid-prototyped temporal bone model. Ultimately, cyanoacrylate with hydroquinone was determined to be the most appropriate infiltrant for both cortical and trabecular simulation. The mechanical properties of all tested infiltrants were similar to real bone</td></tr><tr><td>2009</td><td>Radley GJ et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR83">83</xref>]</td><td>To fabricate and characterize human sinus phantoms by 3D printing for surgery simulation</td><td>A modified surgical instrument was used to evaluate the necessary force to break thin walls made by test materials compared to cadaver bone.</td><td>The materials that could be successfully combined into a suitable fluid were polyurethanes, polishes, and suspended cellulose/polyesters (hardeners).</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><table-wrap id="Tab5"><label>Table 5</label><caption><p>Studies including a quantitative evaluation of 3DP models&#x02019; accuracy</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th>Year</th><th>Author</th><th>Objective</th><th>Methods</th><th>Results / Conclusions</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>2018</td><td>Hsieh TY et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>]</td><td>Fabrication of sinus and skull base 3D-printed models for endoscopic skull base surgery</td><td><p>Numerical measurements and image navigation were used to localize several landmarks on the CT images of the patients compared to the CT of the 3DP model.</p><p>Evaluation of the surgeons perceptions (Likert scale) after dissecting printed models (Haptic Feedback and anatomical accuracy)</p></td><td><p>Comparisons demonstrated less than 5% difference between the images.</p><p>Lickert scores were positive for haptic feedback (4,67/5) and anatomical accuracy (4/5)</p></td></tr><tr><td>2017</td><td>Favier V et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">43</xref>]</td><td>Evaluation of several consumer-grade materials for creating patient-specific 3D-printed skull base model for anatomical learning and surgical training.</td><td>4 different printing materials were compared for accuracy, surgical forces needed to break and drill thin walls</td><td><p>PC and PA displayed the highest printing accuracy.</p><p>The use of printed models in PC is a good substitute to human cadaver bone for skull base surgery simulation</p></td></tr><tr><td>2017</td><td>Legocki AT et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47">47</xref>]</td><td>Evaluation of the feasibility of using low-cost 3D printers for the fabrication of anatomical models for craniofacial reconstruction</td><td><p>Comparison of in-house printing process of surgical models vs commercial printed models.</p><p>3 different mandible models</p><p>Analogical measurements with digital caliper + other criteria (cost, production speed, sterilization &#x02026;)</p></td><td><p>Similar results for the accuracy of both techniques</p><p>Nerve canal visibility, tooth root visibility, and sterilizability were inferior for in house models</p><p>Overall, the in-house technique is adapted for education and surgical planning, including preoperative plates bending.</p></td></tr><tr><td>2016</td><td>Wanibuchi M et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51">51</xref>]</td><td>Fabrication of a 3D temporal bone model and validation of accuracy</td><td>Accuracy was investigated by fusion of the original CT of patient&#x02019;s temporal bone and the 3DP model&#x02019;s CT</td><td><p>The differences between both CT images were below 1&#x02009;mm</p><p>The printed models are adapted for surgical training.</p></td></tr><tr><td>2015</td><td>Rose AS et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR61">61</xref>]</td><td>Producing a patient-specific model for pre-operative simulation in pediatric otologic surgery</td><td><p>Case report of cholesteatoma</p><p>Measurement and comparison of distances between several anatomic landmarks (CT scan / Printed model / During surgery)</p></td><td>The variability was minimal, in terms of absolute distance (mm) and relative distance (%), in measurements between anatomic landmarks obtained from the patient intra-operatively, the pre-operative CT scan and the 3D-printed models.</td></tr><tr><td>2010</td><td>Katatny IE et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR79">79</xref>]</td><td>Simulation of shape and CT values of pulmonary parenchyma and lesions of various sizes using 3DP</td><td>Comparison of patient original CT and printed model CT</td><td><p>High accuracy was observed</p><p>Patient-specific CT imaging phantoms can be obtained by FDM printer</p><p>It can be used for the calibration of CT intensity and validation of image quantification software.</p></td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></p></sec><sec id="Sec21"><title>Qualitative evaluation</title><p id="Par58">Most of the authors analyzed the accuracy and haptic feedback of their models using self-made questionnaires and they usually concluded that 3DP models were accurate. Two authors declared respectively less than 100 and 125&#x02009;&#x003bc;m of geometrical discrepancy between the real bone and the model [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR81">81</xref>]. Some other authors stated that discrepancies could reach 680&#x02009;&#x003bc;m, depending on the size of the model [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47">47</xref>]. The haptic feedback was declared adequate in 75% of articles that investigated it through qualitative tests. A model made of calcium sulfate hemihydrate was considered &#x0201c;too hard&#x0201d; [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">43</xref>] and another 3DP model was &#x0201c;too soft&#x0201d; [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR65">65</xref>]. Few authors showed that it was difficult to print small bones [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR52">52</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR63">63</xref>] and it was reported that some materials melted during drilling [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">43</xref>]. Few authors reported benefiting of a reduction in treatment time up to 20% in the operating room thanks to the models [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50">50</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR75">75</xref>]. A third (35%) of the articles affirmed that the clinical outcomes could potentially be improved by using these techniques, thanks to the better planning and the enhanced comprehension of the patient pathological status. Considering costs and production time, ME printed models were the cheapest [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">38</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">42</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR60">60</xref>] and the fastest printers [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR65">65</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR67">67</xref>]. Cost-effectiveness depended on each clinical case and was more striking when several models needed [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR82">82</xref>]. Only 7% of the authors suggested that their method was not cost-effective [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">43</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR61">61</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR63">63</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR78">78</xref>].</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec22"><title>Discussion</title><p id="Par59">Our original impression was validated by the results, suggesting that, before investing in a printer, the major application of the models needs to be considered. Oral and maxillofacial models for bone surgery applications are mostly used for planning and simulating surgical interventions. Printed products exhibit a wide range of different properties, varying with the machine and the printing material. The main results showed that surgical treatment times can be reduced up to 20%, and that the failure rate tends to decrease [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50">50</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR71">71</xref>]. Many authors suggested that clinical outcomes can be improved, but their findings were not supported by any control group [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">42</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50">50</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR56">56</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR58">58</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR76">76</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR78">78</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR86">86</xref>]. Only Banaszewski et al. involved a control group to compare the use of the 3D printed model for planning the surgical reconstruction of the mandible to the traditional technique. They found that the functional and aesthetic results were greater in the group where a 3DP models were applied [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref>]. A planning model needs to be accurate, but cheap also, as one patient cannot cover extensively all expenses. A training model requires essentially to reproduce relevant haptic feedback and to be an inexpensive investment. These two qualities are also expected to simulate a surgical intervention, but also with a high level of accuracy.</p><sec id="Sec23"><title>Accuracy</title><p id="Par60">The MJ printers are currently the most accurate printers, with printed models exhibiting a geometrical discrepancy of 90&#x02009;&#x003bc;m when compared to the patient&#x02019;s bone [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR76">76</xref>]. The second most accurate printing technique, according to the analyzed articles, is powder bed fusion (PBF). Wanibuchi et al. showed an accuracy ranging from 100&#x02009;&#x003bc;m to 300&#x02009;&#x003bc;m on a temporal bone model measured with a digital caliper [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51">51</xref>]. This result was confirmed by another study where a geometrical discrepancy of 150&#x02009;&#x003bc;m was observed between the model and the bone [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">43</xref>]. BJ and ME were reported to be less accurate methods. A geometrical discrepancy of 400&#x02009;&#x003bc;m was observed when using a BJ printer to print a skull base [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">43</xref>]. Most of the researches involving ME printers did not measure quantitatively the models&#x02019; accuracy, except in one case where they reported a discrepancy reaching 680&#x003bc;m [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47">47</xref>]. Our study did not retrieve any paper measuring the accuracy of VP printers, but was previously reported as being high [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>].</p><p id="Par61">The lack of quantitative evaluation of the printing accuracy was one of the major limitations of the studies included in this review. The accuracy is related to the printer, the radiological image segmentation process, the size of the printed object and the printing material. For example, a ME printer cannot reach the same precision as an VP or MJ printer due for first to the dimension of the nozzle, but its accuracy could be sufficient to reach the operator&#x02019;s purposes. Depending on the radiological images processing technique a 3D-printed model will always exhibit some discrepancies, the operator has to keep it in mind processing the radiological data.</p></sec><sec id="Sec24"><title>Haptic feedback</title><p id="Par62">A good haptic feedback is the most important characteristic of training models and it is strongly dependent on the mechanical characteristics of the printing material. The two fundamental parameters for a model that aims to reproduce the bone haptic feedback are adequate elastic modulus and tensile strength. No quantitative test is currently available to describe the surgeon&#x02019;s haptic feedback during a surgical intervention. Most of the authors created their own questionnaires and asked students and surgeons with different experience about their sensations. Thus, the results were difficult to compare as evaluation protocols were different and also because of the conclusions subjective. However, most of the them were satisfied with their printed models.</p><p id="Par63">The principal materials for ME printers were polylactic acid (PLA), ABS, polycarbonate (PC), polyethylene terephthalate glycol-modified (PETG) and nylon. In the articles included in this review, there was no consensus regarding the best material to reproduce the bone characteristics. One of the PLA&#x02019;s advantages was its biological properties, as it is known to be biodegradable and non-toxic. Moreover, its haptic feedback was similar to bone at low temperature while drilling [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref>]. Haffner et al., compared five different materials, and stated that PETG was the most realistic material, followed by PC, PLA and ABS. Nylon properties were considered as not realistic enough [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref>]. PC was blamed to melt too easily during drilling while ABS could easily reproduce the bone haptic feedback during a cortical mastoidectomy [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">43</xref>]. Favier et al. compared the mechanical characteristics of their models. With Young&#x02019;s Modulus respectively of 2000&#x02013;3000&#x02009;N/mm2 and 1700&#x02009;N/mm2, the MJ and PBF printed models were considered as realistic. Regarding PBF printing, Mori et al. reported that their model was realistic but the feeling of drilling the cancellous part of the bone model lacked the &#x02018;crispy touch&#x02019; of real bone [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR82">82</xref>]. This subjective declaration underlines the need for objective criteria to evaluate the haptic feedback of the models. Among all the materials used in the BJ printing technique, cyanoacrylate powder with hydroquinone resembled the most to sheep cortical bone, which was often used as a surgical training model [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR85">85</xref>].</p><p id="Par64">Unfortunately, no author did quantitative or comparative tests using models printed by VP. However most authors suggested that this technique was efficient for creating adequate models, enhancing the quality of the training [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref>] and suitable for planning complex surgeries [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>] or dental implant treatments [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>].</p><p id="Par65">The segmentation technique is also an important parameter that it has to be considered for obtaining realistic 3D printed models. Segmenting the trabecular bone structures results in a more realistic haptic feedback when compared to fully solid prints.</p></sec><sec id="Sec25"><title>Cost</title><p id="Par66">Cost remains an important parameter that cannot be ignored. There are multiple additional costs in terms of software, printers, printing materials, operators and training hours to produce an in-house 3DP model.</p><p id="Par67">In order to print a model, the first step is to process the DICOM file into an STL file. Among all the commercial software available, the commercial software package Mimics&#x000ae;, was the most widely used software, despite a relatively high cost when compared to others. Many free or open source software are available, like ITK-Snap&#x000ae;, Slicer&#x000ae; or InVesalius&#x000ae; [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR60">60</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR79">79</xref>]. OsiriX&#x000ae; possesses a free version (demo) that allows to export STL renderings [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46">46</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47">47</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR52">52</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR63">63</xref>].</p><p id="Par68">ME printers were the cheapest printers, with reported prices ranging between 2500$ and 3000$ [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47">47</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR82">82</xref>]. However, as previously mentioned, these showed limitations in terms of accuracy. PLA and ABS were the cheapest reported materials [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47">47</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR52">52</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR82">82</xref>]. PC cost was reported to range from 105$ to 155$ for the production of a mandible [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">43</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR57">57</xref>]. The cost for a temporal bone model using BJ was around 400$ [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR67">67</xref>]. MJ models costs ranged from 270$ to 1000$. One team affirmed that these models were too expensive [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR66">66</xref>], but two others suggested that they were satisfied by their investment in these models [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR56">56</xref>]. LS printers are not cheap, but no authors talked mentioned any price. Printing a skull base using polyamide with an LS printer was reported to cost 250&#x02013;280$ [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR85">85</xref>]. Two teams used VP printers and they declared being satisfied by the results [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref>]. A forgotten cost is related to the post-curing machine for object printed trough VP technologies.</p><p id="Par69">The production time can also be considered as a decisive cost. ME printers were the fastest, producing a pediatric temporal bone model in 4.5&#x02009;h and a mandible with a maxilla in 6&#x02009;h [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref>]. The production time of an MJ model was less than a day [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR56">56</xref>]. The time needed to design the STL file is also important to consider. Only one author discussed about the total production time of a LS printer, and reported a need for 4 to 5&#x02009;days [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">43</xref>]. The learning curve of a few months to master and to properly use the software for STL processing is obvious. In every case, the conversion from the DICOM to an adequate STL file could take several hours. One author reported that &#x0201c;the 3DP technique is really cost-effective, only if the operator plans to produce several models to amortize the cost of the 3D printer&#x0201d; [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR82">82</xref>].</p><p id="Par70">It&#x02019;s important to know these costs because the cost-benefit ratio has to be considered before investing in this technique that can get several advantages but it presents some drawbacks in comparison to traditional techniques [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR63">63</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR78">78</xref>].</p></sec><sec id="Sec26"><title>Suggestions</title><p id="Par71">As pre-surgical tools, 3D models can make the surgical outcomes more predictable and safer, reducing the surgeon&#x02019;s stress and the intervention time [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50">50</xref>]. Furthermore, they can strongly improve the quality of clinical education, allowing students to simulate various surgical interventions and to discuss easily about their clinical cases with their mentors [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">42</xref>].</p><p id="Par72">Evaluating the best image processing workflow remains difficult as no author described neither the entire workflow not the human cost involved. The most used training models are made with ME printers. This technology is the cheapest and allows producing suitable training models, despite their limited accuracy. The most appropriate ME printing materials are ABS, PLA and PETG [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">43</xref>]. Temporal bone models printed with PETG were reported to ensure adequate haptic feedback whileperfor drilling, and they were very helpful during training sessions [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref>].</p><p id="Par73">To obtain an adequate simulation model, BJ and VP printers seem more indicated. They showed adequate performances in reproducing training models of the maxilla and their accuracy is really satisfying for creating planning models [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>]. It is also possible to create models for simulating surgeries, thanks to their good haptic feedback [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>]. Also MJ printers allow to produce models that provide good haptic feedback and that can be used to simulate complex surgeries before entering the operating room [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>]. Generally, they cost more than the VP ones, as well as the BJ ones [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR61">61</xref>]. PBF printers allow to produce accurate bone models in polyamide and glass fiber, but without satisfying haptic feedback [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR82">82</xref>].</p><p id="Par74">Printing time and cost are very variable, depending directly on the type of 3D printer, the printing material, the accuracy and the mechanical characteristics required. Figure&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref> demonstrates the main differences among the analyzed 3D printing technologies, depending on the applications.
<fig id="Fig5"><label>Fig. 5</label><caption><p>Advantages (green) and limitations (red) of different 3D printing technology to create 3D anatomical models. These characteristics lead the choice for the best 3D printer technique for every clinical or academical purpose</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41205_2020_82_Fig5_HTML" id="MO5"/></fig></p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec27"><title>Conclusions</title><p id="Par75">The present literature review showed that nowadays, AM models are useful tools in the surgical field.</p><p id="Par76">Several parameters must be considered before choosing a 3D printing model workflow, such as the processing software, the type of 3D printer, the expected mechanical characteristics, accuracy and haptic feedback of the printing material, the production time and the human and material costs.</p><p id="Par77">Due to the large amount of different parameters that has to be considered by the operator, the financial investment in a 3D printer should be made with the precise idea of the final application.</p><sec id="Sec28"><title>Limitations</title><p id="Par78">This analysis was at first limited by the diversity of workflows and applications, involving different materials, printers and testing methods. Despite difficulties for comparing results from a study to another, some common protocols were found for the 3 main purposes of 3D-printed bone models (planning, simulation and training).</p><p id="Par79">The lack of common reliable qualitative tests to evaluate the models was an evident limitation, thus future studies should focus on standardized methods to evaluate 3D-printed models of bone macro- and micro-structures.</p></sec></sec></body><back><glossary><title>Abbreviations</title><def-list><def-item><term>3D</term><def><p id="Par6">Three-dimensional</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>3DP</term><def><p id="Par7">Three-dimensional printed; Three-dimensional printing</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>ABS</term><def><p id="Par8">Acrylonitrile butadiene styrene</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>AM</term><def><p id="Par9">Additive manufacturing</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>BJ</term><def><p id="Par10">Binder jetting</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>CAD/CAM</term><def><p id="Par11">Computer-aided design/computer-aided manufacturing</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>CBCT</term><def><p id="Par12">Cone beam computed tomography</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>CT</term><def><p id="Par13">Computed tomography</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>DICOM</term><def><p id="Par14">Digital imaging and communications in medicine</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>ENT</term><def><p id="Par15">Ear, nose and throat</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>ME</term><def><p id="Par16">Material extrusion</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>MJ</term><def><p id="Par17">Material jetting</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>MRI</term><def><p id="Par18">Magnetic resonance imaging</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>PBF</term><def><p id="Par19">Powder bed fusion</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>PC</term><def><p id="Par20">Polycarbonate</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>PETG</term><def><p id="Par21">Polyethylene terephthalate glycol-modified</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>PLA</term><def><p id="Par22">Polylactic acid</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>STL</term><def><p id="Par23">Standard triangulation language</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>VP</term><def><p id="Par24">Vat photopolymerization</p></def></def-item></def-list></glossary><fn-group><fn><p><bold>Publisher&#x02019;s Note</bold></p><p>Springer Nature remains neutral with regard to jurisdictional claims in published maps and institutional affiliations.</p></fn></fn-group><ack><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>None.</p></ack><notes notes-type="author-contribution"><title>Authors&#x02019; contributions</title><p>All the authors contributed equally to this manuscript. They worked together to design this study, to analyze the data and to write the manuscript. All authors read and approved the final manuscript.</p></notes><notes notes-type="funding-information"><title>Funding</title><p>This work was funded by &#x0201c;Agence Nationale de la Recherche&#x0201d; (ANR-16-CE18-0009-01).&#x000a0;</p></notes><notes notes-type="data-availability"><title>Availability of data and materials</title><p>All data generated or analyzed during this study are included in this published article [and its supplementary information files].</p></notes><notes id="FPar1"><title>Ethics approval and consent to participate</title><p id="Par80">Not applicable.</p></notes><notes id="FPar2"><title>Consent for publication</title><p id="Par81">Not applicable.</p></notes><notes id="FPar3" notes-type="COI-statement"><title>Competing interests</title><p id="Par82">The authors declare that they have no competing interests.</p></notes><ref-list id="Bib1"><title>References</title><ref id="CR1"><label>1.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Naveau</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Bou</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Sharma</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Evolution of Topics in Maxillofacial Prosthetics Publications</article-title><source>Int J Prosthodont</source><year>2018</year><volume>31</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>565</fpage><lpage>568</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.11607/ijp.5894</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30192349</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR2"><label>2.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">ASTM International. Standard Terminology for Additive Manufacturing Technologies 1,2. 2013:2&#x02013;4. doi:10.1520/F2792-12A.2.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR3"><label>3.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>D&#x02019;Haese</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Ackhurst</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Wismejier</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Current state of the art of computer-guided implant surgery</article-title><source>Periodontology 2000</source><year>2017</year><volume>73</volume><issue>25</issue><fpage>121</fpage><lpage>133</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/prd.12175</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28000275</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR4"><label>4.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>HH</given-names></name><name><surname>Lonic</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Lo</surname><given-names>LJ</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>3D printing in orthognathic surgery &#x02212; a literature review</article-title><source>J Formos Med Assoc</source><year>2018</year><volume>117</volume><issue>7</issue><fpage>547</fpage><lpage>558</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jfma.2018.01.008</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29398097</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR5"><label>5.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Gonzalez-perez-somarriba B, Centeno G, Vallellano C et al.. Evaluation of total alloplastic temporo-mandibular joint replacement with two different types of prostheses : A three-year prospective study. 2016;21(6). doi:10.4317/medoral.21189.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR6"><label>6.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Charles Champeaux, Sebastien Froelich and Caudron Y. Titanium Three-Dimensional Printed Cranioplasty for Fronto-Nasal Bone Defect 2019;30(6):1802&#x02013;1805. doi:10.1097/SCS.0000000000005493.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR7"><label>7.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Park JY, Gao G, Jang J, Cho D. 3D printed structures for delivery of biomolecules and cells: tissue repair and regeneration. J Mater Chem B. 2016. 10.1039/C6TB01662F.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR8"><label>8.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Crafts</surname><given-names>TD</given-names></name><name><surname>Ellsperman</surname><given-names>SE</given-names></name><name><surname>Wannemuehler</surname><given-names>TJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Bellicchi</surname><given-names>TD</given-names></name><name><surname>Shipchandler</surname><given-names>TZ</given-names></name><name><surname>Mantravadi</surname><given-names>AV</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Three-Dimensional Printing and Its Applications in Otorhinolaryngology</article-title><source>Head Neck Surg</source><year>2017</year><volume>156</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>999</fpage><lpage>1010</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0194599816678372</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR9"><label>9.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hsieh</surname><given-names>TY</given-names></name><name><surname>Cervenka</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Dedhia</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Strong</surname><given-names>EB</given-names></name><name><surname>Steele</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Assessment of a patient-specific, 3-dimensionally printed endoscopic sinus and skull base surgical model</article-title><source>JAMA Otolaryngol - Head Neck Surg</source><year>2018</year><volume>144</volume><issue>7</issue><fpage>574</fpage><lpage>579</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/jamaoto.2018.0473</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29799965</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR10"><label>10.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Probst</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Stump</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Mokosch</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>R&#x000f6;&#x000f6;sli</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Evaluation of an infant temporal-Bone model as training tool</article-title><source>Otol Neurotol.</source><year>2018</year><volume>39</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>e448</fpage><lpage>e452</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/MAO.0000000000001839</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29889782</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR11"><label>11.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Takahashi</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Morita</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Ohshima</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Izumi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Kubota</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Yamamoto</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Takahashi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Horii</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Creating an optimal 3D printed model for temporal Bone dissection training</article-title><source>Ann Otol Rhinol Laryngol.</source><year>2017</year><volume>126</volume><issue>7</issue><fpage>530</fpage><lpage>536</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0003489417705395</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28420248</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR12"><label>12.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Somji</surname><given-names>SH</given-names></name><name><surname>Valladares</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Ho Kim</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Cheng Paul Yu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Froum</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The use of 3D models to improve sinus augmentation outcomes - a case report</article-title><source>Singap Dent J</source><year>2017</year><volume>38</volume><fpage>63</fpage><lpage>70</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.sdj.2017.10.002</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR13"><label>13.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Marconi S, Pugliese L, Botti M, et al. Value of 3D printing for the comprehension of surgical anatomy. Surg Endosc. 2017. 10.1007/s00464-017-5457-5.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR14"><label>14.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Xiao</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The application of 3D printing Technology for Simultaneous Orthognathic Surgery and Mandibular Contour Osteoplasty in the treatment of craniofacial deformities</article-title><source>Aesthet Plast Surg</source><year>2017</year><volume>41</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>1413</fpage><lpage>1424</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00266-017-0914-z</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR15"><label>15.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Arce K, Waris S, Alexander AE, Ettinger KS. Novel patient-specific 3D printed fixation tray for mandibular reconstruction with fibular free flaps. J Oral Maxillofac Surg. 2018. 10.1016/j.joms.2018.04.028.This.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR16"><label>16.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chou</surname><given-names>PY</given-names></name><name><surname>Hallac</surname><given-names>RR</given-names></name><name><surname>Shih</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>3D-printed models of cleft lip and palate for surgical training and patient education</article-title><source>Cleft Palate-Craniofacial J</source><year>2018</year><volume>55</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>323</fpage><lpage>327</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/1055665617738998</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR17"><label>17.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lim</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Campbell</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Cook</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Erasmus</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A case series of rapid prototyping and intraoperative imaging in orbital reconstruction</article-title><source>Craniomaxillofacial Trauma Reconstr</source><year>2015</year><volume>08</volume><issue>02</issue><fpage>105</fpage><lpage>110</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1055/s-0034-1395384</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR18"><label>18.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yusa</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Yamanochi</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Takagi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Iino</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Three-dimensional printing model as a tool to assist in surgery for large mandibular tumour: a case report</article-title><source>J Oral Maxillofac Res</source><year>2017</year><volume>8</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>7</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5037/jomr.2017.8204</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR19"><label>19.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Gargiulo P, Arnadottir I, Gislason M, Edmunds K, Olafsson I. New directions in 3D medical modeling: 3D-printing anatomy and functions in neurosurgical planning. J Healthc Eng. 2017;2017. 10.1155/2017/1439643/.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR20"><label>20.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Critical Appraisal Skills Programme (2018). CASP Qualitative Checklist. [online] Available at: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://casp-uk.net/wp-content/uploads/2018/01/CASP-Qualitative-Checklist-2018.pdf">https://casp-uk.net/wp-content/uploads/2018/01/CASP-Qualitative-Checklist-2018.pdf</ext-link>. Accessed: 20/11/2018. 1994;(2018).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR21"><label>21.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">EndNote X9, Clarivate Analytics, Web of Science. Philadelphia; Clarivate. 2013(64).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR22"><label>22.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>He</surname><given-names>LH</given-names></name><name><surname>Purton</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Swain</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A novel polymer infiltrated ceramic for dental simulation</article-title><source>J Mater Sci Mater Med.</source><year>2011</year><volume>22</volume><issue>7</issue><fpage>1639</fpage><lpage>1643</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10856-011-4350-3</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21614593</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR23"><label>23.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>He</surname><given-names>LH</given-names></name><name><surname>Foster Page</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Purton</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>An evaluation of dental operative simulation materials</article-title><source>Dent Mater J</source><year>2012</year><volume>31</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>645</fpage><lpage>649</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4012/dmj.2011-264</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22864219</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR24"><label>24.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>G&#x000fc;th</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name><name><surname>Ponn</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Mast</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Gernet</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Edelhoff</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Description and evaluation of a new approach on pre-clinical implant dentistry education based on an innovative simulation model</article-title><source>Eur J Dent Educ</source><year>2010</year><volume>14</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>221</fpage><lpage>226</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1600-0579.2009.00614.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20946250</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR25"><label>25.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hiraumi</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Sato</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Ito</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Papercraft temporal bone in the first step of anatomy education</article-title><source>Auris Nasus Larynx</source><year>2017</year><volume>44</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>277</fpage><lpage>281</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.anl.2016.07.017</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27544628</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR26"><label>26.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chang</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name><name><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>RP</given-names></name><name><surname>Bowe</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Fabrication and validation of a low-cost, medium-fidelity silicone injection molded endoscopic sinus surgery simulation model</article-title><source>Laryngoscope.</source><year>2017</year><volume>127</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>781</fpage><lpage>786</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/lary.26370</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28000224</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR27"><label>27.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>MY</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>JQ</given-names></name><name><surname>Shi</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Printed three-dimensional anatomic templates for virtual preoperative planning before reconstruction of old pelvic injuries</article-title><source>Chin Med J</source><year>2015</year><volume>128</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>477</fpage><lpage>482</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4103/0366-6999.151088</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25673449</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR28"><label>28.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Brouwers</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Teutelink</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>van Tilborg</surname><given-names>FAJB</given-names></name><name><surname>de Jongh</surname><given-names>MAC</given-names></name><name><surname>Lansink</surname><given-names>KWW</given-names></name><name><surname>Bemelman</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Validation study of 3D-printed anatomical models using 2 PLA printers for preoperative planning in trauma surgery, a human cadaver study</article-title><source>Eur J Trauma Emerg Surg</source><year>2018</year><volume>0</volume><issue>0</issue><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>8</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00068-018-0970-3</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR29"><label>29.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Athanasiou</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></name><name><surname>Verstraete</surname><given-names>FJM</given-names></name><name><surname>Winer</surname><given-names>JN</given-names></name><name><surname>Cissell</surname><given-names>DD</given-names></name><name><surname>Arzi</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Lucero</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The application of 3-dimensional printing for preoperative planning in oral and maxillofacial surgery in dogs and cats</article-title><source>Vet Surg</source><year>2017</year><volume>46</volume><issue>7</issue><fpage>942</fpage><lpage>951</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/vsu.12683</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28688157</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR30"><label>30.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lanis</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Alvarez del Canto</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Barriga</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Polido</surname><given-names>WD</given-names></name><name><surname>Morton</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Computer-guided implant surgery and full-arch immediate loading with prefabricated-metal framework-provisional prosthesis created from a 3D printed model</article-title><source>J Esthet Restor Dent</source><year>2019</year><volume>31</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>199</fpage><lpage>208</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/jerd.12458</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30790431</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR31"><label>31.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Freiser</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name><name><surname>Ghodadra</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Hirsch</surname><given-names>BE</given-names></name><name><surname>AA</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Evaluation of 3D Printed Temporal Bone Models in Preparation for Middle Cranial Fossa Surgery</article-title><source>Otol Neurotol</source><year>2019</year><volume>40</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>246</fpage><lpage>253</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/MAO.0000000000002073</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30624410</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR32"><label>32.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Zhuo C, Lei L, Yulin Z, et al. Creation and validation of three-dimensional printed models for basic nasal endoscopic training. Int Forum Allergy Rhinol. 2019;00(0):1&#x02013;7. doi:10.1002/alr.22306.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR33"><label>33.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bhadra</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Shah</surname><given-names>NC</given-names></name><name><surname>Arora</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Meetkumar</surname><given-names>SD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Deducing a surgical dilemma using a novel three Dimensionaldimensional printing technique Dhaval</article-title><source>J Conserv Dent</source><year>2018</year><volume>21</volume><fpage>582</fpage><lpage>585</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4103/JCD.JCD</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30294126</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR34"><label>34.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Using three-dimensional printing to create individualized cranial nerve models for Skull Base tumor surgery</article-title><source>World Neurosurg.</source><year>2018</year><volume>120</volume><fpage>e142</fpage><lpage>e152</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.wneu.2018.07.236</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30121411</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR35"><label>35.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Reymus</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Fotiadou</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Hickel</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Diegritz</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>3D-printed model for hands-on training in dental traumatology</article-title><source>Int Endod J</source><year>2018</year><volume>51</volume><issue>11</issue><fpage>1313</fpage><lpage>1319</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/iej.12947</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29729097</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR36"><label>36.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Sugahara K, Takano M, Koyama Y, et al. Novel condylar repositioning method for 3D-printed models. Maxillofac Plast Reconstr Surg 2018;40(1):0&#x02013;4. doi:10.1186/s40902-018-0143-7.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR37"><label>37.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Werz</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name><name><surname>Zeichner</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Berg</surname><given-names>BI</given-names></name><name><surname>Zeilhofer</surname><given-names>HF</given-names></name><name><surname>Thieringer</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>3D printed surgical simulation models as educational tool by maxillofacial surgeons</article-title><source>Eur J Dent Educ</source><year>2018</year><volume>22</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>e500</fpage><lpage>e505</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/eje.12332</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29479802</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR38"><label>38.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>WJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>A novel three-dimensional-printed paranasal sinus&#x02013;skull base anatomical model</article-title><source>Eur Arch Oto-Rhino-Laryngol</source><year>2018</year><volume>275</volume><issue>8</issue><fpage>2045</fpage><lpage>2049</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00405-018-5051-z</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR39"><label>39.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Haffner</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Quinn</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Hsieh</surname><given-names>TY</given-names></name><name><surname>Strong</surname><given-names>EB</given-names></name><name><surname>Steele</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Optimization of 3D print material for the recreation of patient-specific temporal Bone models</article-title><source>Ann Otol Rhinol Laryngol.</source><year>2018</year><volume>127</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>338</fpage><lpage>343</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0003489418764987</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29667491</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR40"><label>40.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jacek</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Rados&#x00142;aw</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Wies&#x00142;aw</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>3D printed models in mandibular reconstruction with bony free flaps</article-title><source>J Mater Sci Mater Med</source><year>2018</year><volume>29</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>10</fpage><lpage>15</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10856-018-6029-5</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR41"><label>41.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Alodadi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Utilizing three-dimensional printing in treating challenged dental implant cases</article-title><source>World J Dent</source><year>2018</year><volume>9</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>235</fpage><lpage>241</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5005/jp-journals-10015-1540</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR42"><label>42.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Reddy</surname><given-names>GV</given-names></name><name><surname>Vasamsetty</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Kumar Malyala</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Alwala</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Training young maxillofacial surgeons or trainees using additive manufacturing</article-title><source>Mater Today Proc</source><year>2018</year><volume>5</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>4046</fpage><lpage>4049</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.matpr.2017.11.665</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR43"><label>43.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Favier</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Zemiti</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Mora</surname><given-names>OC</given-names></name><name><surname>Subsol</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Captier</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Lebrun</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Crampette</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Mondaine</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Gilles</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Geometric and mechanical evaluation of 3D-printing materials for skull base anatomical education and endoscopic surgery simulation - A first step to create reliable customized simulators</article-title><source>PLoS One</source><year>2017</year><volume>12</volume><issue>12</issue><fpage>e0189486</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0189486</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29252993</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR44"><label>44.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Alrasheed</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name><name><surname>Nguyen</surname><given-names>LHP</given-names></name><name><surname>Mongeau</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Funnell</surname><given-names>WRJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Tewfik</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Development and validation of a 3D-printed model of the ostiomeatal complex and frontal sinus for endoscopic sinus surgery training</article-title><source>Int Forum Allergy Rhinol</source><year>2017</year><volume>7</volume><issue>8</issue><fpage>837</fpage><lpage>841</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/alr.21960</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28614638</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR45"><label>45.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Ye</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Hao</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Comparison of two three-dimensional printed models of complex intracranial aneurysms for surgical simulation</article-title><source>World Neurosurg.</source><year>2017</year><volume>103</volume><fpage>671</fpage><lpage>679</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.wneu.2017.04.098</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28450234</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR46"><label>46.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Javan</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Davidson</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Javan</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Nerves of steel: a low-cost method for 3D printing the cranial nerves</article-title><source>J Digit Imaging</source><year>2017</year><volume>30</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>576</fpage><lpage>583</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10278-017-9951-z</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28224379</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR47"><label>47.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Legocki</surname><given-names>AT</given-names></name><name><surname>Duffy-Peter</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Scott</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Benefits and limitations of entry-level 3-dimensional printing of maxillofacial skeletal models</article-title><source>JAMA Otolaryngol - Head Neck Surg.</source><year>2017</year><volume>143</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>389</fpage><lpage>394</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/jamaoto.2016.3673</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28056140</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR48"><label>48.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Ghizoni E, Ph D, Paulo J, et al. 3D-printed Craniosynostosis model: a new simulation surgical tool. World Neurosurg. 2017. 10.1016/j.wneu.2017.10.025.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR49"><label>49.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wiedermann</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name><name><surname>Joshi</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name><name><surname>Jamshidi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Conchenour</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Preciado</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Utilization of a submental island flap and 3D printed model for skull base reconstruction: infantile giant cranio-cervicofacial teratoma</article-title><source>Int J Pediatr Otorhinolaryngol</source><year>2017</year><volume>92</volume><fpage>143</fpage><lpage>145</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ijporl.2016.11.014</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28012516</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR50"><label>50.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jacobo</surname><given-names>OM</given-names></name><name><surname>Giachero</surname><given-names>VE</given-names></name><name><surname>Hartwig</surname><given-names>DK</given-names></name><name><surname>Mantrana</surname><given-names>GA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Three-dimensional printing modeling: application in maxillofacial and hand fractures and resident training</article-title><source>Eur J Plast Surg</source><year>2018</year><volume>41</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>137</fpage><lpage>146</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00238-017-1373-0</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR51"><label>51.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wanibuchi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Noshiro</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Sugino</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Training for Skull Base surgery with a colored temporal Bone model created by three-dimensional printing technology</article-title><source>World Neurosurg.</source><year>2016</year><volume>91</volume><fpage>66</fpage><lpage>72</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.wneu.2016.03.084</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27062915</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR52"><label>52.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bone</surname><given-names>TM</given-names></name><name><surname>Mowry</surname><given-names>SE</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Content validity of temporal Bone models printed via inexpensive methods and materials</article-title><source>Otol Neurotol.</source><year>2016</year><volume>37</volume><issue>8</issue><fpage>1183</fpage><lpage>1188</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/MAO.0000000000001131</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27362738</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR53"><label>53.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Florentino</surname><given-names>VGB</given-names></name><name><surname>De Mendon&#x000e7;a</surname><given-names>DS</given-names></name><name><surname>Bezerra</surname><given-names>AV</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Reconstruction of frontal bone with custom-made prosthesis using rapid prototyping</article-title><source>J Craniofac Surg.</source><year>2016</year><volume>27</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>e354</fpage><lpage>e356</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/SCS.0000000000002627</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27285896</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR54"><label>54.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kondo</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Harada</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Masuda</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>A neurosurgical simulation of skull base tumors using a 3D printed rapid prototyping model containing mesh structures</article-title><source>Acta Neurochir</source><year>2016</year><volume>158</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>1213</fpage><lpage>1219</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00701-016-2781-9</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27052513</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR55"><label>55.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lim</surname><given-names>SH</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>YH</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>MK</given-names></name><name><surname>Nam</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Kang</surname><given-names>SH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Validation of a fibula graft cutting guide for mandibular reconstruction: experiment with rapid prototyping mandible model</article-title><source>Comput Assist Surg</source><year>2016</year><volume>21</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>9</fpage><lpage>17</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3109/24699322.2016.1167245</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR56"><label>56.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pacione</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Tanweer</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Berman</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Harter</surname><given-names>DH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The utility of a multimaterial 3D printed model for surgical planning of complex deformity of the skull base and craniovertebral junction</article-title><source>J Neurosurg</source><year>2016</year><volume>125</volume><issue>November</issue><fpage>1194</fpage><lpage>1197</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3171/2015.12.jns151936</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26943848</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR57"><label>57.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chan</surname><given-names>HHL</given-names></name><name><surname>Siewerdsen</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name><name><surname>Vescan</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Daly</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Prisman</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Irish</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>3D rapid prototyping for otolaryngology-head and neck surgery: applications in image-guidance, surgical simulation and patient-specific modeling</article-title><source>PLoS One</source><year>2015</year><volume>10</volume><issue>9</issue><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>18</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0136370</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR58"><label>58.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dickinson</surname><given-names>KJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Matsumoto</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Cassivi</surname><given-names>SD</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Individualizing Management of Complex Esophageal Pathology Using Three-Dimensional Printed Models</article-title><source>Ann Thorac Surg</source><year>2015</year><volume>100</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>692</fpage><lpage>697</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.athoracsur.2015.03.115</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26234839</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR59"><label>59.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hochman</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></name><name><surname>Rhodes</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Wong</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Kraut</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Pisa</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Unger</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Comparison of cadaveric and isomorphic three-dimensional printed models in temporal bone education</article-title><source>Laryngoscope.</source><year>2015</year><volume>125</volume><issue>10</issue><fpage>2353</fpage><lpage>2357</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/lary.24919</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26256951</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR60"><label>60.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cohen</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Reyes</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Creation of a 3D printed temporal bone model from clinical CT data</article-title><source>Am J Otolaryngol - Head Neck Med Surg</source><year>2015</year><volume>36</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>619</fpage><lpage>624</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.amjoto.2015.02.012</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR61"><label>61.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rose</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name><name><surname>Webster</surname><given-names>CE</given-names></name><name><surname>Harrysson</surname><given-names>OLA</given-names></name><name><surname>Formeister</surname><given-names>EJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Rawal</surname><given-names>RB</given-names></name><name><surname>Iseli</surname><given-names>CE</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Pre-operative simulation of pediatric mastoid surgery with 3D-printed temporal bone models</article-title><source>Int J Pediatr Otorhinolaryngol</source><year>2015</year><volume>79</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>740</fpage><lpage>744</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ijporl.2015.03.004</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25794654</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR62"><label>62.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ernoult</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Bouletreau</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Meyer</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Aubry</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Breton</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Bachelet</surname><given-names>JT</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Reconstruction assist&#x000e9;e par l&#x02019;impression 3D en chirurgie maxillofaciale</article-title><source>Rev Stomatol Chir Maxillofac Chir Orale</source><year>2015</year><volume>116</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>95</fpage><lpage>102</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.revsto.2015.01.010</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25742704</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR63"><label>63.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mowry</surname><given-names>SE</given-names></name><name><surname>Jammal</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Myer</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Solares</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name><name><surname>Weinberger</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A novel temporal bone simulation model using 3D printing techniques</article-title><source>Otol Neurotol</source><year>2015</year><volume>36</volume><issue>9</issue><fpage>1562</fpage><lpage>1565</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/MAO.0000000000000848</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26375979</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR64"><label>64.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hochman</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></name><name><surname>Rhodes</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Kraut</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Pisa</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Unger</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>End user comparison of anatomically matched 3-dimensional printed and virtual haptic temporal Bone simulation: a pilot study</article-title><source>Otolaryngol - Head Neck Surg (United States)</source><year>2015</year><volume>153</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>263</fpage><lpage>268</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0194599815586756</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR65"><label>65.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Longfield</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></name><name><surname>Brickman</surname><given-names>TM</given-names></name><name><surname>Jeyakumar</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>3D printed pediatric temporal Bone</article-title><source>Otol Neurotol.</source><year>2015</year><volume>36</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>793</fpage><lpage>795</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/mao.0000000000000750</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25839977</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR66"><label>66.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rose</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name><name><surname>Kimbell</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name><name><surname>Webster</surname><given-names>CE</given-names></name><name><surname>Harrysson</surname><given-names>OLA</given-names></name><name><surname>Formeister</surname><given-names>EJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Buchman</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Multi-material 3D models for temporal bone surgical simulation</article-title><source>Ann Otol Rhinol Laryngol</source><year>2015</year><volume>124</volume><issue>7</issue><fpage>528</fpage><lpage>536</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0003489415570937</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25662026</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR67"><label>67.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hochman</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></name><name><surname>Kraut</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Kazmerik</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Unger</surname><given-names>BJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Generation of a 3D printed temporal bone model with internal fidelity and validation of the mechanical construct</article-title><source>Otolaryngol - Head Neck Surg (United States).</source><year>2014</year><volume>150</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>448</fpage><lpage>454</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0194599813518008</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR68"><label>68.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chenebaux</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Lescanne</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Robier</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Bakhos</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Evaluation of a temporal bone prototype by experts in otology</article-title><source>J Laryngol Otol</source><year>2014</year><volume>128</volume><issue>7</issue><fpage>586</fpage><lpage>590</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1017/S0022215114001297</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24932528</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR69"><label>69.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Narayanan</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Narayanan</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Rajagopalan</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Endoscopic skull base training using 3D printed models with pre-existing pathology</article-title><source>Eur Arch Oto-Rhino-Laryngology.</source><year>2015</year><volume>272</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>753</fpage><lpage>757</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00405-014-3300-3</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR70"><label>70.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cui</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Guan</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Ye</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Surgical planning, three-dimensional model surgery and preshaped implants in treatment of bilateral craniomaxillofacial post-traumatic deformities</article-title><source>J Oral Maxillofac Surg</source><year>2014</year><volume>72</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>1138.e1</fpage><lpage>1138.e14</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.joms.2014.02.023</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24679954</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR71"><label>71.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gil</surname><given-names>RS</given-names></name><name><surname>Roig</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>Obispo</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name><name><surname>Morla</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Pag&#x000e8;s</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name><name><surname>Perez</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Surgical planning and microvascular reconstruction of the mandible with a fibular flap using computer-aided design, rapid prototype modelling, and precontoured titanium reconstruction plates: a prospective study</article-title><source>Br J Oral Maxillofac Surg</source><year>2015</year><volume>53</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>49</fpage><lpage>53</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.bjoms.2014.09.015</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25305795</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR72"><label>72.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jardini</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name><name><surname>Larosa</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Filho</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Cranial reconstruction: 3D biomodel and custom-built implant created using additive manufacturing</article-title><source>J Cranio-Maxillofacial Surg</source><year>2014</year><volume>42</volume><issue>8</issue><fpage>1877</fpage><lpage>1884</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jcms.2014.07.006</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR73"><label>73.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jabbour</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Chalouhi</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Simulation-based neurosurgical training for the presigmoid approach with a physical model</article-title><source>Neurosurgery.</source><year>2013</year><volume>73</volume><issue>SUPPL. 4</issue><fpage>2011</fpage><lpage>2014</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1227/NEU.0000000000000090</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR74"><label>74.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Digital design and individually fabricated titanium implants for the reconstruction of traumatic zygomatico-orbital defects</article-title><source>J Craniofac Surg</source><year>2013</year><volume>24</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>363</fpage><lpage>368</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/SCS.0b013e3182701243</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23524694</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR75"><label>75.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ciocca</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Mazzoni</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Fantini</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Persiani</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Marchetti</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Scotti</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>CAD/CAM guided secondary mandibular reconstruction of a discontinuity defect after ablative cancer surgery</article-title><source>J Cranio-Maxillofacial Surg.</source><year>2012</year><volume>40</volume><issue>8</issue><fpage>e511</fpage><lpage>e515</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jcms.2012.03.015</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR76"><label>76.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mori</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Yamamoto</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Nakao</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Esaki</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Surgical simulation of cerebral revascularization via skull base approaches in the posterior circulation using three-dimensional skull model with artificial brain and blood vessels</article-title><source>Neurol Med Chir (Tokyo)</source><year>2011</year><volume>51</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>93</fpage><lpage>96</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2176/nmc.51.93</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21358148</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR77"><label>77.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Morrison</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name><name><surname>Guy</surname><given-names>DT</given-names></name><name><surname>Day</surname><given-names>RE</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>GYF</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Simultaneous repair of two large cranial defects using rapid prototyping and custom computer-designed titanium plates: a case report</article-title><source>Proc Inst Mech Eng Part H J Eng Med</source><year>2011</year><volume>225</volume><issue>11</issue><fpage>1108</fpage><lpage>1112</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0954411911422766</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR78"><label>78.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nikzad</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Azari</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Ghassemzadeh</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Modified flapless dental implant surgery for planning treatment in a maxilla including sinus lift augmentation through use of virtual surgical planning and a 3-dimensional model</article-title><source>J Oral Maxillofac Surg</source><year>2010</year><volume>68</volume><issue>9</issue><fpage>2291</fpage><lpage>2298</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.joms.2010.02.002</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20576335</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR79"><label>79.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Katatny</surname><given-names>IE</given-names></name><name><surname>Masood</surname><given-names>SH</given-names></name><name><surname>Morsi</surname><given-names>YS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Evaluation and Validation of the Shape Accuracy of FDM Fabricated Medical Models</article-title><source>Adv Mater Res</source><year>2009</year><volume>83&#x02013;86</volume><fpage>275</fpage><lpage>280</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4028/www.scientific.net/amr.83-86.275</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR80"><label>80.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lambrecht</surname><given-names>JTH</given-names></name><name><surname>Berndt</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Christensen</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>Zehnder</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Haptic model fabrication for undergraduate and postgraduate teaching</article-title><source>Int J Oral Maxillofac Surg</source><year>2010</year><volume>39</volume><issue>12</issue><fpage>1226</fpage><lpage>1229</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ijom.2010.07.014</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20851573</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR81"><label>81.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sohmura</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Kusumoto</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Otani</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Yamada</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Wakabayashi</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Yatani</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>CAD/CAM fabrication and clinical application of surgical template and bone model in oral implant surgery</article-title><source>Clin Oral Implants Res</source><year>2009</year><volume>20</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>87</fpage><lpage>93</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1600-0501.2008.01588.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19126112</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR82"><label>82.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mori</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Dissectable modified three-dimensional temporal bone and whole skull base models for training in skull base approaches</article-title><source>Skull Base</source><year>2009</year><volume>19</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>333</fpage><lpage>343</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1055/s-0029-1224862</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20190943</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR83"><label>83.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Radley</surname><given-names>GJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Sama</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Watson</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Harris</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Characterization, quantification, and replication of human sinus bone for surgery simulation phantoms</article-title><source>Proc Inst Mech Eng Part H J Eng Med.</source><year>2009</year><volume>223</volume><issue>7</issue><fpage>875</fpage><lpage>887</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1243/09544119JEIM577</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR84"><label>84.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cohen</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Laviv</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Berman</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Nashef</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Abu-Tair</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Mandibular reconstruction using stereolithographic 3-dimensional printing modeling technology</article-title><source>Oral Surg Oral Med Oral Pathol Oral Radiol Endodontol</source><year>2009</year><volume>108</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>661</fpage><lpage>666</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.tripleo.2009.05.023</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR85"><label>85.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Suzuki</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Hagiwara</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Ogawa</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Ono</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Rapid-prototyped temporal bone and inner-ear models replicated by adjusting computed tomography thresholds</article-title><source>J Laryngol Otol</source><year>2007</year><volume>121</volume><issue>11</issue><fpage>1025</fpage><lpage>1028</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1017/S0022215107006706</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17381895</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR86"><label>86.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Mavili ME, Canter HI, Saglam-Aydinatay B, et al. Use of three-dimensional medical modeling methods for the precise planning of orthognathic surgery. J Craniofacial Surg. 18(4):740&#x02013;7. 10.4103/JCD.JCD_133_18.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR87"><label>87.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Suzuki</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Ogawa</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Kawano</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Hagiwara</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Yamaguchi</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Ono</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Rapid prototyping of temporal bone for surgical training and medical education</article-title><source>Acta Otolaryngol</source><year>2004</year><volume>124</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>400</fpage><lpage>402</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/00016480410016478</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15224862</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR88"><label>88.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>M&#x000fc;ller</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Krishnan</surname><given-names>KG</given-names></name><name><surname>Uhl</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Mast</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The application of rapid prototyping techniques in cranial reconstruction and preoperative planning in neurosurgery</article-title><source>J Craniofac Surg.</source><year>2003</year><volume>14</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>98</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/00001665-200311000-00014</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR89"><label>89.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>L&#x000f6;pp&#x000f6;nen</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Holma</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Sorri</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Computed tomography data based rapid prototyping model of the temporal bone before cochlear implant surgery</article-title><source>Acta Oto-Laryngologica, Suppl</source><year>1997</year><volume>6489</volume><issue>529</issue><fpage>47</fpage><lpage>49</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3109/00016489709124077</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>