<!DOCTYPE article
PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.2 20190208//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-mathml3.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">3 Biotech</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">3 Biotech</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>3 Biotech</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">2190-572X</issn><issn pub-type="epub">2190-5738</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Springer International Publishing</publisher-name><publisher-loc>Cham</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">32864286</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">7441129</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">2387</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s13205-020-02387-y</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Original Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Characterization of methicillin-resistant <italic>Staphylococcus aureus</italic> through genomics approach</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0001-9430-4643</contrib-id><name><surname>Naorem</surname><given-names>Romen Singh</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Urban</surname><given-names>Peter</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Goswami</surname><given-names>Gunajit</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-6562-6106</contrib-id><name><surname>Fekete</surname><given-names>Csaba</given-names></name><address><email>fekete@gamma.ttk.pte.hu</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><aff id="Aff1"><label>1</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.9679.1</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0001 0663 9479</institution-id><institution>Department of General and Environmental Microbiology, Institute of Biology, </institution><institution>University of P&#x000e9;cs, </institution></institution-wrap>P&#x000e9;cs, 7624 Hungary </aff><aff id="Aff2"><label>2</label>Microbial Biotechnology Research Group, Szent&#x000e1;gothai Research Centre, P&#x000e9;cs, 7624 Hungary </aff><aff id="Aff3"><label>3</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.412023.6</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0001 0674 667X</institution-id><institution>Department of Life Sciences, </institution><institution>Dibrugarh University, </institution></institution-wrap>Dibrugarh, 786004 Assam India </aff></contrib-group><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>20</day><month>8</month><year>2020</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>20</day><month>8</month><year>2020</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><month>9</month><year>2020</year></pub-date><volume>10</volume><issue>9</issue><elocation-id>401</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>14</day><month>5</month><year>2020</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>10</day><month>8</month><year>2020</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; The Author(s) 2020</copyright-statement><license license-type="OpenAccess"><license-p><bold>Open Access</bold>This article is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License, which permits use, sharing, adaptation, distribution and reproduction in any medium or format, as long as you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons licence, and indicate if changes were made. The images or other third party material in this article are included in the article's Creative Commons licence, unless indicated otherwise in a credit line to the material. If material is not included in the article's Creative Commons licence and your intended use is not permitted by statutory regulation or exceeds the permitted use, you will need to obtain permission directly from the copyright holder. To view a copy of this licence, visit <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract id="Abs1"><p id="Par1">In the present study, a total of 35 <italic>S. aureus</italic> isolates collected from two different geographical locations viz., Germany and Hungary were tested for their methicillin-resistant phenotype which revealed a high incidence of methicillin-resistant <italic>S. aureus</italic>. The quantitative test for biofilm production revealed that 73.3% of isolates were biofilm producers. The isolates were further characterized using a set of biochemical and genotypic methods such as amplification and analysis of <italic>S. aureus</italic> species-specific sequence and <italic>mecA</italic> gene. The 33 <italic>mecA</italic> positive isolates were then characterized by the amplification of <italic>SCCmec</italic> and <italic>pvl</italic> toxin genes. Further, based on the biofilm-forming phenotype, 15 isolates were selected and characterized through PCR&#x02013;RFLP of <italic>coa</italic> gene, polymorphism of <italic>spa</italic> gene and amplification of biofilm-associated genes. The dendrogram prepared from the results of both biochemical and genotypic analyses of the 15 isolates showed that except for the isolates SA G5 and SA H29, the rest of the isolates grouped themselves according to their locations. Thus, the two isolates were selected for further characterization through whole-genome sequencing. Comparative genome analysis revealed that SA G5 and SA H29 have 97.20% ANI values with 2344 gene clusters (core-genome) of which 16 genes were related to antibiotic resistance genes and 57 genes encode virulence factors. The highest numbers of singleton genes were found in SA H29 that encodes proteins for virulence, resistance, mobile elements, and lanthionine biosynthesis. The high-resolution phylogenetic trees generated based on shared proteins and SNPs revealed a clear difference between the two strains and can be useful in distinguishing closely related genomes. The present study demonstrated that the whole-genome sequence analysis technique is required to get a better insight into the MRSA strains which would be helpful in improving diagnostic investigations in real-time to improve patient care.</p><sec><title>Electronic supplementary material</title><p>The online version of this article (10.1007/s13205-020-02387-y) contains supplementary material, which is available to authorized users.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group xml:lang="en"><title>Keywords</title><kwd>MRSA</kwd><kwd>Molecular typing</kwd><kwd>Whole genome sequencing</kwd><kwd>Comparative genome analysis</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="FundRef">http://dx.doi.org/10.13039/501100008530</institution-id><institution>European Regional Development Fund</institution></institution-wrap></funding-source><award-id>GINOP-2.3.2-15-2016-00021</award-id><award-id>GINOP-2.3.2-15-2016-00047</award-id><principal-award-recipient><name><surname>Fekete</surname><given-names>Csaba</given-names></name></principal-award-recipient></award-group></funding-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source><institution>University of P&#x000e9;cs</institution></funding-source></award-group><open-access><p>Open access funding provided by University of P&#x000e9;cs.</p></open-access></funding-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name><meta-value>&#x000a9; King Abdulaziz City for Science and Technology 2020</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="Sec1"><title>Introduction</title><p id="Par2"><italic>Staphylococcus aureus</italic> is one of the leading causes in both communities- and nosocomial-acquired infections. It acquires an arsenal of antibiotic resistance genes (ARGs) and virulence factors-encoding genes (VFGs) that are subjected to horizontal gene transfer (HGT) and recombination (Hughes and Friedman <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR61">2005</xref>; Chan et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">2011</xref>). It can cause a diverse range of infections including chronic skin and soft tissue infections to life-threatening illnesses (Stefani and Varaldo <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR120">2003</xref>; Yamamoto et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR132">2013</xref>; Mottola et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR96">2016</xref>). The genomic plasticity of <italic>S. aureus</italic> has enabled the emergence of hypervirulent and drug-resistant strains and led to challenging issues in antibiotic therapy. Consequently, the morbidity and mortality rates caused by <italic>S. aureus</italic> infections have a substantial impact on health concern (Denis <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">2017</xref>). Methicillin-resistant <italic>S. aureus</italic> (MRSA) acquired methicillin resistance gene (<italic>mecA</italic>) which is present within Staphylococcal Chromosomal Cassette <italic>mec</italic> (<italic>SCCmec</italic>) (Zhang et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR134">2012</xref>) and reduced affinity of penicillin and &#x003b2;-lactam antibiotics (Jansen et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR65">2006</xref>; Mistry et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR92">2016</xref>). <italic>S. aureus</italic> anchors epithelial surfaces and produces biofilm (Strand&#x000e9;n et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR121">2003</xref>; Goudarzi et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44">2017</xref>). Biofilms act as a barrier against many antibiotics and other stressors and prevent their entry into the cells. Biofilms also defend the bacterial cells from host-immune evasion (Mah and O&#x02019;Toole <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR82">2001</xref>; Donlan and Costerton <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">2002</xref>; Le et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR77">2018</xref>; Vestby et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR127">2020</xref>). Biofilm is a complex 3D structure of sessile microbial community covered by an exopolysaccharide glycocalyx (Otto <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR100">2008</xref>; Deka et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">2019</xref>). The biofilm-forming ability depends on several physicals, chemical, and biological factors (Garrett et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">2008</xref>). The biofilm-forming processes of <italic>S. aureus</italic> are determined by the <italic>icaADBC</italic> gene cluster, responsible for the synthesis of polysaccharide intracellular adhesin (PIA), and capsular polysaccharide/adhesion (PS/A) (Chaieb et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">2005</xref>; Arciola et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">2015</xref>; Hoang et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR53">2019</xref>). The PIA is composed of &#x003b2;-1,6-linked N-acetylglucosamine with partially deacetylated residues, a major component of the exopolysaccharide matrix that surrounds bacterial cells in the biofilm (Mack et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR81">1996</xref>; Vuong et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR128">2004</xref>). It was reported that the co-existence of <italic>icaA</italic> and <italic>icaD</italic> increase N-acetylglucosaminyltransferase activity and slime production (Arciola et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">2001</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">2006</xref>). Additionally, <italic>S. aureus</italic> possesses microbial surface components recognizing adhesive matrix molecules (MSCRAMMs), such as elastin (<italic>ebps</italic>), laminin (<italic>eno</italic>), collagen (<italic>cna</italic>), fibronectin A and B (<italic>fnbA</italic> and <italic>fnbB</italic>), fibrinogen (<italic>fib</italic>), bone sialoprotein (<italic>bbp</italic>) and clumping factors A and B (<italic>clfA</italic> and <italic>clfB</italic>) and these molecules are present on the bacterial surface to enable adherence to host tissues, thus playing a pivotal role in pathogenesis (Lindsay et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR80">2006</xref>; Foster et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">2014</xref>; Ghasemian et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">2015</xref>; Dufr&#x000ea;ne and Viljoen <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">2020</xref>).</p><p id="Par3">Methods for molecular typing of MRSA that depend on gene-specific polymerase chain reaction such as <italic>SCCmec</italic>, <italic>pvl</italic> (Panton-Valentine leukocidin), <italic>coa</italic> (coagulase), and <italic>spa</italic> (<italic>S. aureus</italic> protein A) genes and followed by restriction enzyme digestion (PCR&#x02013;RFLP) has proven its good discriminatory power (DP) and is used routinely for typing MRSA strains (Faria et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">2008</xref>; Omar et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR99">2014</xref>; Al-Obaidi et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">2018</xref>; Tenover et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR126">2019</xref>; Alkharsah et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">2019</xref>). <italic>SCCmec</italic> typing classifies the MRSA into hospital-associated (HA-MRSA) and community-associated (CA-MRSA) strains (Appelbaum <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">2007</xref>). HA-MRSA isolates carried <italic>SCCmec</italic> types I to III, but CA-MRSA isolates has a novel, small variant of <italic>SCCmec</italic> IV and V, but also has the locus for <italic>pvl</italic> gene (Baba et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">2002</xref>; Shukla et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR116">2012</xref>). The coagulase enzyme, a virulence factor encoded by the <italic>coa</italic> gene contains several tandem repeats suitable to generate polymorphic RFLP patterns among different isolates. These molecular typing methods may be helpful in determining the relatedness among geographically diverse MRSA (Singh et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR117">2006</xref>; Grundmann et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46">2010</xref>).</p><p id="Par4">Phenotypic analysis including the antibiotic resistance patterns and molecular typing methods are beneficial for identifying the risk factors associated with MRSA infections which support the establishment of adequate infection control programs (Zhang et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR134">2012</xref>; Mistry et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR92">2016</xref>). Epidemiological studies of MRSA apply various molecular typing techniques such as Pulsed-Field Gel Electrophoresis (PFGE), <italic>SCCmec</italic>, <italic>spa</italic> genes typing, Multi-Locus Sequence Typing (MLST), and detection of <italic>pvl</italic> gene as well as PCR&#x02013;RFLP of <italic>coa</italic> gene (Zhang et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR134">2012</xref>; Al-Obaidi et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">2018</xref>). Many of these established techniques are costly and time-consuming, and the discriminatory abilities of these techniques are also different (Du et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">2011</xref>). However, the <italic>spa</italic> typing method has been considered as a rapid and inexpensive method for genotyping and it provides high discriminating power than other typing methods (Shittu et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR114">2011</xref>; O&#x02019;Hara et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR98">2016</xref>; Goudarzi et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44">2017</xref>; Ali et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">2019</xref>; Rezai et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR107">2019</xref>; Kareem et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR68">2020</xref>). Both phenotypic and molecular typing methods have been used widely to detect and differentiate several MRSA strains, but these techniques have certain limitations in infection control and investigating the nosocomial transmission as these techniques provide low resolution and more time-consuming. Because of that in recent times whole genome-based typing has been used as it offers an excellent resolution in global and local epidemiological investigations of pathogen outbreaks and offers further data mining activities essentially for ARGs and VFGs profiling (K&#x000f6;ser et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR74">2012</xref>). So, the Next Generation Sequencer (NGS) based-genome sequencing technique has become a vital tool in the clinical microbiology arenas for comparative genomic analysis of several other species of the Staphylococcus genus in terms of the niche adaptation, combat antibiotics, and emergence of new virulent strains in real-time (Al-Obaidi et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">2018</xref>; McClure et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR89">2018</xref>; Tenover et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR126">2019</xref>; Maljkovic Berry et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR85">2019</xref>; Raven et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR106">2020</xref>). In the current study, we performed characterization through molecular typing methods and their integrated polyphasic approach to determine the <italic>S. aureus</italic> lineage strains. The lineage strains were compared deeply into a genomic level based on Average Nucleotide Identity (ANI), genome distance, orthologue gene/ clusters, and the evolutionary relationship. Further, ARGs and VFGs were characterized to understand their crucial role in pathogenesis and defense. The information on genomic characteristics and comparative genomics of <italic>S. aureus</italic> will facilitate investigations into the molecular basis of pathogenesis and improve diagnostic investigations of infectious diseases in real-time and improve patient care.</p></sec><sec id="Sec2"><title>Materials and methods</title><sec id="Sec3"><title>Collection and preliminary identification of the isolates</title><p id="Par5">In this study, 35 <italic>S. aureus</italic> strains were collected from the Department of Medical Microbiology and Immunology Laboratory, Medical School, University of Pecs, Hungary. The Hungarian <italic>S. aureus</italic> strains (60%) were previously recovered during February to July 2016 from wounds (31.42%), blood (8.57%), tracheas (5.71%), <italic>ear</italic>s (2.85%), lungs (2.85%), nostrils (2.85%), skins (2.85%) and throats (2.85%) while the German <italic>S. aureus</italic> strains (40%) were recovered from body sites without documentation. The isolates were identified as Staphylococcal strain based on colony morphology on Nutrient agar, Blood Agar, Mannitol Salt Agar, Gram staining, and different biochemical tests (Bergey and Holt <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">1994</xref>). The isolates were tested for catalase, coagulase, urease, DNase production, and mannitol fermentation test (Collee et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">1996</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="Sec4"><title>Antibiotic susceptibility test</title><p id="Par6">The 35 <italic>S. aureus</italic> clinical strains were screened for MRSA using BBL&#x02122; CHROMagar&#x02122; MRSA II media (BD, USA). Susceptibility of <italic>S. aureus</italic> strains to oxacillin (1&#x000a0;&#x003bc;g), cefoxitin (30&#x000a0;&#x003bc;g), erythromycin (15&#x000a0;&#x003bc;g) and vancomycin (30&#x000a0;&#x003bc;g) were determined using disk diffusion method according to Clinical and Laboratory Standards Institute (CLSI) guidance (CLSI 2014). The entire antimicrobial susceptibility test (AST) was repeated three times using the <italic>S. aureus</italic> ATCC25923 and ATCC700698 as MRSA negative and positive controls, respectively. The diameter zone of inhibition was measured in millimetre (mm).</p></sec><sec id="Sec5"><title>Biofilm formation assay</title><p id="Par7">Biofilm formation was performed as previously described (Rahimi et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR105">2016</xref>) with some modifications. Briefly, <italic>S. aureus</italic> strains were cultured overnight at 37&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C in tryptic soy broth (TSB) (BD, Germany) containing 0.25% (w/v) glucose. The cell density was adjusted to a final concentration of 10<sup>6</sup>&#x000a0;CFU/ml in TSB supplemented with 0.25% (w/v) glucose. Cell suspensions (200&#x000a0;&#x000b5;l) were loaded into 96-well round-bottomed microtiter plate (Sarstedt, Germany), and incubated at 37&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C for 18&#x000a0;h without shaking. Cells were washed three times with 200&#x000a0;&#x000b5;l sterile PBS (pH 7.2), dried at room temperature and fixed with methanol (99% v/v). The dried biofilm was stained with 200&#x000a0;&#x000b5;l of 0.16% (w/v) crystal violet for 15&#x000a0;min. To remove the unbound dye, biofilms were washed three times with PBS and air dry. Finally, the biofilm-bound dye was solubilized with 200&#x000a0;&#x000b5;l of 95% (v/v) ethanol, and absorbance was measured at 540&#x000a0;nm wavelength using a Multiskan Ex microtiter plate reader (Thermo Electron Corporation, USA) in a flat-bottom 96-well plate (Costar 3599; Corning; USA). Experiments were performed in triplicates with <italic>S. aureus</italic> ATCC25923 as a biofilm-positive control strain.</p></sec><sec id="Sec6"><title>Molecular identification and genotyping</title><p id="Par8">The DNA of the 35 strains was extracted from the overnight culture of <italic>S. aureus</italic> using QIAamp DNA Mini Kit (Qiagen GmbH, Hilden, Germany). The extracted DNA concentration was assayed by the Nanodrop-2000 spectrophotometer. Genomic DNA was used for the detection of <italic>S. aureus</italic> species-specific sequence (Martineau et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR86">1996</xref>), <italic>mecA</italic> (Strommenger et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR123">2003</xref>), and the <italic>pvl</italic> toxin (Hisata et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR52">2005</xref>; Karahan and &#x000c7;etinkaya <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR67">2007</xref>) genes. <italic>S. aureus</italic> ATCC25923, ATCC700698, and ATCC700699 strains were used as reference strains for <italic>mecA</italic> negative and positive controls respectively. Multiplex PCR typing of <italic>SCCmec</italic> gene was performed on <italic>mecA</italic>-positive <italic>S. aureus</italic> strains using primers as described previously (Zhang et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR135">2005</xref>). The MRSA isolates that showed unexpected amplified fragments or no amplification were defined as non-typeable (NT). For PCR&#x02013;RFLP, the <italic>coa</italic> gene amplicons were digested with HaeIII (Fermentas, USA) restriction enzyme (Khoshkharam-Roodmajani et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR70">2014</xref>) and a heat-map with dendrogram was generated from the restriction banding pattern using Morpheus web-based program (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://software.broadinstitute.org/morpheus/">https://software.broadinstitute.org/morpheus/</ext-link>) using the Euclidean distance feature. Polymorphism of the <italic>spa</italic> gene was detected based on a previously described primer set (Harmsen et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49">2003</xref>). The PCR products were purified using the ZR-96 DNA Clean-up Kit (Zymo Research, USA). Concentration was determined by Qubit 3.0 and sequencing reactions were performed using BigDye Terminator v3.1 Cycle Sequencing Kit (Applied Biosystems, USA). Sequencing reactions were run on ABI PRISM 310 Genetic Analyzer (Applied Biosystems, USA). The <italic>spa</italic> sequence types were assigned using spaTyper (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://spatyper.fortinbras.us/">https://spatyper.fortinbras.us/</ext-link>) and confirmed by a <italic>spa</italic> database (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://spa.ridom.de/">https://spa.ridom.de/</ext-link>) in DNAGear software (Al-Tam et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2012</xref>). The <italic>spa</italic> sequences were aligned, and a phylogenetic tree was constructed by the UPGMA method in MEGA X software (Kumar et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR75">2018</xref>). The DPs of <italic>coa</italic> and <italic>spa</italic> typing were calculated based on Simpson's index using the DP calculator, available online (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://insilico.ehu.es/mini_tools/discriminatory_power/">https://insilico.ehu.es/mini_tools/discriminatory_power/</ext-link>).</p><p id="Par9">Biofilm-encoding genes were amplified using the primer sets listed in Supplementary Table 2. The PCR amplification was performed using DreamTaq PCR Master Mix according to the manufacturer's recommendation (Thermo Fisher Scientific, USA) in a Veriti&#x02122; 96-Well Thermal Cycler (Applied Biosystem, USA) as follows: 96&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C for 3&#x000a0;min; 96&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C for 30&#x000a0;s, 54&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C for 30&#x000a0;s, 72&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C for 1&#x000a0;min repeated for 35 cycles; final extension was performed at 72&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C for 7&#x000a0;min. The amplified products were electrophorized on 2% (w/v) agarose gel, stained using 0.5&#x000a0;&#x000b5;g/ml ethidium bromide solution, and captured using the FluroChem Q system (ProteinSimple&#x02122;, USA).</p></sec><sec id="Sec7"><title>Data setting for a polyphasic approach</title><p id="Par10">Individual result of the applied techniques was converted into the unweighted binary code (0, 1), Jacquard&#x02019;s similarity index was generated and visualized according to the Neighbour-Joining (NJ) clustering method using Past 3.x (Hammer et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48">2001</xref>). Besides the binary data (Supplementary file 2) was used to perform a logistic Principal Component Analysis (PCA) in R software.</p></sec><sec id="Sec8"><title>Whole-genome sequencing</title><p id="Par11">Based on the dendrogram and PCA plot generated from combined results of the phenotypic and genotypic analysis (binary data) of the <italic>S. aureus</italic> strains it was observed that two strains viz., SA G5 (collected from Germany) and SA H29 (collected from Hungary) were found in the same group (Fig. <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>a&#x02013;c). Therefore, these two strains (SA G5 and SA H29) were selected for further analysis through whole-genome sequencing to get a better insight into their genomic background.<fig id="Fig1"><label>Fig. 1</label><caption><p>Polyphasic comparison of <italic>S. aureus</italic> clinical isolates. <bold>a</bold> Colored similarity matrix categories representing resistant test against different antibiotics (ART), biochemical test, PCR based <italic>mecA</italic> and <italic>pvl</italic> genes detection, <italic>SCCmec</italic> typing, <italic>coa</italic>-HaeIII RFLP, <italic>spa</italic> type, biofilm-forming assay and detection of biofilm-associated genes. Red and blue colors indicate the presence (&#x02009;+) and absence (&#x02212;) of particular properties respectively. <bold>b</bold> NJ-dendrogram prepared from the results of biochemical and molecular analysis of the 15 <italic>S. aureus</italic> clinical isolates (SA). The isolates were labeled according to their geographical origin where G and H indicate Germany and Hungary. Clusters are labeled as A-F. <bold>c</bold> Principal component analysis of the results of biochemical and molecular analysis of the 15 <italic>S. aureus</italic> clinical isolates</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="13205_2020_2387_Fig1_HTML" id="MO1"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="Sec9"><title>Genomic DNA extraction, library preparation, and sequencing</title><p id="Par12">Whole-genome sequencing was performed at Microbial Biotechnology Research Group, Szent&#x000e1;gothai Research Centre, University of Pecs, Hungary with the following procedures: the genomic DNA was extracted using the GenElute&#x02122; Bacterial Genomic DNA Kit (Sigma, USA) following the manufacturer&#x02019;s recommendation. The extracted DNA samples were quantified in a Qubit 3.0 fluorometer (Invitrogen, USA) using dsDNA High Sensitivity (HS) Assay Kit (Thermo Fisher Scientific Inc. USA) and subsequently, DNA quality was visualized by agarose gel electrophoresis. Genomic libraries were prepared using the NEB Next Fast DNA Fragmentation and Library Preparation Kit, developed for Ion Torrent (New England Biolabs, USA) and used according to 200&#x000a0;bp protocol. After chemical fragmentation, DNA size selection was performed on precast 2% E-Gel Size Select Gel (Thermo Fisher Scientific Inc. USA). The quality of the libraries was verified using Agilent high sensitivity DNA assay kit (Agilent Technologies Inc. USA) in Agilent 2100 Bioanalyzer System (Agilent Technologies Inc. USA). For the template preparation, Ion PGM Hi-Q View OT2 Kit was used (Thermo Fisher Scientific Inc. USA). The template positive beads were loaded on Ion 316v2 Chip and sequenced using Ion PGM Hi-Q View Sequencing Kit on Ion Torrent Personal Genome Machine (PGM) (Thermo Fisher Scientific Inc. USA).</p></sec><sec id="Sec10"><title>Genome assembly, annotation, and comparison</title><p id="Par13">Quality trimming of the reads was performed with the Ion Torrent Suite 5.4.0 (Thermo Fisher Scientific Inc. USA) with default settings. De novo genome assembly was performed by SPAdes 3.7.1 software with default parameters for Ion Torrent data and <italic>k-mer</italic> settings of 21, 33, 55, 77, 99, and 127 (Nurk et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR97">2013</xref>). Closely related reference genomes were identified using kmerFinder 3.1 and NCBI microbial genome blast web-platforms. Identified high-quality reference genomes, CP006044.1 (<italic>S. aureus</italic> CA-347), and CP023390 (<italic>S. aureus</italic> subsp<italic>. aureus str. Newman</italic>) were applied to orientate and order contigs of SA G5 and SA H29 respectively using the &#x02018;Move Contigs&#x02019; algorithm in Mauve 2.4.0 (Darling et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">2010</xref>). Scaffolds were generated using the reference-based scaffolder MeDuSa (Bosi et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">2015</xref>). Gene annotation was performed by two independent automated pipelines based on Rapid Annotation using Subsystem Technology (RAST) (Aziz et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">2008</xref>) and NCBI Prokaryotic Genome Annotation Pipeline (Tatusova et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR125">2016</xref>).</p><p id="Par14">The values for ANI were calculated using the OrthoANIu algorithm (Yoon et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR133">2017</xref>). Also, dDDH (digital DNA-DNA Hybridization) estimates were obtained from Genome to Genome Distance Calculator 2.1 (Meier-Kolthoff et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR91">2013</xref>). RAST server-based SEED viewer was used for the subsystem functional categorization (Overbeek et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR101">2014</xref>). The protein-coding sequence identified by RAST was analyzed for orthologous genes/clusters and subsequent functional annotation using web platform OrthoVenn2 (Xu et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR131">2019</xref>). Graphical map of sequence features embedded circular genomes of SA G5, CP006044.1, SA H29, and CP023390.1 were generated using CGView Server (Grant and Stothard <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">2008</xref>) with default parameters against the reference genome <italic>Staphylococcus aureus subsp. aureus</italic> NCTC 8325 (NC_007795.1). ARGs and VFGs were identified by the Comprehensive Antibiotic Resistance Database (CARD) and the virulence factor database (VFDB) in PATRIC 3.5.43 (Chen et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">2016</xref>; Wattam et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR130">2017</xref>). The genome assemblies were screened for plasmid replicon (<italic>rep</italic>) genes in nonaligned contigs or scaffold regions using PlasmidFinder version 2.1 (Carattoli et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">2014</xref>) with default parameters. The identified nonaligned contigs or scaffolds associated with plasmid sequences were extracted and used for the identification of full-length plasmid regions using PLSDB (Plasmid Database) version-2020-03-04 with search strategy Mash screen, and the default values were a maximum <italic>P</italic> value of 0.1 and a minimum identity of 0.99 (Galata et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">2019</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="Sec11"><title>Phylogenetic analysis</title><p id="Par15">The 16S rRNA sequences obtained from the whole genome data of the two strains were aligned with the other closely related 16S rRNA sequences of <italic>S. strains</italic> and <italic>Bacillus cereus</italic> ATCC14579 (AE016877.1) using MUSCLE algorithm in MEGA X (Kumar et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR75">2018</xref>). The phylogenetic tree was then constructed by the NJ method with 500 replicates. Phylogenetic trees were generated based on the concatenated alignment of all shared proteins (core) of <italic>S. aureus</italic> genome sequences with <italic>B. cereus</italic> ATCC14579 (AE016877.1) as outgroup by RAxML in PATRIC 3.5.43 (Wattam et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR130">2017</xref>). SNPs were filtered from the genome sequences and generate phylogeny based on the concatenated alignment of the high-quality SNPs using CSI phylogeny 1.4 servers (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://cge.cbs.dtu.dk/services/CSIPhylogeny/">https://cge.cbs.dtu.dk/services/CSIPhylogeny/</ext-link>) and the tree was visualized in MEGA X (Kumar et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR75">2018</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="Sec12"><title>Sequence supporting data</title><p id="Par16">The genomic data of this study were deposited in the NCBI genome database under the GenBank accession numbers: CP032160 and CP032468-CP032470.</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec13"><title>Results</title><sec id="Sec14"><title>Phenotypic characterization</title><p id="Par17">The colony characteristics of the strain are yellow colored, moist, round, glistening opaque colonies with &#x003b2; or weak hemolysis on blood agar. The strains are Gram-positive cocci showing typical staphylococcal bunch.</p></sec><sec id="Sec15"><title>Antibiotic susceptibility test</title><p id="Par18">The 35 <italic>S. aureus</italic> clinical strains were screened for MRSA using BBL&#x02122; CHROMagar&#x02122; MRSA II media which revealed that 94.28% of the strains were MRSA. The tested strains were highly resistant to beta-lactam antibiotics viz<italic>.</italic> oxacillin (94.28%) and cefoxitin (94.28%), but less resistant to non-beta lactam antibiotics, erythromycin (71.43%), and none of the strain displayed resistant to vancomycin (Table <xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>).<table-wrap id="Tab1"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Antibiotic susceptibility patterns of <italic>S. aureus</italic> isolates</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="2">Strain ID</th><th align="left" rowspan="2">Origin</th><th align="left" colspan="4">Diameter of inhibition zone (mm)</th></tr><tr><th align="left">Ox-1&#x000a0;&#x000b5;g</th><th align="left">Cfox-30&#x000a0;&#x003bc;g</th><th align="left">Ery-15&#x000a0;&#x000b5;g</th><th align="left">Van-30&#x000a0;&#x003bc;g</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left">SA G1</td><td align="left">HA</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">6&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0 (R)</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">6&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0 (R)</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">6&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0 (R)</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">19.5&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.7 (S)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">SA G2</td><td align="left">HA</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">11.5&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.7 (R)</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">6&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0 (R)</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">6&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0 (R)</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">20&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.7 (S)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">SA G3</td><td align="left">HA</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">28&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0 (S)</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">18.5&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.7 (S)</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">27&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0 (S)</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">21&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.4 (S)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">SA G4</td><td align="left">HA</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">6&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0 (R)</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">6&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0 (R)</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">24.5&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;7.7 (S)</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">20.5&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.7 (S)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">SA G5</td><td align="left">HA</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">6&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0 (R)</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">6&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0 (R)</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">24.5&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;7.7 (S)</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">19.5&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.7 (S)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">SA G6</td><td align="left">HA</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">6&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0 (R)</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">6&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0 (R)</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">6&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0 (R)</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">20&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0 (S)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">SA G7</td><td align="left">HA</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">24.5&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.7 (S)</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">18&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0 (S)</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">30&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0 (S)</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">18.5&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.7 (S)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">SA G8</td><td align="left">HA</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">6&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0 (R)</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">6&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0 (R)</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">6&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0 (R)</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">18.5&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.7 (S)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">SA G9</td><td align="left">CA</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">6&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0 (R)</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">6&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0 (R)</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">24&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;8 (S)</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">18&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0 (S)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">SA G10</td><td align="left">CA</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">6&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0 (R)</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">6&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0 (R)</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">6&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0 (R)</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">20&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.4 (S)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">SA G11</td><td align="left">CA</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">6&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0 (R)</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">6&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0 (R)</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">10&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0 (S)</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">19&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.4 (S)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">SA G12</td><td align="left">CA</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">6&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0 (R)</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">7.5&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;2.1 (R)</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">30&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0 (S)</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">19.5&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;07 (S)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">SA G13</td><td align="left">CA</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">6&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0 (R)</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">6&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0 (R)</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">30&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0 (S)</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">19&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0 (S)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">SA G14</td><td align="left">CA</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">6&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0 (R)</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">6&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0 (R)</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">30&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0 (S)</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">19&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0 (S)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">SA H15</td><td align="left">HA</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">6&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0 (R)</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">6&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0 (R)</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">6&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0 (R)</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">19&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0 (S)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">SA H16</td><td align="left">HA</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">6&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0 (R)</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">6&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0 (R)</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">6&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0 (R)</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">20&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0 (S)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">SA H17</td><td align="left">HA</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">6&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0 (R)</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">6&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0 (R)</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">6&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0 (R)</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">18&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0 (S)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">SA H18</td><td align="left">HA</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">6&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0 (R)</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">6&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0 (R)</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">6&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0 (R)</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">18.5&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.7 (S)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">SA H19</td><td align="left">HA</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">6&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0 (R)</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">6&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0 (R)</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">6&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0 (R)</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">19.5&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.7 (S)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">SA H20</td><td align="left">HA</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">6&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0 (R)</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">6&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0 (R)</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">6&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0 (R)</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">19&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.4 (S)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">SA H21</td><td align="left">HA</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">6&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0 (R)</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">6&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0 (R)</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">11&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0 (R)</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">18.5&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.7 (S)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">SA H22</td><td align="left">HA</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">6&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0 (R)</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">6&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0 (R)</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">11&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0 (R)</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">18.5&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.7 (S)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">SA H23</td><td align="left">HA</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">6&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0 (R)</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">7.5&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;2.1 (R)</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">6&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0 (R)</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">20&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0 (S)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">SA H24</td><td align="left">HA</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">6&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0 (R)</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">6&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0 (R)</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">6&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0 (R)</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">19&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0 (S)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">SA H25</td><td align="left">HA</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">6&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0 (R)</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">6&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0 (R)</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">6&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0 (R)</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">20&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0 (S)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">SA H26</td><td align="left">HA</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">8&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;2.8 (R)</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">14.5&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.7 (R)</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">6&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0 (R)</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">19&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.4 (S)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">SA H27</td><td align="left">HA</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">6&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0 (R)</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">6&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0 (R)</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">16.14&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0 (R)</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">19.5&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.7 (S)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">SA H28</td><td align="left">HA</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">6&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0 (R)</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">6&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0 (R)</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">24.5&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.7 (R)</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">19&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.4 (S)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">SA H29</td><td align="left">HA</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">10.5&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.7 (R)</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">8&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;2.8 (R)</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">6&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0 (R)</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">19&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.4 (S)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">SA H30</td><td align="left">HA</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">6&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0 (R)</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">3&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0 (R)</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">6&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0 (R)</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">18.5&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;2.1 (S)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">SA H31</td><td align="left">HA</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">6&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0 (R)</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">6&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0 (R)</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">6&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0 (R)</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">18.5&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.7 (S)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">SA H32</td><td align="left">HA</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">6&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0 (R)</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">6&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0 (R)</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">6&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0 (R)</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">19&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.4 (S)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">SA H33</td><td align="left">HA</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">6&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0 (R)</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">6&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0 (R)</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">6&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0 (R)</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">19&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.4 (S)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">SA H34</td><td align="left">HA</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">6&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0 (R)</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">6&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0 (R)</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">6&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0 (R)</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">19.5&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.7 (S)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">SA H35</td><td align="left">HA</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">6&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0 (R)</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">6&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0 (R)</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">6&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0 (R)</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">19&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.4 (S)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">ATCC700698</td><td align="left">&#x02013;</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">6&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0 (R)</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">6&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0 (R)</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">6&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0 (R)</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">19.5&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.7 (S)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">ATCC25923</td><td align="left">&#x02013;</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">26.5&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.7 (S)</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">25&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0 (S)</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">33.5&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.7 (S)</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">20.5&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.7 (S)</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>Zone of inhibition in mm is given as Mean&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;SD; <italic>R </italic>and<italic> S</italic> denote the resistant and susceptible, <italic>Ox</italic> oxacillin (&#x02264;&#x02009;10&#x000a0;mm&#x02009;=&#x02009;Resistant), <italic>Cfox</italic> cefoxitin (&#x02264;&#x02009;14&#x000a0;mm&#x02009;=&#x02009;Resistant), <italic>Ery</italic> erythromycin (&#x02264;&#x02009;13&#x000a0;mm&#x02009;=&#x02009;Resistant), <italic>Van</italic> vancomycin (&#x02264;&#x02009;9&#x000a0;mm&#x02009;=&#x02009;Resistant)</p><p><sup>a</sup>SA G and SA H represent strains isolated from Germany and Hungary respectively. HA and CA represent the Hospital and Community-associated <italic>S. aureus</italic> strains respectively</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p></sec><sec id="Sec16"><title>Biofilm production test</title><p id="Par19">The quantitative test for biofilm production revealed that among the 33 methicillin-resistant strains, 87.87% of strains produced biofilm. Fifteen strains were selected among 33 methicillin-resistant strains based on non- (26.7%), moderate- (40%), and strong- (33.3%) biofilm-forming abilities for molecular typing and discrimination. (Supplementary Table 1).</p></sec><sec id="Sec17"><title>Molecular characterization and genotyping</title><p id="Par20">The PCR amplified products showed that 100% strains of <italic>S. aureus</italic> were positive to <italic>S. aureus</italic> species-specific sequence represented by a distinct band of 107 base pairs (bp) (Supplementary Fig. 1). The <italic>mecA</italic> and <italic>pvl</italic> genes were detected in 94.28% with an amplicon size of 532&#x000a0;bp and 22.85% with the amplicon size 1918&#x000a0;bp respectively (Supplementary Figs. 2, 3). The AST and <italic>mecA</italic> gene detection revealed concordant results, thus 94.28% of <italic>S. aureus</italic> isolates were confirmed as MRSA.</p><p id="Par21"><italic>SCCmec</italic> typing revealed that <italic>SCCmec</italic> type II (33.33%) was the most predominant followed by type I (21.21%), type IVa (15.5%), type IVd (9.09%), IVb (3.03%) and the rest of the strains were non-typeable (12.12%). Among the 35 strains, eight strains were positive for <italic>pvl</italic> of which four strains belonged to <italic>SCCmec</italic> II, three strains to <italic>SCCmec</italic> IV and, one to <italic>SCCmec</italic> V (Supplementary Fig.4). The distribution of <italic>SCCmec</italic> types showed that 36.36% of strains were CA-MRSA and 54.54% strains were HA-MRSA (Table <xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref>).<table-wrap id="Tab2"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Biochemical tests and PCR based molecular detection of <italic>mecA</italic>, <italic>pvl</italic> and <italic>SCCmec</italic> genes of <italic>S. aureus</italic> isolates</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="2"><sup>a</sup>Strain ID</th><th align="left" colspan="8">Biochemical tests</th><th align="left" colspan="3">Molecular detection</th></tr><tr><th align="left">Catalase</th><th align="left">Coagulase</th><th align="left">DNase</th><th align="left">Citrate utilization</th><th align="left">Urease production</th><th align="left">MF</th><th align="left"><italic>Blood Lysis</italic></th><th align="left">Biofilm</th><th align="left"><italic>mecA</italic></th><th align="left"><italic>pvl</italic></th><th align="left"><italic>SCCmec</italic> type</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left">SA G1</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02009;+&#x02009;</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02009;+&#x02009;</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02009;+&#x02009;</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02009;+&#x02009;</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02009;+&#x02009;</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02009;+&#x02009;</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02009;+&#x02009;</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02212;</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02009;+&#x02009;</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02212;</td><td char="." align="char">I</td></tr><tr><td align="left">SA G2</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02009;+&#x02009;</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02009;+&#x02009;</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02009;+&#x02009;</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02009;+&#x02009;</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02009;+&#x02009;</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02009;+&#x02009;</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02009;+&#x02009;</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02212;</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02009;+&#x02009;</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02212;</td><td char="." align="char">I</td></tr><tr><td align="left">SA G3</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02009;+&#x02009;</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02009;+&#x02009;</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02009;+&#x02009;</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02009;+&#x02009;</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02009;+&#x02009;</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02009;+&#x02009;</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02009;+&#x02009;</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02009;+&#x02009;</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02212;</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02212;</td><td char="." align="char">NT</td></tr><tr><td align="left">SA G4</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02009;+&#x02009;</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02009;+&#x02009;</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02009;+&#x02009;</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02009;+&#x02009;</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02009;+&#x02009;</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02009;+&#x02009;</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02009;+&#x02009;</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02009;+&#x02009;</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02009;+&#x02009;</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02212;</td><td char="." align="char">NT</td></tr><tr><td align="left">SA G5</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02009;+&#x02009;</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02009;+&#x02009;</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02009;+&#x02009;</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02009;+&#x02009;</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02009;+&#x02009;</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02009;+&#x02009;</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02009;+&#x02009;</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02009;+&#x02009;</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02009;+&#x02009;</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02212;</td><td char="." align="char">IVd</td></tr><tr><td align="left">SA G6</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02009;+&#x02009;</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02009;+&#x02009;</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02009;+&#x02009;</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02009;+&#x02009;</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02009;+&#x02009;</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02009;+&#x02009;</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02009;+&#x02009;</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02212;</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02009;+&#x02009;</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02212;</td><td char="." align="char">I</td></tr><tr><td align="left">SA G7</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02009;+&#x02009;</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02009;+&#x02009;</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02009;+&#x02009;</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02009;+&#x02009;</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02009;+&#x02009;</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02009;+&#x02009;</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02009;+&#x02009;</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02009;+&#x02009;</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02212;</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02212;</td><td char="." align="char">NT</td></tr><tr><td align="left">SA G8</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02009;+&#x02009;</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02009;+&#x02009;</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02009;+&#x02009;</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02009;+&#x02009;</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02009;+&#x02009;</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02009;+&#x02009;</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02009;+&#x02009;</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02009;+&#x02009;</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02009;+&#x02009;</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02009;+&#x02009;</td><td char="." align="char">II</td></tr><tr><td align="left">SA G9</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02009;+&#x02009;</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02009;+&#x02009;</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02009;+&#x02009;</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02009;+&#x02009;</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02009;+&#x02009;</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02009;+&#x02009;</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02009;+&#x02009;</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02009;+&#x02009;</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02009;+&#x02009;</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02009;+&#x02009;</td><td char="." align="char">IVa</td></tr><tr><td align="left">SA G10</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02009;+&#x02009;</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02009;+&#x02009;</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02009;+&#x02009;</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02009;+&#x02009;</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02009;+&#x02009;</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02009;+&#x02009;</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02009;+&#x02009;</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02009;+&#x02009;</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02009;+&#x02009;</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02009;+&#x02009;</td><td char="." align="char">IVa</td></tr><tr><td align="left">SA G11</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02009;+&#x02009;</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02009;+&#x02009;</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02009;+&#x02009;</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02009;+&#x02009;</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02009;+&#x02009;</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02009;+&#x02009;</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02009;+&#x02009;</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02009;+&#x02009;</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02009;+&#x02009;</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02009;+&#x02009;</td><td char="." align="char">IVa</td></tr><tr><td align="left">SA G12</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02009;+&#x02009;</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02009;+&#x02009;</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02009;+&#x02009;</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02009;+&#x02009;</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02009;+&#x02009;</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02009;+&#x02009;</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02009;+&#x02009;</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02009;+&#x02009;</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02009;+&#x02009;</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02212;</td><td char="." align="char">IVa</td></tr><tr><td align="left">SA G13</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02009;+&#x02009;</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02009;+&#x02009;</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02009;+&#x02009;</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02009;+&#x02009;</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02009;+&#x02009;</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02009;+&#x02009;</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02009;+&#x02009;</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02009;+&#x02009;</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02009;+&#x02009;</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02212;</td><td char="." align="char">IVa</td></tr><tr><td align="left">SA G14</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02009;+&#x02009;</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02009;+&#x02009;</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02009;+&#x02009;</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02009;+&#x02009;</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02009;+&#x02009;</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02009;+&#x02009;</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02009;+&#x02009;</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02009;+&#x02009;</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02009;+&#x02009;</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02009;+&#x02009;</td><td char="." align="char">V</td></tr><tr><td align="left">SA H15</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02009;+&#x02009;</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02009;+&#x02009;</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02009;+&#x02009;</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02009;+&#x02009;</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02009;+&#x02009;</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02009;+&#x02009;</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02009;+&#x02009;</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02009;+&#x02009;</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02009;+&#x02009;</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02212;</td><td char="." align="char">II</td></tr><tr><td align="left">SA H16</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02009;+&#x02009;</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02009;+&#x02009;</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02009;+&#x02009;</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02009;+&#x02009;</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02009;+&#x02009;</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02009;+&#x02009;</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02009;+&#x02009;</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02212;</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02009;+&#x02009;</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02009;+&#x02009;</td><td char="." align="char">II</td></tr><tr><td align="left">SA H17</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02009;+&#x02009;</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02009;+&#x02009;</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02009;+&#x02009;</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02009;+&#x02009;</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02009;+&#x02009;</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02009;+&#x02009;</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02009;+&#x02009;</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02009;+&#x02009;</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02009;+&#x02009;</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02212;</td><td char="." align="char">II</td></tr><tr><td align="left">SA H18</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02009;+&#x02009;</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02009;+&#x02009;</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02009;+&#x02009;</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02009;+&#x02009;</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02009;+&#x02009;</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02009;+&#x02009;</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02009;+&#x02009;</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02009;+&#x02009;</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02009;+&#x02009;</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02212;</td><td char="." align="char">I</td></tr><tr><td align="left">SA H19</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02009;+&#x02009;</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02009;+&#x02009;</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02009;+&#x02009;</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02009;+&#x02009;</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02009;+&#x02009;</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02009;+&#x02009;</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02009;+&#x02009;</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02009;+&#x02009;</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02009;+&#x02009;</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02212;</td><td char="." align="char">I</td></tr><tr><td align="left">SA H20</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02009;+&#x02009;</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02009;+&#x02009;</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02009;+&#x02009;</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02009;+&#x02009;</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02009;+&#x02009;</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02009;+&#x02009;</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02009;+&#x02009;</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02009;+&#x02009;</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02009;+&#x02009;</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02212;</td><td char="." align="char">II</td></tr><tr><td align="left">SA H21</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02009;+&#x02009;</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02009;+&#x02009;</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02009;+&#x02009;</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02009;+&#x02009;</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02009;+&#x02009;</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02009;+&#x02009;</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02009;+&#x02009;</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02009;+&#x02009;</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02009;+&#x02009;</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02212;</td><td char="." align="char">IVb</td></tr><tr><td align="left">SA H22</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02009;+&#x02009;</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02009;+&#x02009;</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02009;+&#x02009;</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02009;+&#x02009;</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02009;+&#x02009;</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02009;+&#x02009;</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02009;+&#x02009;</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02009;+&#x02009;</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02009;+&#x02009;</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02212;</td><td char="." align="char">II</td></tr><tr><td align="left">SA H23</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02009;+&#x02009;</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02009;+&#x02009;</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02009;+&#x02009;</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02009;+&#x02009;</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02009;+&#x02009;</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02009;+&#x02009;</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02009;+&#x02009;</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02009;+&#x02009;</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02009;+&#x02009;</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02212;</td><td char="." align="char">IVa</td></tr><tr><td align="left">SA H24</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02009;+&#x02009;</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02009;+&#x02009;</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02009;+&#x02009;</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02009;+&#x02009;</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02009;+&#x02009;</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02009;+&#x02009;</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02009;+&#x02009;</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02009;+&#x02009;</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02009;+&#x02009;</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02212;</td><td char="." align="char">II</td></tr><tr><td align="left">SA H25</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02009;+&#x02009;</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02009;+&#x02009;</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02009;+&#x02009;</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02009;+&#x02009;</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02009;+&#x02009;</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02009;+&#x02009;</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02009;+&#x02009;</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02009;+&#x02009;</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02009;+&#x02009;</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02212;</td><td char="." align="char">II</td></tr><tr><td align="left">SA H26</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02009;+&#x02009;</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02009;+&#x02009;</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02009;+&#x02009;</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02009;+&#x02009;</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02009;+&#x02009;</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02009;+&#x02009;</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02009;+&#x02009;</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02009;+&#x02009;</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02009;+&#x02009;</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02212;</td><td char="." align="char">I</td></tr><tr><td align="left">SA H27</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02009;+&#x02009;</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02009;+&#x02009;</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02009;+&#x02009;</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02009;+&#x02009;</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02009;+&#x02009;</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02009;+&#x02009;</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02009;+&#x02009;</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02009;+&#x02009;</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02009;+&#x02009;</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02212;</td><td char="." align="char">IVd</td></tr><tr><td align="left">SA H28</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02009;+&#x02009;</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02009;+&#x02009;</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02009;+&#x02009;</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02009;+&#x02009;</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02009;+&#x02009;</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02009;+&#x02009;</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02009;+&#x02009;</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02009;+&#x02009;</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02009;+&#x02009;</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02212;</td><td char="." align="char">IVa</td></tr><tr><td align="left">SA H29</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02009;+&#x02009;</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02009;+&#x02009;</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02009;+&#x02009;</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02009;+&#x02009;</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02009;+&#x02009;</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02009;+&#x02009;</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02009;+&#x02009;</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02009;+&#x02009;</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02009;+&#x02009;</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02212;</td><td char="." align="char">IVd</td></tr><tr><td align="left">SA H30</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02009;+&#x02009;</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02009;+&#x02009;</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02009;+&#x02009;</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02009;+&#x02009;</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02009;+&#x02009;</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02009;+&#x02009;</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02009;+&#x02009;</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02009;+&#x02009;</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02009;+&#x02009;</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02009;+&#x02009;</td><td char="." align="char">II</td></tr><tr><td align="left">SA H31</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02009;+&#x02009;</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02009;+&#x02009;</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02009;+&#x02009;</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02009;+&#x02009;</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02009;+&#x02009;</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02009;+&#x02009;</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02009;+&#x02009;</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02009;+&#x02009;</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02009;+&#x02009;</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02212;</td><td char="." align="char">I</td></tr><tr><td align="left">SA H32</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02009;+&#x02009;</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02009;+&#x02009;</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02009;+&#x02009;</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02009;+&#x02009;</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02009;+&#x02009;</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02009;+&#x02009;</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02009;+&#x02009;</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02009;+&#x02009;</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02009;+&#x02009;</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02212;</td><td char="." align="char">NT</td></tr><tr><td align="left">SA H33</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02009;+&#x02009;</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02009;+&#x02009;</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02009;+&#x02009;</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02009;+&#x02009;</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02009;+&#x02009;</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02009;+&#x02009;</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02009;+&#x02009;</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02009;+&#x02009;</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02009;+&#x02009;</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02212;</td><td char="." align="char">II</td></tr><tr><td align="left">SA H34</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02009;+&#x02009;</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02009;+&#x02009;</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02009;+&#x02009;</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02009;+&#x02009;</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02009;+&#x02009;</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02009;+&#x02009;</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02009;+&#x02009;</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02009;+&#x02009;</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02009;+&#x02009;</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02009;+&#x02009;</td><td char="." align="char">II</td></tr><tr><td align="left">SA H35</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02009;+&#x02009;</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02009;+&#x02009;</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02009;+&#x02009;</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02009;+&#x02009;</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02009;+&#x02009;</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02009;+&#x02009;</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02009;+&#x02009;</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02009;+&#x02009;</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02009;+&#x02009;</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02212;</td><td char="." align="char">NT</td></tr><tr><td align="left">ATCC700698</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02009;+&#x02009;</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02009;+&#x02009;</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02009;+&#x02009;</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02009;+&#x02009;</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02009;+&#x02009;</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02009;+&#x02009;</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02009;+&#x02009;</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02009;+&#x02009;</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02009;+&#x02009;</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02212;</td><td char="." align="char">II</td></tr><tr><td align="left">ATCC25923</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02009;+&#x02009;</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02009;+&#x02009;</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02009;+&#x02009;</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02009;+&#x02009;</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02009;+&#x02009;</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02009;+&#x02009;</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02009;+&#x02009;</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02009;+&#x02009;</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02212;</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02212;</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02212;</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p><sup>a</sup>MF represents mannitol production, Blood lysis represents hemolysis on blood agar, Biofilm represents biofilm production, <italic>mecA</italic> represents gene encode for penicillin-binding protein 2A (PBP2A); <italic>pvl</italic> represents gene encode for Panton-Valentine leukocidin toxin.&#x02009;+&#x02009;and &#x02013; represent present and absent; NT denotes <italic>SCCmec</italic> cassette non-typeable</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p><p id="Par22">The <italic>coa</italic> gene amplification produced amplicons size in the range of 550 to 800&#x000a0;bp, the amplicons of 700&#x000a0;bp showed the highest frequency (33.33%) followed by amplicon sizes of 550&#x000a0;bp (26.66%), 650&#x000a0;bp (13.33%), 740&#x000a0;bp (0.66%), 660&#x000a0;bp (0.66%), 800&#x000a0;bp (0.66%) and 600&#x000a0;bp (0.66%) (Supplementary Fig. 5). The result of the <italic>coa</italic> gene PCR&#x02013;RFLP is summarized in supplementary Table 3 and supplementary Fig.&#x000a0;6. To get more insight into the similarity and difference of complex RFLP banding pattern, presence/absence heat-map and dendrogram was generated. Visualisation of banding patterns revealed six distinct clusters, namely A-F with calculated prevalence of 6.6, 13.3, 13.3, 20, 33.3 and 13.3%, respectively. (Supplementary Fig.&#x000a0;7). Typing of <italic>coa</italic> gene and <italic>HaeIII</italic> RFLP, as well as DIs, were presented in supplementary Table 3.</p><p id="Par23">Typing of the <italic>spa</italic> gene revealed 10 amplicons, ranging in size from 355 to 560&#x000a0;bp (Supplementary Fig.&#x000a0;8). The DI of <italic>spa</italic>-PCR typing was 0.9429. Analysis of the <italic>spa</italic> gene revealed twelve known <italic>spa</italic> types. SA G11 and SA H29 strains possessing <italic>SCCmec</italic>-IV gene (CA-MRSA) and both were in the same t008 <italic>spa</italic>-type. SA H16 and SA H19 strains clustered together into t062 <italic>spa</italic>-type and both were found resistant to erythromycin, also classified into HA-MRSA group (Supplementary Table 4). The phylogenetic tree based on <italic>spa</italic> sequences revealed four distinct clusters, designated as A, B, C, and D with a prevalence of 33.33%, 46.66%, 13.33%, and 6.66% respectively (Supplementary Fig.&#x000a0;9).</p><p id="Par24">Although, all the selected strains did not produce biofilm each of them harbors genes for intracellular adhesion (<italic>icaADBC</italic>) and regulation (<italic>icaR</italic>). The presence of <italic>fnbA</italic> and <italic>fnbB</italic> genes were detected in 73.3% and 66.6% strains, respectively. Genes also associated with biofilm-forming ability viz. <italic>cna</italic>, <italic>clfA</italic>, <italic>clfB</italic>, and <italic>ebps</italic> were found present in 53.33%, 80%, 73.3%, and 86.6% strains, respectively. Agarose gel electrophoresis pictures of biofilm-associated genes are presented in supplementary figs. 10&#x02013;20.</p></sec><sec id="Sec18"><title>Cluster analysis based on phenotypic and genotypic data</title><p id="Par25">Although, the individual test, for example, performed AST, catalase, coagulase, DNase, citrate utilization, urease production, mannitol fermentation, blood lysis, and biofilm production assays has the advantage of being cost-effective, but often cannot differentiate among the strains. PCR-based detection of <italic>mecA</italic> gene and genes responsible for PIA (<italic>icaADBC</italic> and <italic>icaR</italic>) could not differentiate the clinical isolates in the present study. PCR-based detection of <italic>pvl</italic> gene and genes encoding for MSCRAMMs (<italic>fnaA</italic>, <italic>fnaB</italic>, <italic>clfA</italic>, <italic>clfB</italic>, <italic>cna</italic>, and <italic>ebps</italic>) also showed poor DP, while <italic>SCCmec</italic>, <italic>coa</italic>-HaeIII RFLP and <italic>spa</italic> typing revealed moderate DP. To avoid the misleading conclusion, the data from all applied methods were coupled to perform cluster and PCA analysis. The generated dendrogram suggested that strains collected from the same geographical region shared the same cluster F. Except for cluster E in which strains SA G5 and SA H29 from different geographical locations clustered together (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>b). The PCA analysis also revealed that SA G5 and SA H29 shared less variance than the other strains (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>c).</p></sec><sec id="Sec19"><title>General features of sequenced genomes</title><p id="Par26">Ion-Torrent PGM sequencing of SA G5 and SA H29 genomes generated reads range of 18.55 and 25.98 million bases (Mb) per sample covering more than 98% of the reference genome (ASM1342v1) with an average depth of 152.4X. SPAdes assembled sequences were further analyzed by QUAST producing genomes with 43 and 47 contigs and N50 ranging from 85 and 185&#x000a0;kb after filtering contigs size&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;200&#x000a0;bp. Mauve contigs ordering and MeDuSa scaffolder produced SA G5 and SA H29 final genomes sequence lengths of 2,760,385 and 2,834,624&#x000a0;bp respectively. The total GC contents were 32.77 and 32.65%. The SA G5 and SA H29 genomes contain 2689 and 2843 coding sequences (CDS) with 9 and 6 rRNAs, and 59 and 51 tRNAs, respectively. The summarized genomic features were shown in Table <xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref>.</p></sec><sec id="Sec20"><title>Comparative genome analysis</title><p id="Par27">OrthoANIu identity found ANI of 97.20% among the SA G5 and SA H29 genome sequences. Similarly, dDDH was calculated using the GGDC tool revealed that the probability of DDH (DNA-DNA hybridization) is 84.5% with a genetic distance of 0.0308, suggesting that SA G5 and SA H29 occupy identical taxonomic status which is also supported by the different genotypic data.</p><p id="Par28">According to SEED subsystems, SA H29 genome contains amino acids and derivatives encoding genes (245 CDSs), virulence, disease and defense genes (67 CDSs), carbohydrate utilization genes (178 CDSs) and genes derived from phages, prophages, transposable elements and plasmid (20 CDSs) as presented in the Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>a, b. In addition, the relationship between SA G5 and SA H29 genomes were analyzed using web platform OrthoVenn2, which identified 2366 gene clusters (pan-genome), of which 2344 orthologous clusters were shared between SA G5 and SA H29, and 2337 were single-copy gene clusters (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>c). These two strains shared 2344 gene clusters (core-genome) comprising 4695 proteins (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>a, b). SA H29 genome possesses the highest singleton genes covering 37 numbers of proteins that are responsible for virulence, resistance, mobile genetic elements, and lanthionine biosynthesis. Whole-genome circular comparative map of two genomes (SA G5 and SA H29) and their close genomes against <italic>Staphylococcus aureus subsp. aureus NCTC 8325</italic> (NC_007795.1) was generated using CGView server based on BLAST sequence similarities (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>). Each genome was represented by a different color and the darker areas in the circular genome showed a 100% sequence similarity with the reference genome, whereas the lighter areas showed a 70% sequence similarity.<fig id="Fig2"><label>Fig. 2</label><caption><p>Subsystem category distribution of <bold>(a)</bold> SA G5 and <bold>(b)</bold> SA H29 genomes. The genomes of SA G5 and SA H29 annotated using the RAST Server classified subsystems into 270 and 276 respectively. The green part in the bar-chart at the leftmost position corresponds to the percentage of proteins included and the pie-chart in the right panel demonstrates the subsystem category distribution</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="13205_2020_2387_Fig2_HTML" id="MO2"/></fig><fig id="Fig3"><label>Fig. 3</label><caption><p>Comprehensive comparative protein analysis of SA G5 and SA H29. <bold>a</bold> Venn diagram showing the distribution of shared orthologous clusters (core-genome) among the genomes. <bold>b</bold> Occurrence pattern of shared orthologous groups among SA G5 and SA H29. The pattern to the left indicates SA G5 and SA H29 genomes are in the clusters, the number of clusters shared between genomes (cluster count), and the number of protein members in the shared clusters (protein count). <bold>c</bold> Showing the numbers of proteins, cluster genes, and singletons with respect to species</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="13205_2020_2387_Fig3_HTML" id="MO3"/></fig><fig id="Fig4"><label>Fig. 4</label><caption><p>Circular genome comparison map showing homologous chromosome of <italic>S. aureus</italic> genomes against <italic>S. aureus subsp. aureus NCTC 8325</italic> (NC_007795.1) genome using CGviewer. The inner scales designate the coordinates in mega-base pairs (Mbp). White spaces indicate regions with no identity to the reference genome and the genome features were indicated by the outermost (black) ring</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="13205_2020_2387_Fig4_HTML" id="MO4"/></fig></p><p id="Par29">Epidemiological characterizations of <italic>SCCmec</italic> type, <italic>spa</italic> type, and multilocus sequence type (MLST) are&#x000a0;presented in Table <xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref>. In silico analysis of ARGs using&#x000a0;CARD database revealed 18 genes related to antibiotic resistance and among them, 16 genes were shared which are responsible for the resistance against&#x000a0;methicillin (<italic>mecA</italic>), beta-lactams (<italic>blaZ</italic>), fluoroquinolone (<italic>norA, gyrA,</italic> and <italic>gyrB</italic>), tetracycline (<italic>tet-38</italic>), glycylcycline (<italic>mepA</italic>), multidrug and toxic compound (<italic>mepR</italic>), fluoroquinolone and acridine dye (<italic>arlS</italic> and <italic>arlR),</italic> tetracycline, penam, cephalosporin, glycylcycline, rifamycin, phenicol, triclosan and fluoroquinolone (<italic>mgrA</italic>), daptomycin (<italic>clsA</italic>), diaminopyrimidine (<italic>dfrC</italic>), nitroimidazole (<italic>msbA</italic>), rifamycin (<italic>rpoB32</italic>) and defensin (<italic>mprF</italic>). In addition, genes that provide&#x000a0;resistance against&#x000a0;macrolide, lincosamide, streptogramin (e<italic>mrA</italic>) were detected in the SA H29 genome. <italic>In-silico</italic> identification of ARGs and the results of <italic>in-vitro</italic> AST (for erythromycin, vancomycin, and beta-lactam antibiotics) are in good agreement.</p><p id="Par30">The VFGs were predicted against the VFDB in the PATRIC annotation system. Genomic comparison of the two strains identified 78 genes that encode virulence factors of which 57 are common. These virulence factors are responsible for adherence, toxins production, antiphagocytosis, immune evasion, exoenzyme activity, iron uptake, and secretion system. Genomes annotation revealed common genes encoding MSCRAMMs <italic>i.e</italic>. adhesion (<italic>sdrC, sdrD</italic>, and <italic>sdrE</italic>) elastin binding protein (<italic>ebps</italic>), polysaccharide intercellular adhesion proteins (<italic>icaA</italic>, <italic>icaB</italic>, <italic>icaC</italic>, <italic>icaD</italic>, and <italic>icaR</italic>), clumping factor (<italic>clfB</italic>) and cell wall anchored protein (<italic>sasH</italic>). The genome of SA H29 isolate harbored all these genes extended with additional genes encoding clumping factor A and B (<italic>clfA</italic> and <italic>clfB</italic>), fibronectin-binding protein A (<italic>fnbA</italic>), serine-aspartate repeat-containing proteins (<italic>sdrC</italic> and <italic>sdrD</italic>), and fibronectin-binding protein (<italic>fnbp</italic>), while the genome of SA G5 contained additional genes responsible for collagen adhesion (<italic>cna</italic>), and extracellular adherence protein (<italic>eap</italic>/<italic>map</italic>).</p><p id="Par31">Several hemolysin toxin genes such as alpha (<italic>hla</italic>), beta (<italic>hlb</italic>), delta (<italic>hld</italic>) and gamma A, B, and C (<italic>hlgA, hlgC</italic>, and <italic>hlgB</italic>) were identified in both the strains. Bicomponent leukotoxins, leukocidin <italic>lukE</italic>, and <italic>lukD</italic> genes were identified in the SA H29 genome. In the sequenced genomes 10 Staphylococcal enterotoxins (SEs) types were detected. The most prevalent enterotoxin genes, <italic>sea</italic>, and <italic>seb</italic> were presented in SA H29. The genome of SA G5 possessed 8 enterotoxin gene types such as <italic>sec</italic>, <italic>sec3</italic>, <italic>seg</italic>, sei, <italic>sel</italic>, <italic>sem, seo,</italic> and <italic>seu</italic>. Toxin genes involved in immune evasions such as IgG-binding proteins (<italic>sbi</italic> and <italic>spa</italic>), staphylococcal complement inhibitor (<italic>scn</italic>), and staphylokinase (<italic>sak</italic>) were present in both genomes. Chemotaxis-inhibiting protein (CHIPS) encoded by <italic>chp</italic> was identified in the SA G5 genome. The antiphagocytosis capsular stereotype encoding genes such as <italic>cap5C, cap5D, cap5F, cap5G, cap5O, cap5P, cap8M</italic>, and <italic>cap8N</italic> were present in both genomes, however, <italic>cap5E</italic> gene was detected in SA H29 genome. Moreover, capsular stereotype 8 genes (<italic>cap8E</italic> and <italic>cap8H</italic>) were detected in SA G5 genomes. <italic>S. aureus</italic> secret ESAT-6-like proteins consist of eight genes cluster namely <italic>esxA, esxB, esaA, esaB, esaC, essA, essB,</italic> and <italic>essC</italic>. These eight secretary system genes were identified in both genomes. Several exoenzyme encoding genes namely staphylocoagulase (<italic>coa</italic>), catalase (<italic>katA</italic>), hyaluronidase (<italic>hysA</italic>), von Willebrand factor binding protein (<italic>vwb</italic>), zinc metalloproteinase aureolysin (<italic>aur</italic>), V8 protease/glutamyl endopeptidase (<italic>sspA</italic>), staphopain B (<italic>sspB</italic>), staphostatin B (<italic>sspC</italic>) and lipase (<italic>geh</italic>) were present in both genomes. Genes involved in iron uptake mechanism such as <italic>isdA, isdB, isdC, isdD, isdE, isdF, srtB,</italic> and <italic>isdG</italic> that encodes for cell surface protein, cell surface receptor, cell wall anchor protein, heme-transporter component, high-affinity heme-uptake system protein, heme&#x02013;iron transport system permease protein, sortase B and heme-degrading monooxygenase/staphylobilin-producing respectively, were identified in both genomes.</p><p id="Par32">The putative plasmids were identified in nonaligned contigs that displayed an unexpected high coverage level after the genome assemblies. Two putative plasmids, p1H29 and p2H29 of 17,165&#x000a0;bp and 9020&#x000a0;bp lengths, respectively were identified in nonaligned contigs (scaffolds 2 and 3) of SA H29 genome, and these two plasmids constitute <italic>rep20</italic> and <italic>rep7C</italic> type genes. Plasmid p1H29 has and showed 44.20% and 57.34% sequence coverage with plasmids pBU108b (KF831356.1) and pPS00089.1A.1 (NZ_CP022911.1) respectively. Plasmid p2H29 has a length of and showed 23.42% and 23.45% sequence coverage with plasmid: II (LT671860.1), and UP_1395 plasmid (NZ_CP047821.1) respectively. Identified plasmid p1H29 carried genes encoding cadmium resistance (CadD) and transportation (CadX) proteins, and enterotoxins (EntA, EntD and EntG). Identified plasmid, p2H29 has <italic>blaZ</italic> (beta-lactamase), <italic>blaR,</italic> and <italic>mecI</italic> genes that conferred resistance to penicillin. The identified plasmids of <italic>S. aureus</italic> encode no transfer factors; thus, these plasmids may transfer via bacteriophage generalized transduction (McCarthy and Lindsay <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR88">2012</xref>).</p><p id="Par33">A comparative phylogenetic relationship was analyzed using three different gene sequences (viz., 16S rRNA genes, SNPs, and genes encoding core protein) to compare at the strain level. The phylogenetic tree generated using 16S rRNA gene sequences showed that SA G5 and SA H29 strains are highly similar and grouped them in the same group (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>b), however, the phylogenetic tree prepared from the SNP sequences and protein-coding gene sequences grouped them differently suggesting that 16S rRNA gene sequences are not sufficient to discriminate them on the strain level, possibly due to the low resolution of their evolutionary relationships (Konstantinidis and Tiedje <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR72">2007</xref>). It is interesting that both these methods and ANI values support each other and can be useful in distinguishing the genomes even in the strain level (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>b, c).<fig id="Fig5"><label>Fig. 5</label><caption><p>Comparative phylogenetic analysis of SA G5 and SA H29 strains with their closely related <italic>S. aureus</italic> strains. <bold>a</bold> Neighbor-joining tree prepared from the 16S rRNA gene sequences of SA G5, SA H29, and other related strains. <italic>Bacillus cereus</italic> ATCC 14,579 was used as an out-group and branch values are calculated from 500 bootstrap replicates. <bold>b</bold> Maximum likelihood (ML) tree based on all shared proteins (core) obtained from the <italic>S. aureus</italic> genome sequences, where <italic>B. cereus</italic> ATCC14579 was used as an out-group. The ML tree was prepared with the help of RAxML program. <bold>c</bold> Phylogeny tree based on the concatenated alignment of the high-quality SNPs using CSI phylogeny tool</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="13205_2020_2387_Fig5_HTML" id="MO5"/></fig></p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec21"><title>Discussion</title><p id="Par34">In the present study thirty-five European <italic>S. aureus</italic> clinical isolates were characterized by several different typing methods. The data generated from typing results along with virulence genes detection were evaluated through cluster analysis. Antibiotic susceptibility test and detection of <italic>mecA</italic> gene result showed 33 (94.28%) strains were MRSA while 2 (5.72%) strains were MSSA. Such a validation process was reported by other researchers (Skov et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR118">2006</xref>; Kumurya <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR76">2015</xref>). Among the tested strains, 26 strains (71.43%) were found to be resistant to erythromycin. Prevalence of erythromycin-resistant strains collected from Hungary representing 90.47% in a good agreement with previous data (Szab&#x000f3; et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR124">2009</xref>). It was also reported that the frequency of erythromycin-resistance during 2010&#x02013;2015 was 72% in Germany (Walter et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR129">2017</xref>) and 60% in Greece (Stefanaki et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR119">2017</xref>). However, in the present study, no vancomycin-resistant strains were found which is supported by the observations of previous studies (Szab&#x000f3; et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR124">2009</xref>; Chaudhari et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">2014</xref>). Vancomycin kills Gram-positive bacteria by interfering with peptidoglycan synthesis and peptidoglycan assembly (McGuinness et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR90">2017</xref>). The vancomycin susceptibility can be helpful in the treatment of MRSA infections. The resistance of <italic>S. aureus</italic> to vancomycin is governed by many factors. Previous studies have shown that point mutation in different regulatory loci associated with cell wall metabolism including two-component regulatory systems (guanylate kinase gene (<italic>gmk</italic>); <italic>walRK</italic>, <italic>graSR,</italic> and <italic>vraSR</italic>) resulted in vancomycin-resistant <italic>S. aureus</italic> strains (McAleese et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR87">2006</xref>; Howden et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR56">2008</xref>; Cui et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">2009</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">2010</xref>; Cameron et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">2012</xref>; Shekarabi et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR113">2017</xref>). In addition to cell wall thickening, altered surface protein profile, enhanced capsule, and <italic>agr</italic> gene dysfunction are also found to be the cause of the generation of vancomycin-resistant <italic>S. aureus</italic>. The presence of the <italic>vanA</italic> operon is also found to confer vancomycin-resistant (P&#x000e9;richon and Courvalin <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR104">2009</xref>; McGuinness et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR90">2017</xref>). Also, it was observed that vancomycin-susceptibility in MRSA due to the activation of the WalRK two-component regulatory system (Cameron et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">2016</xref>). The stains of the present study may neither have these mutations or cell wall-related modifications nor do they carry the genes required for vancomycin resistance and thus showed susceptible phenotype. However, a detailed study will be required to confirm the presence or absence of these factors.</p><p id="Par35">Some of the MRSA strains produce PVL, encoded by two genes, <italic>lukS-PV</italic>, and <italic>lukF-PV</italic> which have been shown to play a role in the pathogenicity of <italic>S. aureus</italic> by provoking necrosis, accelerating apoptosis and destruction of polymorphonuclear and mononuclear-cells, thereby contributing to morbidity and mortality (Lina et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR78">1999</xref>). It was reported that the low prevalence of <italic>pvl</italic> has found 5% and 4.9% in MRSA strains isolated from France and the UK respectively (Holmes et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR54">2005</xref>). In the present study, 24.24% (8/33) strains were found positive to the <italic>pvl</italic> gene. Among these strains, three carried <italic>SCCmec</italic> type IV and one classified as <italic>SCCmec</italic> type V, however, four strains carried <italic>SCCmec</italic> II (Table <xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref>). According to previous reports, MRSA strains belong to <italic>SCCmec</italic> types I, II, and III are dominant among the HA-MRSA, while <italic>SCCmec</italic> types IV and V characteristic of CA-MRSA (Monecke et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR93">2011</xref>; Chua et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">2014</xref>). In the present study, we found that <italic>SCCmec</italic> type II prevalence (12.12%) was higher in comparison with other <italic>SCCmec</italic> types. It was also reported that <italic>SCCmec</italic> type II usually presents in multidrug-resistant MRSA strains (Ito et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR62">2001</xref>; Hiramatsu et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51">2001</xref>) and were dominant outside European countries (Kilic et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR71">2006</xref>; Makgotlho et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR84">2009</xref>; de Oliveira et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">2015</xref>). Our data related to <italic>SCCmec</italic> type IV showed a higher prevalence (27.6%). The reason behind this observation is probably due to the easy acquisition of short size <italic>SCCmec</italic> type IV cassette (Robinson and Enright <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR108">2004</xref>). Even though the representation of non-typeable <italic>SCCmec</italic> in our case complies with the previous finding (Makgotlho et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR84">2009</xref>), a few non-typeable <italic>SCCmec</italic> can be reduced by applying the new <italic>SCCmec</italic> cassette detection (Kaya et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR69">2018</xref>). Some of the MRSA strains harbored <italic>SCCmec</italic> IVa showed signs of <italic>pvl</italic> gene negative (Table <xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref>), which is similar to the finding, reported earlier (Moroney et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR95">2007</xref>). Our data related to <italic>pvl</italic> gene detection revealed that MRSA strains harboring <italic>SCCmec</italic> IVb and <italic>SCCmec</italic> IVd were found negative. Our finding also supports the idea that the harboring bacteriophage <italic>pvl</italic> gene by MRSA strains may not be a promising marker for CA-MRSA (Rossney et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR110">2007</xref>). This conclusion is supported by other studies about <italic>SCCmec</italic> typing for the classification of HA-MRSA and CA-MRSA (Monecke et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR93">2011</xref>; Chua et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">2014</xref>). Taken together, our finding suggested that the <italic>SCCmec</italic> typing method is more informative in problem-solving approaches (control and prevent infections caused by MRSA strains) for the clinicians and epidemiologists.</p><p id="Par36"><italic>S. aureus</italic> secretes the coagulase enzyme, a polypeptide that helps promote the clotting of plasma or blood (Cheng et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">2010</xref>). The <italic>coa</italic> gene shows heterogenicity in the 81&#x02009;base-pair long tandem repeats region differing in number and location of restriction sites among the <italic>S. aureus</italic> isolates (Goh et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">1992</xref>; Schwarzkopf and Karch <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR111">1994</xref>). The assay based on PCR amplification of the <italic>coa</italic> gene followed by RFLP was used to differentiate among the geographically diverse MRSA strains. This technique is simple, rapid, specific, inexpensive, and reproducible; allowing early recognition of an epidemic strain in a hospital setting (Martineau et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR86">1996</xref>; Hookey et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55">1998</xref>; Shopsin et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR115">2000</xref>; Mahmoudi et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR83">2017</xref>). In this study, <italic>coa</italic>-PCR typing yielded seven different amplicons in size range from 550 to 800&#x000a0;bp. Among 15 <italic>S. aureus</italic> strains, the highest occurrence size is 700&#x000a0;bp (33.33%) as shown in Table 4, however, it was earlier reported that 600&#x000a0;bp amplicon is the most predominant (Mahmoudi et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR83">2017</xref>). Discrimination of <italic>coa</italic> gene-specific amplicon pattern was further improved by HaeIII restriction enzyme digestion, which yielded 11 types of patterns with DI of 0.9619. Our data were in good agreement with the previous result in which DI was improved by digestion (Janwithayanuchit et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR66">2006</xref>). <italic>S. aureus</italic> produces protein A, an antiphagocytic protein that is coded by the <italic>spa</italic> gene (Shakeri et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR112">2010</xref>). The analysis of <italic>spa</italic>-sequence revealed high diversity, however, two strains belonged to <italic>spa</italic>-type t008, and another two were classified to <italic>spa</italic>-type t062 (Supplementary Table 3). In a previous study conducted on German, <italic>S. aureus</italic> isolates reported that t003 and t008 were predominant <italic>spa</italic> types (Strommenger et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR122">2008</xref>). Also, a recently published article stated that t008 was the most prevalent <italic>spa</italic> type in Europe and America (Asadollahi et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">2018</xref>). The <italic>spa</italic>-PCR typing method produced eleven different genotypes with variable amplicons size ranges from 335 to 560&#x000a0;bp and revealed 0.9429 DI, which provides similar DI with <italic>coa</italic>-HaeIII RFLP method which is supported by a previous study (Omar et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR99">2014</xref>). This study suggested that <italic>spa</italic>-typing has performed better than other molecular typing methods and showed better DP. This typing method is useful for studying the genetic diversity of <italic>S. aureus</italic> for the epidemiological tracking of the source of infections (Koreen et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR73">2004</xref>) and offering several advantages in comparison with alternatives methods, such as a publicly available comprehensive and curated database for analyzing <italic>spa</italic> sequence with standard nomenclature (Strommenger et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR122">2008</xref>).</p><p id="Par37">In a good agreement with previous data, we found that not all <italic>ica</italic>-positive isolates produce biofilms (M&#x000f8;retr&#x000f8; et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR94">2003</xref>; Fitzpatrick et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">2005</xref>), however, the clinical origin of the used <italic>S. aureus</italic> isolates was supported by the presence of <italic>icaADBC</italic> and <italic>icaR</italic>, indicating the ability to discriminate between the normal floras and virulence strains representatives (Galdbart et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">2000</xref>). In this study, we observed that 66% of the isolates harbor two <italic>fnb</italic> genes almost similar to the results reported by Peacock et al. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR102">2000</xref>) for European <italic>S. aureus</italic> strains. However, the presence of <italic>fnb</italic> genes in an isolate does not guarantee the biofilm-forming ability of the isolate.</p><p id="Par38">In this study, the <italic>cna</italic> gene was found to be present in 53.3% isolates. Earlier, the prevalence of the <italic>cna</italic> gene was reported in a range from 22 to 56.5% (Peacock et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR103">1999</xref>; Rohde et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR109">2007</xref>; Zmantar et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR136">2008</xref>), The <italic>clfA</italic>, <italic>clfB,</italic> and <italic>epbs</italic> genes play an initial role for biofilm development (Ghasemian et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">2015</xref>), however, our data showed that the presence or absence of these genes does not represent a clear discriminative marker for differentiating strains in terms of biofilm-forming ability.</p><p id="Par39">The grouping of the isolates based on the results of <italic>coa-Hae</italic>III<italic>-</italic>RFLP and <italic>spa</italic> gene sequences produced different groups with different strains. Therefore, the results of all the biochemical and genotypic tests were used to prepare a dendrogram followed by PCA analysis. The dendrogram generated from the combined data of phenotypic and genotypic methods showed that the strain SA G5 and SA H29 collected from different geographical regions clustered together in the same group (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>b). Similar results were also obtained from the PCA analysis <bold>(</bold>Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>c<bold>).</bold> To gain a better idea about their genetic background and closeness between the two strains, both strains were subjected to whole-genome sequencing and analysis. Comparative genome analysis of these two strains revealed 97.03% OrthoANI identity with a genetic distance of 0.0308, sharing 2344 gene clusters. The genes for virulence, resistance, plasmids, pathogenicity islands, prophage-like elements, and mobile elements are encoded by singleton genes of the SA H29 genome, suggesting that these singleton genes might be inherited through horizontal gene transfer (HGT) events (Lindsay <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR79">2014</xref>). Besides, the genes (5 genes) encoding lanthionine biosynthesis proteins were also found as singleton genes in the SA H29 genome. The presence of such genes influences the niche adaptation, pathogenesis, and contributes to evolution (Hacker and Carniel <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47">2001</xref>). The map revealed a small gap with colorless region against the reference genome, which is due to the change in GC % content, this change in GC % content is due to the acquisition of gene through HGT (Hayek <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50">2013</xref>) and the GC skewed regions indicated the regions where HGT occurred.</p><p id="Par40">The 16S rRNA gene sequence-based phylogenetic analysis has been used widely to study the evolutionary relationships of microbes (Janda and Abbott <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR64">2002</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR63">2007</xref>; Goswami et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">2017</xref>). The phylogenetic tree generated using 16S rRNA gene sequences of the two isolates viz<italic>.</italic>, SA G5, and SA H29 also clustered them in the same group whereas the other publicly available isolates were found in other groups (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>a) supporting the observations of the dendrogram and PCA analysis. However, the other two phylogenetic trees generated based on the SNP and core protein-coding gene sequences grouped the strain SA G5 and SA H29 in different groups. This indicated that these novel approaches of phylogenetic analysis using core protein-coding gene sequences and SNPs (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>b, c) are more powerful than the16S rRNA gene sequence-based phylogeny and are generally acceptable to distinguish the genomes even in the genus or species level, higher strain-level resolution. It has been reported that 16S rRNA gene sequence analysis is not powerful enough to discern clearly among the closely related species (Fox et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">1992</xref>). Overall, the results of the present study indicate that whole-genome sequence analysis is more powerful than the individual genotypic test and provide better insight into the taxonomic and genotypic background of the test isolates.</p></sec><sec id="Sec22"><title>Conclusion</title><p id="Par41">Methicillin-resistant <italic>S. aureus</italic> is the leading cause of nosocomial and community infections and the emergence of hypervirulent strains and becoming a greater threat to the public. The high-frequency emergence of antibiotic-resistant could be due to the acquisition of resistance determinants such as plasmids, integrons, and transposons through horizontal or vertical gene transfer and partly by improper administration of antibiotics. The phenotypic and genotypic characterizations are important for identifying the risk factors associated with <italic>S. aureus</italic> infections and useful to monitor and control the circulation or transmission of these strains. But a comparative analysis of the pathogens based on the NGS-based genome sequencing technique could extend our understanding of pathogenesis and evolution at the molecular level and has the potential to a breakthrough in diagnosis, treatment, and infection control. In this study, the comparative genomic analysis revealed that niche-specific differences between the <italic>S. aureus</italic> strains in terms of genes and genes clusters that are related to amino acid metabolism, carbohydrate metabolism, cell envelope biogenesis, defense mechanisms, secondary metabolism, and phage-like elements. The difference in the presence of resistance genes (penicillin, methicillin, erythromycin, aminoglycoside, streptothricin acetyltransferase, and cadmium), VFGs (<italic>hlb</italic>, <italic>chp</italic>, <italic>scn</italic>, <italic>ear</italic>, <italic>qsa, sea</italic>, <italic>seb</italic>, <italic>sel</italic>, <italic>seg</italic>, <italic>lukD</italic>, <italic>lukE</italic>, <italic>sasH</italic>, <italic>clfA</italic>, and <italic>eap</italic>), plasmids and phage-related genes between the strains were also observed which may be due to the events like HGT and homologous recombination. Also, the comparative genome analysis provides high resolution to distinguish between the closely related sequenced strains which are indistinguishable by <italic>SCCmec</italic> and <italic>spa</italic> typing. The whole-genome analysis technique is a feasible tool to improve clinical diagnostic investigations of clinical infectious diseases in real-time and provides the goal of improving patient care.</p></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material"><title>Electronic supplementary material</title><sec id="Sec23"><p>Below is the link to the electronic supplementary material.<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM1"><media xlink:href="13205_2020_2387_MOESM1_ESM.docx"><caption><p>Supplementary file1 (DOCX 11382 kb)</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM2"><media xlink:href="13205_2020_2387_MOESM2_ESM.csv"><caption><p>Supplementary file2 (CSV 3 kb)</p></caption></media></supplementary-material></p></sec></sec></body><back><ack><p>This work was partially supported by the European Regional Development Fund (ERDF) under the grant numbers GINOP-2.3.2-15-2016-00021 and GINOP-2.3.2-15-2016-00047. The authors acknowledge the anonymous reviewers for their valuable suggestions that helped improve the quality of the manuscript.</p></ack><notes notes-type="funding-information"><title>Funding</title><p>Open access funding provided by University of P&#x000e9;cs.</p></notes><notes notes-type="ethics"><title>Compliance with ethical standards</title><notes id="FPar1" notes-type="COI-statement"><title>Conflict of interest</title><p id="Par42">The authors have no conflict of interest.</p></notes></notes><ref-list id="Bib1"><title>References</title><ref id="CR1"><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Al-Obaidi MMJ, Suhaili Z, Desa MNM (2018) Genotyping approaches for identification and characterization of <italic>Staphylococcus aureus</italic>. IntechOpen: London, UK, 2018</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR2"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Al-Tam</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Brunel</surname><given-names>A-S</given-names></name><name><surname>Bouzinbi</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>DNAGear&#x02014;a free software for spa type identification in <italic>Staphylococcus aureus</italic></article-title><source>BMC Res Notes</source><year>2012</year><volume>5</volume><fpage>642</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1756-0500-5-642</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23164452</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR3"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ali</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name><name><surname>Isa</surname><given-names>NM</given-names></name><name><surname>Abedelrhman</surname><given-names>FM</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Genomic analysis of methicillin-resistant <italic>Staphylococcus aureus</italic> strain SO-1977 from Sudan</article-title><source>BMC Microbiol</source><year>2019</year><volume>19</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>9</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12866-019-1470-2</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30616583</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR4"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Alkharsah</surname><given-names>KR</given-names></name><name><surname>Rehman</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Alnimr</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Molecular typing of MRSA isolates by spa and PFGE</article-title><source>J King Saud Univ Sci</source><year>2019</year><volume>31</volume><fpage>999</fpage><lpage>1004</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jksus.2018.07.018</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR5"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Appelbaum</surname><given-names>PC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Microbiology of antibiotic resistance in <italic>Staphylococcus aureus</italic></article-title><source>Clin Infect Dis</source><year>2007</year><volume>45</volume><fpage>S165</fpage><lpage>S170</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1086/519474</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17712742</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR6"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Arciola</surname><given-names>CR</given-names></name><name><surname>Baldassarri</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Montanaro</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Presence of icaA and icaD genes and slime production in a collection of staphylococcal strains from catheter-associated infections</article-title><source>J Clin Microbiol</source><year>2001</year><volume>39</volume><fpage>2151</fpage><lpage>2156</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/JCM.39.6.2151-2156.2001</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11376050</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR7"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Arciola</surname><given-names>CR</given-names></name><name><surname>Campoccia</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Baldassarri</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Detection of biofilm formation in <italic>Staphylococcus epidermidis</italic> from implant infections. Comparison of a PCR-method that recognizes the presence ofica genes with two classic phenotypic methods</article-title><source>J Biomed Mater Res Part A</source><year>2006</year><volume>76A</volume><fpage>425</fpage><lpage>430</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/jbm.a.30552</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR8"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Arciola</surname><given-names>CR</given-names></name><name><surname>Campoccia</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Ravaioli</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Montanaro</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Polysaccharide intercellular adhesin in biofilm: structural and regulatory aspects</article-title><source>Front Cell Infect Microbiol</source><year>2015</year><volume>5</volume><fpage>7</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fcimb.2015.00007</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25713785</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR9"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Asadollahi</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Farahani</surname><given-names>NN</given-names></name><name><surname>Mirzaii</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Distribution of the most prevalent spa types among clinical isolates of methicillin-resistant and -susceptible <italic>Staphylococcus aureus</italic> around the world: a review</article-title><source>Front Microbiol</source><year>2018</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>163</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fmicb.2018.00163</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29487578</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR10"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Aziz</surname><given-names>RK</given-names></name><name><surname>Bartels</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Best</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The RAST server: rapid annotations using subsystems technology</article-title><source>BMC Genomics</source><year>2008</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>75</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1471-2164-9-75</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18261238</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR11"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Baba</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Takeuchi</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Kuroda</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Genome and virulence determinants of high virulence community-acquired MRSA</article-title><source>Lancet</source><year>2002</year><volume>359</volume><fpage>1819</fpage><lpage>1827</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0140-6736(02)08713-5</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12044378</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR12"><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bergey</surname><given-names>DH</given-names></name><name><surname>Holt</surname><given-names>JG</given-names></name></person-group><source>Bergey&#x02019;s manual of determinative bacteriology, Ninth edit</source><year>1994</year><publisher-loc>Baltimore</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Williams &#x00026; Wilkins, Philadelphia</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR13"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bosi</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Donati</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Galardini</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>MeDuSa: a multi-draft based scaffolder</article-title><source>Bioinformatics</source><year>2015</year><volume>31</volume><fpage>2443</fpage><lpage>2451</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/bioinformatics/btv171</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25810435</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR14"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cameron</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name><name><surname>Jiang</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name><name><surname>Kostoulias</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Vancomycin susceptibility in methicillin-resistant <italic>Staphylococcus aureus</italic>is mediated by YycHI activation of the WalRK essential two-component regulatory system</article-title><source>Sci Rep</source><year>2016</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>11</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/srep30823</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28442746</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR15"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cameron</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name><name><surname>Ward</surname><given-names>DV</given-names></name><name><surname>Kostoulias</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Serine/Threonine phosphatase Stp1 contributes to reduced susceptibility to vancomycin and virulence in <italic>Staphylococcus aureus</italic></article-title><source>J Infect Dis</source><year>2012</year><volume>205</volume><fpage>1677</fpage><lpage>1687</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/infdis/jis252</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22492855</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR16"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Carattoli</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Zankari</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Garc&#x000ed;a-Fern&#x000e1;ndez</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>In silico detection and typing of plasmids using plasmidfinder and plasmid multilocus sequence typing</article-title><source>Antimicrob Agents Chemother</source><year>2014</year><volume>58</volume><fpage>3895</fpage><lpage>3903</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/AAC.02412-14</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24777092</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR17"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chaieb</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Mahdouani</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Bakhrouf</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Detection of icaA and icaD loci by polymerase chain reaction and biofilm formation by <italic>Staphylococcus epidermidis</italic> isolated from dialysate and needles in a dialysis unit</article-title><source>J Hosp Infect</source><year>2005</year><volume>61</volume><fpage>225</fpage><lpage>230</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jhin.2005.05.014</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16165246</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR18"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chan</surname><given-names>CX</given-names></name><name><surname>Beiko</surname><given-names>RG</given-names></name><name><surname>Ragan</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Lateral transfer of genes and gene fragments in staphylococcus extends beyond mobile elements</article-title><source>J Bacteriol</source><year>2011</year><volume>193</volume><fpage>3964</fpage><lpage>3977</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/JB.01524-10</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21622749</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR19"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chaudhari</surname><given-names>CN</given-names></name><name><surname>Tandel</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Grover</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>In vitro vancomycin susceptibility amongst methicillin resistant <italic>Staphylococcus aureus</italic></article-title><source>Med J Armed Forces India</source><year>2014</year><volume>70</volume><fpage>215</fpage><lpage>219</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.mjafi.2013.11.008</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25378772</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR20"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Zheng</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>VFDB 2016: hierarchical and refined dataset for big data analysis&#x02014;10 years on</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res</source><year>2016</year><volume>44</volume><fpage>D694</fpage><lpage>D697</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/gkv1239</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26578559</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR21"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cheng</surname><given-names>AG</given-names></name><name><surname>McAdow</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>HK</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Contribution of Coagulases towards <italic>Staphylococcus aureus</italic> disease and protective immunity</article-title><source>PLoS Pathog</source><year>2010</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>e1001036</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.ppat.1001036</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20700445</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR22"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chua</surname><given-names>KYL</given-names></name><name><surname>Howden</surname><given-names>BP</given-names></name><name><surname>Jiang</surname><given-names>J-H</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Population genetics and the evolution of virulence in <italic>Staphylococcus aureu</italic></article-title><source>Infect Genet Evol</source><year>2014</year><volume>21</volume><fpage>554</fpage><lpage>562</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.meegid.2013.04.026</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23628638</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR23"><mixed-citation publication-type="other">CLSI (2014) Performance standards for antimicrobial susceptibility testing; twenty-fourth informational supplement. CLSI document M100-S24. Clinical and laboratory standards institute, Wayne, PA, USA</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR24"><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Collee</surname><given-names>JG</given-names></name><name><surname>Fraser</surname><given-names>AG</given-names></name><name><surname>Marmion</surname><given-names>BP</given-names></name></person-group><source>Mackie and McCartney Practical Medical Microbiology</source><year>1996</year><edition>14</edition><publisher-loc>India</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Elsevier Health Sciences</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR25"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cui</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Isii</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Fukuda</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>An RpoB mutation confers dual heteroresistance to daptomycin and vancomycin in <italic>Staphylococcus aureus</italic></article-title><source>Antimicrob Agents Chemother</source><year>2010</year><volume>54</volume><fpage>5222</fpage><lpage>5233</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/AAC.00437-10</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20837752</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR26"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cui</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Neoh</surname><given-names>HM</given-names></name><name><surname>Shoji</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Hiramatsu</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Contribution of vraSR and graSR point mutations to vancomycin resistance in vancomycin-intermediate <italic>Staphylococcus aureus</italic></article-title><source>Antimicrob Agents Chemother</source><year>2009</year><volume>53</volume><fpage>1231</fpage><lpage>1234</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/AAC.01173-08</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19124662</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR27"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Darling</surname><given-names>AE</given-names></name><name><surname>Mau</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Perna</surname><given-names>NT</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>ProgressiveMauve: multiple genome alignment with gene gain loss and rearrangement</article-title><source>PLoS ONE</source><year>2010</year><volume>5</volume><fpage>e11147</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0011147</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20593022</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR28"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>de Oliveira</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name><name><surname>van der Heijden</surname><given-names>IM</given-names></name><name><surname>Golding</surname><given-names>GR</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title><italic>Staphylococcus aureus</italic> isolates colonizing and infecting cirrhotic and liver-transplantation patients: comparison of molecular typing and virulence factors</article-title><source>BMC Microbiol</source><year>2015</year><volume>15</volume><fpage>264</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12866-015-0598-y</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26572493</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR29"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Deka</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Goswami</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Das</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Bacterial exopolysaccharide promotes acid tolerance in <italic>Bacillus amyloliquefaciens</italic> and improves soil aggregation</article-title><source>Mol Biol Rep</source><year>2019</year><volume>46</volume><fpage>1079</fpage><lpage>1091</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11033-018-4566-0</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30554311</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR30"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Denis</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Route of transmission of <italic>Staphylococcus aureus</italic></article-title><source>Lancet Infect Dis</source><year>2017</year><volume>17</volume><fpage>124</fpage><lpage>125</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S1473-3099(16)30512-6</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27863960</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR31"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Donlan</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name><name><surname>Costerton</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Biofilms: survival mechanisms of clinically relevant microorganisms</article-title><source>Clin Microbiol Rev</source><year>2002</year><volume>15</volume><fpage>167</fpage><lpage>193</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/CMR.15.2.167-193.2002</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11932229</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR32"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Du</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Ding</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Molecular characterization and antimicrobial susceptibility of nasal <italic>Staphylococcus aureus</italic> isolates from a Chinese Medical College Campus</article-title><source>PLoS ONE</source><year>2011</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>e27328</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0027328</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22114670</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR33"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dufr&#x000ea;ne</surname><given-names>YF</given-names></name><name><surname>Viljoen</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Binding strength of gram-positive bacterial adhesins</article-title><source>Front Microbiol</source><year>2020</year><volume>11</volume><fpage>1457</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fmicb.2020.01457</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32670256</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR34"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Faria</surname><given-names>NA</given-names></name><name><surname>Carrico</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Oliveira</surname><given-names>DC</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Analysis of typing methods for epidemiological surveillance of both methicillin-resistant and methicillin-susceptible <italic>Staphylococcus aureus</italic> strains</article-title><source>J Clin Microbiol</source><year>2008</year><volume>46</volume><fpage>136</fpage><lpage>144</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/JCM.01684-07</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17989188</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR35"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fitzpatrick</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Humphreys</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>O&#x02019;Gara</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Evidence for icaADBC-independent biofilm development mechanism in methicillin-resistant <italic>Staphylococcus aureus</italic> clinical isolates</article-title><source>J Clin Microbiol</source><year>2005</year><volume>43</volume><fpage>1973</fpage><lpage>1976</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/JCM.43.4.1973-1976.2005</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15815035</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR36"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Foster</surname><given-names>TJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Geoghegan</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Ganesh</surname><given-names>VK</given-names></name><name><surname>H&#x000f6;&#x000f6;k</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Adhesion, invasion and evasion: the many functions of the surface proteins of <italic>Staphylococcus aureus</italic></article-title><source>Nat Rev Microbiol</source><year>2014</year><volume>12</volume><fpage>49</fpage><lpage>62</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nrmicro3161</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24336184</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR37"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fox</surname><given-names>GE</given-names></name><name><surname>Wisotzkey</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name><name><surname>Jurtshuk</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>How close is close: 16S rRNA sequence identity may not be sufficient to guarantee species identity</article-title><source>Int J Syst Bacteriol</source><year>1992</year><volume>42</volume><fpage>166</fpage><lpage>170</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1099/00207713-42-1-166</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1371061</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR38"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Galata</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Fehlmann</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Backes</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Keller</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>PLSDB: a resource of complete bacterial plasmids</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res</source><year>2019</year><volume>47</volume><fpage>D195</fpage><lpage>D202</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/gky1050</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30380090</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR39"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Galdbart</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Allignet</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Tung</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Screening for <italic>Staphylococcus epidermidis</italic> markers discriminating between skin-flora strains and those responsible for infections of joint prostheses</article-title><source>J Infect Dis</source><year>2000</year><volume>182</volume><fpage>351</fpage><lpage>355</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1086/315660</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10882623</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR40"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Garrett</surname><given-names>TR</given-names></name><name><surname>Bhakoo</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Bacterial adhesion and biofilms on surfaces</article-title><source>Prog Nat Sci</source><year>2008</year><volume>18</volume><fpage>1049</fpage><lpage>1056</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.pnsc.2008.04.001</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR41"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ghasemian</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Peerayeh</surname><given-names>SN</given-names></name><name><surname>Bakhshi</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Mirzaee</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The microbial surface components recognizing adhesive matrix molecules (MSCRAMMs) genes among clinical isolates of <italic>Staphylococcus aureus</italic> from hospitalized children</article-title><source>Iran J Pathol</source><year>2015</year><volume>10</volume><fpage>258</fpage><lpage>264</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7508/ijp.2015.04.002</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26351495</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR42"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Goh</surname><given-names>SH</given-names></name><name><surname>Byrne</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><name><surname>Chow</surname><given-names>AW</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Molecular typing of <italic>Staphylococcus aureus</italic> on the basis of coagulase gene polymorphisms</article-title><source>J Clin Microbiol</source><year>1992</year><volume>30</volume><fpage>1642</fpage><lpage>1645</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/JCM.30.7.1642-1645.1992</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1352784</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR43"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Goswami</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Deka</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Das</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Diversity and functional properties of acid-tolerant bacteria isolated from tea plantation soil of Assam</article-title><source>3 Biotech</source><year>2017</year><volume>7</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>229</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s13205-017-0864-9</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28681289</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR44"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Goudarzi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Seyedjavadi</surname><given-names>SS</given-names></name><name><surname>Nasiri</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Molecular characteristics of methicillin-resistant <italic>Staphylococcus aureus</italic> (MRSA) strains isolated from patients with bacteremia based on MLST, SCCmec, spa, and agr locus types analysis</article-title><source>Microb Pathog</source><year>2017</year><volume>104</volume><fpage>328</fpage><lpage>335</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.micpath.2017.01.055</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28159661</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR45"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Grant</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name><name><surname>Stothard</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The CGView Server: a comparative genomics tool for circular genomes</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res</source><year>2008</year><volume>36</volume><fpage>W181</fpage><lpage>W184</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/gkn179</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18411202</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR46"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Grundmann</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Aanensen</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name><name><surname>van den Wijngaard</surname><given-names>CC</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Geographic distribution of <italic>Staphylococcus aureus </italic>causing invasive infections in Europe: a molecular-epidemiological analysis</article-title><source>PLoS Med</source><year>2010</year><volume>7</volume><fpage>e1000215</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pmed.1000215</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20084094</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR47"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hacker</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Carniel</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Ecological fitness, genomic islands and bacterial pathogenicity</article-title><source>EMBO Rep</source><year>2001</year><volume>2</volume><fpage>376</fpage><lpage>381</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/embo-reports/kve097</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11375927</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR48"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hammer</surname><given-names>&#x000d8;</given-names></name><name><surname>Harper</surname><given-names>DAT</given-names></name><name><surname>Ryan</surname><given-names>PD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>PAST: paleontological statistics software package for education and data analysis</article-title><source>Palaeontol Electron</source><year>2001</year><volume>4</volume><fpage>3</fpage><lpage>9</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR49"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Harmsen</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Claus</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Witte</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Typing of methicillin-resistant <italic>Staphylococcus aureus </italic>in a University Hospital setting by using novel software for spa repeat determination and database management</article-title><source>J Clin Microbiol</source><year>2003</year><volume>41</volume><fpage>5442</fpage><lpage>5448</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/JCM.41.12.5442-5448.2003</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14662923</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR50"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hayek</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Lateral transfer and GC content of bacterial resistant genes</article-title><source>Front Microbiol</source><year>2013</year><volume>4</volume><fpage>41</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fmicb.2013.00041</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23487592</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR51"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hiramatsu</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Cui</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Kuroda</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Ito</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The emergence and evolution of methicillin-resistant <italic>Staphylococcus aureus</italic></article-title><source>Trends Microbiol</source><year>2001</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>486</fpage><lpage>493</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0966-842X(01)02175-8</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11597450</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR52"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hisata</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Kuwahara-Arai</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Yamanoto</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Dissemination of methicillin-resistant staphylococci among healthy Japanese children</article-title><source>J Clin Microbiol</source><year>2005</year><volume>43</volume><fpage>3364</fpage><lpage>3372</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/JCM.43.7.3364-3372.2005</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16000461</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR53"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hoang</surname><given-names>TM</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Lindgren</surname><given-names>JK</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Transcriptional regulation of icaADBC by both IcaR and TcaR in <italic>Staphylococcus epidermidis</italic></article-title><source>J Bacteriol</source><year>2019</year><volume>201</volume><fpage>e00524</fpage><lpage>e618</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/JB.00524-18</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30602488</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR54"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Holmes</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Ganner</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>McGuane</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title><italic>Staphylococcus aureus</italic> isolates carrying panton-valentine Leucocidin genes in England and Wales: frequency, characterization, and association with clinical disease</article-title><source>J Clin Microbiol</source><year>2005</year><volume>43</volume><fpage>2384</fpage><lpage>2390</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/JCM.43.5.2384-2390.2005</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15872271</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR55"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hookey</surname><given-names>JV</given-names></name><name><surname>Richardson</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name><name><surname>Cookson</surname><given-names>BD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Molecular typing of <italic>Staphylococcus aureus</italic> based on PCR restriction fragment length polymorphism and DNA sequence analysis of the coagulase gene</article-title><source>J Clin Microbiol</source><year>1998</year><volume>36</volume><fpage>1083</fpage><lpage>1089</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/JCM.36.4.1083-1089.1998</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9542942</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR56"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Howden</surname><given-names>BP</given-names></name><name><surname>Stinear</surname><given-names>TP</given-names></name><name><surname>Allen</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Genomic analysis reveals a point mutation in the two-component sensor gene graS that leads to intermediate vancomycin resistance in clinical <italic>Staphylococcus aureus</italic></article-title><source>Antimicrob Agents Chemother</source><year>2008</year><volume>52</volume><fpage>3755</fpage><lpage>3762</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/AAC.01613-07</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18644967</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR57"><mixed-citation publication-type="other"><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://insilico.ehu.es/mini_tools/discriminatory_power/">https://insilico.ehu.es/mini_tools/discriminatory_power/</ext-link> Discriminatory power Calculator. Accessed 8 Feb 2019</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR58"><mixed-citation publication-type="other"><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://spa.ridom.de/">https://spa.ridom.de/</ext-link> Ridom SpaServer</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR59"><mixed-citation publication-type="other"><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://spatyper.fortinbras.us/">https://spatyper.fortinbras.us/</ext-link> spa Type Finder/Identifier. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://spatyper.fortinbras.us/">https://spatyper.fortinbras.us/</ext-link>. Accessed 8 Feb 2019</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR60"><mixed-citation publication-type="other"><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://cge.cbs.dtu.dk/services/CSIPhylogeny/">https://cge.cbs.dtu.dk/services/CSIPhylogeny/</ext-link> CSI Phylogeny 1.4 (Call SNPs &#x00026; Infer Phylogeny). Accessed 2 Mar 2019</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR61"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hughes</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name><name><surname>Friedman</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Nucleotide substitution and recombination at orthologous loci in <italic>Staphylococcus aureus</italic></article-title><source>J Bacteriol</source><year>2005</year><volume>187</volume><fpage>2698</fpage><lpage>2704</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/JB.187.8.2698-2704.2005</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15805516</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR62"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ito</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Katayama</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Asada</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Structural comparison of three types of staphylococcal cassette chromosome mec integrated in the chromosome in methicillin-resistant <italic>Staphylococcus aureus</italic></article-title><source>Antimicrob Agents Chemother</source><year>2001</year><volume>45</volume><fpage>1323</fpage><lpage>1336</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/AAC.45.5.1323-1336.2001</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11302791</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR63"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Janda</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Abbott</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>16S rRNA Gene sequencing for bacterial identification in the diagnostic laboratory: pluses, perils, and pitfalls</article-title><source>J Clin Microbiol</source><year>2007</year><volume>45</volume><fpage>2761</fpage><lpage>2764</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/JCM.01228-07</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17626177</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR64"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Janda</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Abbott</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Bacterial identification for publication: when is enough enough?</article-title><source>J Clin Microbiol</source><year>2002</year><volume>40</volume><fpage>1887</fpage><lpage>1891</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/JCM.40.6.1887-1891.2002</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12037039</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR65"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jansen</surname><given-names>WTM</given-names></name><name><surname>van der Bruggen</surname><given-names>JT</given-names></name><name><surname>Verhoef</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Fluit</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Bacterial resistance: a sensitive issue. complexity of the challenge and containment strategy in Europe</article-title><source>Drug Resist Updat</source><year>2006</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>123</fpage><lpage>133</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.drup.2006.06.002</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16807066</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR66"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Janwithayanuchit</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Ngam-Ululert</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Paungmoung</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Rangsipanuratn</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Epidemiologic study of methicillin-resistant <italic>Staphylococcus aureus</italic> by coagulase gene polymorphism</article-title><source>ScienceAsia</source><year>2006</year><volume>32</volume><fpage>127</fpage><lpage>132</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2306/scienceasia1513-1874.2006.32.127</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR67"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Karahan</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>&#x000c7;etinkaya</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Coagulase gene polymorphisms detected by PCR in <italic>Staphylococcus aureus</italic> isolated from subclinical bovine mastitis in Turkey</article-title><source>Vet J</source><year>2007</year><volume>174</volume><fpage>428</fpage><lpage>431</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.tvjl.2006.05.016</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16901735</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR68"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kareem</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name><name><surname>Aljubori</surname><given-names>SS</given-names></name><name><surname>Ali</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Novel determination of spa gene diversity and its molecular typing among <italic>Staphylococcus aureus</italic> Iraqi isolates obtained from different clinical samples</article-title><source>New Microbes New Infect</source><year>2020</year><volume>34</volume><fpage>100653</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.nmni.2020.100653</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32123566</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR69"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kaya</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Hasman</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Larsen</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>SCCmecFinder, a web-based tool for typing of staphylococcal cassette chromosome mec in <italic>Staphylococcus aureus</italic> using whole-genome sequence data</article-title><source>mSphere</source><year>2018</year><volume>3</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>e00612</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/mSphere.00612-17</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29468193</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR70"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Khoshkharam-Roodmajani</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Sarvari</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Bazargani</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Molecular typing of methicillin-resistant and methicillin-susceptible <italic>Staphylococcus aureus</italic> isolates from Shiraz teaching hospitals by PCR-RFLP of coagulase gene</article-title><source>Iran J Microbiol</source><year>2014</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>246</fpage><lpage>252</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25802708</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR71"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kilic</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Stratton</surname><given-names>CW</given-names></name><name><surname>Tang</surname><given-names>Y-W</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Antimicrobial susceptibility patterns and staphylococcal cassette chromosome mec types of, as well as panton-valentine leukocidin occurrence among, methicillin-resistant <italic>Staphylococcus aureus</italic> isolates from children and adults in middle Tennessee</article-title><source>J Clin Microbiol</source><year>2006</year><volume>44</volume><fpage>4436</fpage><lpage>4440</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/JCM.01546-06</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17065272</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR72"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Konstantinidis</surname><given-names>KT</given-names></name><name><surname>Tiedje</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Prokaryotic taxonomy and phylogeny in the genomic era: advancements and challenges ahead</article-title><source>Curr Opin Microbiol</source><year>2007</year><volume>10</volume><fpage>504</fpage><lpage>509</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.mib.2007.08.006</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17923431</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR73"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Koreen</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Ramaswamy</surname><given-names>SV</given-names></name><name><surname>Graviss</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>spa typing method for discriminating among <italic>Staphylococcus aureus</italic> isolates: implications for use of a single marker to detect genetic micro- and macro variation</article-title><source>J Clin Microbiol</source><year>2004</year><volume>42</volume><fpage>792</fpage><lpage>799</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/jcm.42.2.792-799.2004</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14766855</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR74"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>K&#x000f6;ser</surname><given-names>CU</given-names></name><name><surname>Ellington</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Cartwright</surname><given-names>EJP</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Routine use of microbial whole genome sequencing in diagnostic and public health microbiology</article-title><source>PLoS Pathog</source><year>2012</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>e1002824</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.ppat.1002824</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22876174</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR75"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kumar</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Stecher</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>MEGA X: molecular evolutionary genetics analysis across computing platforms</article-title><source>Mol Biol Evol</source><year>2018</year><volume>35</volume><fpage>1547</fpage><lpage>1549</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/molbev/msy096</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29722887</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR76"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kumurya</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>One step PCR for detection of <italic>Staphylococcus aureus</italic> specific sequence gene and mecA gene in Northwestern Nigerian hospitals</article-title><source>Antimicrob Resist Infect Control</source><year>2015</year><volume>4</volume><fpage>P196</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/2047-2994-4-S1-P196</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR77"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Le</surname><given-names>KY</given-names></name><name><surname>Park</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name><name><surname>Otto</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Immune evasion mechanisms of <italic>Staphylococcus epidermidis</italic> biofilm infection</article-title><source>Front Microbiol</source><year>2018</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>359</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fmicb.2018.00359</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29541068</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR78"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lina</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Pi&#x000e9;mont</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Godail-Gamot</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Involvement of Panton-Valentine leukocidin-producing <italic>Staphylococcus aureus</italic> in primary skin infections and pneumonia</article-title><source>Clin Infect</source><year>1999</year><volume>29</volume><fpage>1128</fpage><lpage>1132</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1086/313461</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR79"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lindsay</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title><italic>Staphylococcus aureus</italic> genomics and the impact of horizontal gene transfer</article-title><source>Int J Med Microbiol</source><year>2014</year><volume>304</volume><fpage>103</fpage><lpage>109</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ijmm.2013.11.010</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24439196</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR80"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lindsay</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Moore</surname><given-names>CE</given-names></name><name><surname>Day</surname><given-names>NP</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Microarrays reveal that each of the ten dominant lineages of <italic>Staphylococcus aureus</italic> has a unique combination of surface-associated and regulatory genes</article-title><source>J Bacteriol</source><year>2006</year><volume>188</volume><fpage>669</fpage><lpage>676</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/JB.188.2.669-676.2006</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16385056</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR81"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mack</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Fischer</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Krokotsch</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The intercellular adhesin involved in biofilm accumulation of <italic>Staphylococcus epidermidis</italic> is a linear beta-1,6-linked glucosaminoglycan: purification and structural analysis</article-title><source>J Bacteriol</source><year>1996</year><volume>178</volume><fpage>175</fpage><lpage>183</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/JB.178.1.175-183.1996</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8550413</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR82"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mah</surname><given-names>T-FC</given-names></name><name><surname>O&#x02019;Toole</surname><given-names>GA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Mechanisms of biofilm resistance to antimicrobial agents</article-title><source>Trends Microbiol</source><year>2001</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>34</fpage><lpage>39</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0966-842X(00)01913-2</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11166241</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR83"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mahmoudi</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Arabestani</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name><name><surname>Mousavi</surname><given-names>SF</given-names></name><name><surname>Alikhani</surname><given-names>MY</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Molecular analysis of the coagulase gene in clinical and nasal carrier isolates of methicillin-resistant <italic>Staphylococcus aureus</italic> by restriction fragment length polymorphism</article-title><source>J Glob Antimicrob Resist</source><year>2017</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>41</fpage><lpage>45</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jgar.2016.10.007</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27987442</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR84"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Makgotlho</surname><given-names>PE</given-names></name><name><surname>Kock</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name><name><surname>Hoosen</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Molecular identification and genotyping of MRSA isolates</article-title><source>FEMS Immunol Med Microbiol</source><year>2009</year><volume>57</volume><fpage>104</fpage><lpage>115</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1574-695X.2009.00585.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19712080</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR85"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Maljkovic Berry</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Melendrez</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name><name><surname>Bishop-Lilly</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Next generation sequencing and bioinformatics methodologies for infectious disease research and public health: approaches, applications, and considerations for development of laboratory capacity</article-title><source>J Infect Dis</source><year>2019</year><volume>221</volume><fpage>S292</fpage><lpage>S307</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/infdis/jiz286</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR86"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Martineau</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Picard</surname><given-names>FJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Roy</surname><given-names>PH</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Species-specific and ubiquitous DNA-based assays for rapid identification of <italic>Staphylococcus epidermidis</italic></article-title><source>J Clin Microbiol</source><year>1996</year><volume>34</volume><fpage>2888</fpage><lpage>2893</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/JCM.34.12.2888-2893.1996</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8940417</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR87"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>McAleese</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>SW</given-names></name><name><surname>Sieradzki</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Overexpression of genes of the cell wall stimulon in clinical isolates of <italic>Staphylococcus aureus</italic> exhibiting vancomycin-intermediate-S.aureus-type resistance to vancomycin</article-title><source>J Bacteriol</source><year>2006</year><volume>188</volume><fpage>1120</fpage><lpage>1133</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/JB.188.3.1120-1133.2006</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16428416</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR88"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>McCarthy</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Lindsay</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The distribution of plasmids that carry virulence and resistance genes in <italic>Staphylococcus aureus</italic> is lineage associated</article-title><source>BMC Microbiol</source><year>2012</year><volume>12</volume><fpage>104</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1471-2180-12-104</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22691167</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR89"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>McClure</surname><given-names>J-AM</given-names></name><name><surname>Lakhundi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Kashif</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Genomic comparison of highly virulent, moderately virulent, and avirulent strains from a genetically closely-related MRSA ST239 sub-lineage provides insights into pathogenesis</article-title><source>Front Microbiol</source><year>2018</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>1531</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fmicb.2018.01531</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30042755</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR90"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>McGuinness</surname><given-names>WA</given-names></name><name><surname>Malachowa</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>DeLeo</surname><given-names>FR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Vancomycin resistance in <italic>Staphylococcus aureus</italic></article-title><source>Yale J Biol Med</source><year>2017</year><volume>90</volume><fpage>269</fpage><lpage>281</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28656013</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR91"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Meier-Kolthoff</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name><name><surname>Auch</surname><given-names>AF</given-names></name><name><surname>Klenk</surname><given-names>H-P</given-names></name><name><surname>G&#x000f6;ker</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Genome sequence-based species delimitation with confidence intervals and improved distance functions</article-title><source>BMC Bioinformatics</source><year>2013</year><volume>14</volume><fpage>60</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1471-2105-14-60</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23432962</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR92"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mistry</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Sharma</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Mahato</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Prevalence and characterization of oxacillin susceptible mecA-positive clinical isolates of <italic>Staphylococcus aureus</italic> causing bovine mastitis in India</article-title><source>PLoS ONE</source><year>2016</year><volume>11</volume><fpage>e0162256</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0162256</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27603123</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR93"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Monecke</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Coombs</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Shore</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>A field guide to pandemic, epidemic and sporadic clones of methicillin-resistant <italic>Staphylococcus aureus</italic></article-title><source>PLoS ONE</source><year>2011</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>e17936</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0017936</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21494333</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR94"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>M&#x000f8;retr&#x000f8;</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Hermansen</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Holck</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Biofilm formation and the presence of the intercellular adhesion locus ica among staphylococci from food and food processing environments</article-title><source>Appl Environ Microbiol</source><year>2003</year><volume>69</volume><fpage>5648</fpage><lpage>5655</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/AEM.69.9.5648-5655.2003</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12957956</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR95"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Moroney</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name><name><surname>Heller</surname><given-names>LC</given-names></name><name><surname>Arbuckle</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Staphylococcal cassette chromosome mec and panton-valentine leukocidin characterization of methicillin-resistant <italic>Staphylococcus aureus</italic> clones</article-title><source>J Clin Microbiol</source><year>2007</year><volume>45</volume><fpage>1019</fpage><lpage>1021</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/JCM.01706-06</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17192420</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR96"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mottola</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Semedo-Lemsaddek</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Mendes</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Molecular typing, virulence traits and antimicrobial resistance of diabetic foot staphylococci</article-title><source>J Biomed Sci</source><year>2016</year><volume>23</volume><fpage>33</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12929-016-0250-7</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26952716</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR97"><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nurk</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Bankevich</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Antipov</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Assembling genomes and mini-metagenomes from highly chimeric reads</article-title><source>Lecture Notes in Computer Science (including subseries Lecture Notes in Artificial Intelligence and Lecture Notes in Bioinformatics)</source><year>2013</year><publisher-loc>Berlin, Heidelberg</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Springer</publisher-name><fpage>158</fpage><lpage>170</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR98"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>O&#x02019;Hara</surname><given-names>FP</given-names></name><name><surname>Suaya</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Ray</surname><given-names>GT</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Spa typing and multilocus sequence typing show comparable performance in a macro epidemiologic study of <italic>Staphylococcus aureus</italic> in the United States</article-title><source>Microb Drug Resist</source><year>2016</year><volume>22</volume><fpage>88</fpage><lpage>96</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1089/mdr.2014.0238</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26669861</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR99"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Omar</surname><given-names>NY</given-names></name><name><surname>Ali</surname><given-names>HAS</given-names></name><name><surname>Harfoush</surname><given-names>RAH</given-names></name><name><surname>El Khayat</surname><given-names>EH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Molecular typing of methicillin resistant <italic>Staphylococcus aureus</italic> clinical isolates on the basis of protein A and coagulase gene polymorphisms</article-title><source>Int J Microbiol</source><year>2014</year><volume>2014</volume><fpage>650328</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1155/2014/650328</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24955091</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR100"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Otto</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Staphylococcal biofilms</article-title><source>Curr Top Microbiol Immunol</source><year>2008</year><volume>322</volume><fpage>207</fpage><lpage>228</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/978-3-540-75418-3_10</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18453278</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR101"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Overbeek</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Olson</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Pusch</surname><given-names>GD</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The SEED and the rapid annotation of microbial genomes using subsystems technology (RAST)</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res</source><year>2014</year><volume>42</volume><fpage>D206</fpage><lpage>D214</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/gkt1226</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24293654</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR102"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Peacock</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Day</surname><given-names>NP</given-names></name><name><surname>Thomas</surname><given-names>MG</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Clinical isolates of <italic>Staphylococcus aureus</italic> exhibit diversity in fnb genes and adhesion to human fibronectin</article-title><source>J Infect</source><year>2000</year><volume>41</volume><fpage>23</fpage><lpage>31</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1053/jinf.2000.0657</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10942636</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR103"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Peacock</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Foster</surname><given-names>TJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Cameron</surname><given-names>BJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Berendt</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Bacterial fibronectin-binding proteins and endothelial cell surface fibronectin mediate adherence of <italic>Staphylococcus aureus</italic> to resting human endothelial cells</article-title><source>Microbiology</source><year>1999</year><volume>145</volume><fpage>3477</fpage><lpage>3486</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1099/00221287-145-12-3477</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10627045</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR104"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>P&#x000e9;richon</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Courvalin</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>VanA-type vancomycin-resistant <italic>Staphylococcus aureus</italic></article-title><source>Antimicrob Agents Chemother</source><year>2009</year><volume>53</volume><fpage>4580</fpage><lpage>4587</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/AAC.00346-09</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19506057</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR105"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rahimi</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Katouli</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Karimi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Biofilm production among methicillin resistant <italic>Staphylococcus aureus</italic> strains isolated from catheterized patients with urinary tract infection</article-title><source>Microb Pathog</source><year>2016</year><volume>98</volume><fpage>69</fpage><lpage>76</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.micpath.2016.06.031</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27374894</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR106"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Raven</surname><given-names>KE</given-names></name><name><surname>Blane</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Kumar</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Defining metrics for whole-genome sequence analysis of MRSA in clinical practice</article-title><source>Microb Genomics</source><year>2020</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>e000354</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1099/mgen.0.000354</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR107"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rezai</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Valadan</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Ahangarkani</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Rezai</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The spa typing and characterization of nasal carriage methicillin-resistant <italic>Staphylococcus aureus</italic> isolates from healthy children</article-title><source>J Pediatr Rev</source><year>2019</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>59</fpage><lpage>64</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.32598/jpr.8.1.59</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR108"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Robinson</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name><name><surname>Enright</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Multilocus sequence typing and the evolution of methicillin-resistant <italic>Staphylococcus aureus</italic></article-title><source>Clin Microbiol Infect</source><year>2004</year><volume>10</volume><fpage>92</fpage><lpage>97</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1469-0691.2004.00768.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14759234</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR109"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rohde</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Burandt</surname><given-names>EC</given-names></name><name><surname>Siemssen</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Polysaccharide intercellular adhesin or protein factors in biofilm accumulation of <italic>Staphylococcus epidermidis</italic> and <italic>Staphylococcus aureus</italic> isolated from prosthetic hip and knee joint infections</article-title><source>Biomaterials</source><year>2007</year><volume>28</volume><fpage>1711</fpage><lpage>1720</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.biomaterials.2006.11.046</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17187854</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR110"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rossney</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name><name><surname>Shore</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name><name><surname>Morgan</surname><given-names>PM</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The emergence and importation of diverse genotypes of methicillin-resistant <italic>Staphylococcus aureus</italic> (MRSA) harboring the panton-valentine leukocidin gene (pvl) reveal that pvl Is a poor marker for community-acquired MRSA strains in Ireland</article-title><source>J Clin Microbiol</source><year>2007</year><volume>45</volume><fpage>2554</fpage><lpage>2563</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/JCM.00245-07</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17581935</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR111"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schwarzkopf</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Karch</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Genetic variation in <italic>Staphylococcus aureus</italic> coagulase genes: potential and limits for use as epidemiological marker</article-title><source>J Clin Microbiol</source><year>1994</year><volume>32</volume><fpage>2407</fpage><lpage>2412</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/JCM.32.10.2407-2412.1994</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7814475</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR112"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shakeri</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Shojai</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Golalipour</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Spa diversity among MRSA and MSSA strains of <italic>Staphylococcus aureus</italic> in North of Iran</article-title><source>Int J Microbiol</source><year>2010</year><volume>2010</volume><fpage>351397</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1155/2010/351397</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20862383</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR113"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shekarabi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Hajikhani</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Salimi Chirani</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Molecular characterization of vancomycin-resistant <italic>Staphylococcus aureus</italic> strains isolated from clinical samples: a three year study in Tehran, Iran</article-title><source>PLoS ONE</source><year>2017</year><volume>12</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>10</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0183607</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR114"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shittu</surname><given-names>AO</given-names></name><name><surname>Okon</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Adesida</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Antibiotic resistance and molecular epidemiology of <italic>Staphylococcus aureus</italic> in Nigeria</article-title><source>BMC Microbiol</source><year>2011</year><volume>11</volume><fpage>92</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1471-2180-11-92</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21545717</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR115"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shopsin</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Gomez</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Waddington</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Use of Coagulase Gene Repeat Region Nucleotide Sequences for Typing of Methicillin-Resistant <italic>Staphylococcus aureus</italic>; Strains</article-title><source>J Clin Microbiol</source><year>2000</year><volume>38</volume><fpage>3453</fpage><lpage>3456</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/JCM.38.9.3453-3456.2000</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10970402</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR116"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shukla</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></name><name><surname>Pantrang</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Stahl</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Comparative whole-genome mapping to determine <italic>Staphylococcus aureus</italic> genome size, virulence motifs, and clonality</article-title><source>J Clin Microbiol</source><year>2012</year><volume>50</volume><fpage>3526</fpage><lpage>3533</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/JCM.01168-12</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22915603</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR117"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Goering</surname><given-names>RV</given-names></name><name><surname>Simjee</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Application of molecular techniques to the study of hospital infection</article-title><source>Clin Microbiol Rev</source><year>2006</year><volume>19</volume><fpage>512</fpage><lpage>530</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/CMR.00025-05</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16847083</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR118"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Skov</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Smyth</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Larsen</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Phenotypic detection of methicillin resistance in <italic>Staphylococcus aureus</italic> by disk diffusion testing and Etest on Mueller-Hinton agar</article-title><source>J Clin Microbiol</source><year>2006</year><volume>44</volume><fpage>4395</fpage><lpage>4399</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/JCM.01411-06</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17050809</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR119"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Stefanaki</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Ieronymaki</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Matoula</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Six-year retrospective review of hospital data on antimicrobial resistance profile of <italic>Staphylococcus aureus</italic> isolated from skin infections from a single institution in Greece</article-title><source>Antibiotics</source><year>2017</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>39</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/antibiotics6040039</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR120"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Stefani</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Varaldo</surname><given-names>PE</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Epidemiology of methicillin-resistant staphylococci in Europe</article-title><source>Clin Microbiol Infect</source><year>2003</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>1179</fpage><lpage>1186</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1469-0691.2003.00698.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14686982</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR121"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Strand&#x000e9;n</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Frei</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Widmer</surname><given-names>AF</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Molecular typing of methicillin-resistant <italic>Staphylococcus aureus</italic>: can PCR replace pulsed-field gel electrophoresis?</article-title><source>J Clin Microbiol</source><year>2003</year><volume>41</volume><fpage>3181</fpage><lpage>3186</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/jcm.41.7.3181-3186.2003</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12843061</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR122"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Strommenger</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Braulke</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Heuck</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>spa Typing of <italic>Staphylococcus aureus</italic> as a frontline tool in epidemiological typing</article-title><source>J Clin Microbiol</source><year>2008</year><volume>46</volume><fpage>574</fpage><lpage>581</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/JCM.01599-07</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18032612</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR123"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Strommenger</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Kettlitz</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Werner</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Witte</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Multiplex PCR assay for simultaneous detection of nine clinically relevant antibiotic resistance genes in <italic>Staphylococcus aureus</italic></article-title><source>J Clin Microbiol</source><year>2003</year><volume>41</volume><fpage>4089</fpage><lpage>4094</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/JCM.41.9.4089-4094.2003</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12958230</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR124"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Szab&#x000f3;</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Dombr&#x000e1;di</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Dobay</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Phenotypic and genetic characterisation of methicillin-resistant <italic>Staphylococcus aureus</italic> strains isolated from the university hospitals of Debrecen</article-title><source>Eur J Clin Microbiol Infect Dis</source><year>2009</year><volume>28</volume><fpage>129</fpage><lpage>136</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10096-008-0588-1</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18830728</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR125"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tatusova</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>DiCuccio</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Badretdin</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>NCBI prokaryotic genome annotation pipeline</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res</source><year>2016</year><volume>44</volume><fpage>6614</fpage><lpage>6624</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/gkw569</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27342282</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR126"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tenover</surname><given-names>FC</given-names></name><name><surname>Tickler</surname><given-names>IA</given-names></name><name><surname>Le</surname><given-names>VM</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Updating molecular diagnostics for detecting methicillin-susceptible and methicillin-resistant <italic>Staphylococcus aureus</italic> isolates in blood culture bottles</article-title><source>J Clin Microbiol</source><year>2019</year><volume>57</volume><fpage>e01195</fpage><lpage>e1219</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/JCM.01195-19</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31484703</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR127"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Vestby</surname><given-names>LK</given-names></name><name><surname>Gr&#x000f8;nseth</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Simm</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Nesse</surname><given-names>LL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Bacterial biofilm and its role in the pathogenesis of disease</article-title><source>Antibiotics</source><year>2020</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>59</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/antibiotics9020059</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR128"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Vuong</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Kocianova</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Voyich</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>A crucial role for exopolysaccharide modification in bacterial biofilm formation, immune evasion, and virulence</article-title><source>J Biol Chem</source><year>2004</year><volume>279</volume><fpage>54881</fpage><lpage>54886</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1074/jbc.M411374200</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15501828</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR129"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Walter</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Noll</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Feig</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Decline in the proportion of methicillin resistance among <italic>Staphylococcus aureus</italic> isolates from non-invasive samples and in outpatient settings, and changes in the co-resistance profiles: an analysis of data collected within the Antimicrobial Resistance Surveillance Network, Germany 2010 to 2015</article-title><source>BMC Infect Dis</source><year>2017</year><volume>17</volume><fpage>169</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12879-017-2271-6</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28231850</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR130"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wattam</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name><name><surname>Davis</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Assaf</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Improvements to PATRIC, the all-bacterial bioinformatics database and analysis resource center</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res</source><year>2017</year><volume>45</volume><fpage>D535</fpage><lpage>D542</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/gkw1017</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27899627</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR131"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Dong</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Fang</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>OrthoVenn2: a web server for whole-genome comparison and annotation of orthologous clusters across multiple species</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res</source><year>2019</year><volume>47</volume><fpage>W52</fpage><lpage>W58</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/gkz333</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31053848</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR132"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yamamoto</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Hung</surname><given-names>W-C</given-names></name><name><surname>Takano</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Nishiyama</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Genetic nature and virulence of community-associated methicillin-resistant <italic>Staphylococcus aureus</italic></article-title><source>BioMedicine</source><year>2013</year><volume>3</volume><fpage>2</fpage><lpage>18</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.biomed.2012.12.001</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR133"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yoon</surname><given-names>S-H</given-names></name><name><surname>Ha</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Lim</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>A large-scale evaluation of algorithms to calculate average nucleotide identity</article-title><source>Antonie Van Leeuwenhoek</source><year>2017</year><volume>110</volume><fpage>1281</fpage><lpage>1286</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10482-017-0844-4</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28204908</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR134"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>McClure</surname><given-names>J-A</given-names></name><name><surname>Conly</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Enhanced multiplex PCR assay for typing of staphylococcal cassette chromosome mec types I to V in methicillin-resistant <italic>Staphylococcus aureus</italic></article-title><source>Mol Cell Probes</source><year>2012</year><volume>26</volume><fpage>218</fpage><lpage>221</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.mcp.2012.04.002</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22659351</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR135"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>McClure</surname><given-names>J-A</given-names></name><name><surname>Elsayed</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Novel multiplex PCR assay for characterization and concomitant subtyping of staphylococcal cassette chromosome mec Types I to V in methicillin-resistant <italic>Staphylococcus aureus</italic></article-title><source>J Clin Microbiol</source><year>2005</year><volume>43</volume><fpage>5026</fpage><lpage>5033</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/JCM.43.10.5026-5033.2005</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16207957</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR136"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zmantar</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Chaieb</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Makni</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Detection by PCR of adhesins genes and slime production in clinical <italic>Staphylococcus aureus</italic></article-title><source>J Basic Microbiol</source><year>2008</year><volume>48</volume><fpage>308</fpage><lpage>314</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/jobm.200700289</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18720490</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>