<!DOCTYPE article
PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.2 20190208//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-mathml3.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">3 Biotech</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">3 Biotech</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>3 Biotech</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">2190-572X</issn><issn pub-type="epub">2190-5738</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Springer International Publishing</publisher-name><publisher-loc>Cham</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">32547899</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">7280406</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">2285</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s13205-020-02285-3</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Original Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Ameliorated reserpine production via in vitro direct and indirect regeneration system in <italic>Rauvolfia serpentina</italic> (L.) Benth. ex Kurz.</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes"><name><surname>Mukherjee</surname><given-names>Eashan</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Sarkar</surname><given-names>Sutanu</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Bhattacharyya</surname><given-names>Somnath</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes" equal-contrib="yes"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0001-5059-2428</contrib-id><name><surname>Gantait</surname><given-names>Saikat</given-names></name><address><email>saikatgantait@yahoo.com</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/></contrib><aff id="Aff1"><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.444578.e</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0000 9427 2533</institution-id><institution>Crop Research Unit (Genetics and Plant Breeding), </institution><institution>Bidhan Chandra Krishi Viswavidyalaya, </institution></institution-wrap>Mohanpur, Nadia, West Bengal 741252 India </aff></contrib-group><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>8</day><month>6</month><year>2020</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>8</day><month>6</month><year>2020</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><month>7</month><year>2020</year></pub-date><volume>10</volume><issue>7</issue><elocation-id>294</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>16</day><month>4</month><year>2020</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>1</day><month>6</month><year>2020</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; The Author(s) 2020</copyright-statement><license license-type="OpenAccess"><license-p><bold>Open Access</bold>This article is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License, which permits use, sharing, adaptation, distribution and reproduction in any medium or format, as long as you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons licence, and indicate if changes were made. The images or other third party material in this article are included in the article's Creative Commons licence, unless indicated otherwise in a credit line to the material. If material is not included in the article's Creative Commons licence and your intended use is not permitted by statutory regulation or exceeds the permitted use, you will need to obtain permission directly from the copyright holder. To view a copy of this licence, visit <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract id="Abs1"><p id="Par1"><italic>Rauvolfia serpentina</italic> (L.) Benth. ex Kurz., popularly known as Indian Snakeroot plant, belonging to Apocynaceae&#x000a0;family, holds immense medicinal importance, owing to its rich source of multiple secondary metabolites such as ajmaline, ajmalicine, reserpine, and serpentine. To meet the constant demands for&#x000a0;the key secondary metabolite (reserpine) by majority of&#x000a0;the pharmaceutical industries, the present study assessed the effects of direct and indirect regeneration system on amelioration of&#x000a0;reserpine accumulation in shoots of <italic>R. serpentina</italic>. In vitro multiple shoot cultures were established using shoot tip explants. Best results for shoot initiation, multiplication, and biomass production were obtained in case of Murashige and Skoog medium, supplemented with 1&#x000a0;mg/l <italic>N</italic><sup>6</sup>-benzyladenine. The multiple shoots were then sub-cultured on cytokinin&#x02013;auxin combination media for further proliferation. Highest shoot and leaf multiplication rates and the most enhanced biomass were obtained in case of 1&#x02013;1.5&#x000a0;mg/l Kinetin&#x02009;+&#x02009;0.2&#x000a0;mg/l &#x003b1;-naphthalene acetic acid (NAA). Callus induction and its subsequent proliferation was obtained using 1.5&#x000a0;mg/l 2,4-dichlorophenoxyacetic acid. The best indirect shoot regeneration with highest shoot and leaf proliferation from calli was observed in case of 1&#x000a0;mg/l thidiazuron&#x02009;+&#x02009;0.2&#x000a0;mg/l NAA. Reserpine content estimation via HPTLC from in vitro shoots (direct regeneration) and calli (indirect regeneration)&#x000a0;were recorded to undergo an&#x000a0;almost three-fold and two-fold increment (respectively) in comparison to that of the mother plant. Thus, in vitro direct regeneration system&#x000a0;proved to be more effective and efficient in ameliorating the reserpine content.</p></abstract><kwd-group xml:lang="en"><title>Keywords</title><kwd>Biomass</kwd><kwd>Callus</kwd><kwd>HPTLC</kwd><kwd>Multiple shoots</kwd><kwd>Plant growth regulator</kwd><kwd>Secondary metabolite</kwd></kwd-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name><meta-value>&#x000a9; King Abdulaziz City for Science and Technology 2020</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="Sec1"><title>Introduction</title><p id="Par2"><italic>Rauvolfia</italic> genus comprises of different species of plants which have diverse medicinal and allied uses. The genus belongs to the family Apocynaceae and order Gentianales, under the kingdom Plantae. These plants are erect, evergreen, perennial shrubs growing up to a height of 60&#x02013;90&#x000a0;cm (Mukherjee et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">2019</xref>). Amongst different species, <italic>Rauvolfia serpentina</italic> (L.) Benth. ex Kurz. finds itself to be quite indispensable owing to the presence of assorted secondary metabolites, which have varied medicinal and therapeutic uses. Centre of origin of the plant is South-East Asia. The plant is extensively distributed in the tropical zones of America, Africa, India, Sri Lanka, Myanmar, and Nepal. In India, the distribution covers parts of tropical Himalaya, Gangetic plains, sub-Himalayan territories covering Shimla to Assam, and Sikkim to Nepal and Bhutan. Almost all parts of the plant such as leaves, shoots, flowers, and especially the roots contain several secondary metabolites like ajmaline, ajmalicine, rescinamine, reserpine, serpentine, etc. These compounds are mainly indole alkaloids that are&#x000a0;biosynthesised from the aromatic acid tryptophan. Since ancient times, this plant has been utilized in Ayurveda and Unani as remedies for fever, hypertension, insomnia, epilepsy, psychosis, schizophrenia, and other central nervous system disorders (reviewed by Mukherjee et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">2019</xref>). Root extracts have been used as a cure for snakebites and ulcers (Lobay <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">2015</xref>; Bunkar <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">2017</xref>). As per the reports of Soni et al. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">2016</xref>), root bark find its usage as a hypnotic and sedative which aids in lowering down blood pressure.</p><p id="Par3">By and large, this plant is propagated via seeds; stem cuttings and root cuttings have been reported in some cases&#x000a0;as well (Ghate et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">2019</xref>). However, these traditional ways of propagation are subject to several limitations, viz., low seed set, poor&#x000a0;rooting (Khan et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">2018</xref>), and high occurrences of genetic variation in seed propagated populations (Pillai et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">2012</xref>). Lucrative pharmacological and ethnobotanical uses (due the presence of the above-mentioned secondary metabolites) have led to the exploitation of <italic>R. serpentina</italic> natural resources, thereby pushing the species to a&#x000a0;threatened category as per IUCN. Keeping in view these constraints that are involved with the propagation and conservation of this plant species; in vitro tissue culture technologies offer a practical and constructive solution to the preservation and maintenance of this plant. It is hypothesized that in vitro propagation technology of <italic>R. serpentina</italic>, following direct and indirect (callus-mediated) regeneration for enhancement of biomass and secondary metabolites production, would be a significant contribution to the pharmacological industry at large, since both biomass-cum-secondary metabolite production would be facilitated simultaneously.</p><p id="Par4">Arrays of reports are available on all these aspects of reserpine production via different in vitro biotechnological interventions, discretely (reviewed by Mukherjee et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">2019</xref>). For instance, there are quite a few reports on the production of reserpine from in vitro plant cell, tissue, and organ cultures using transformed hairy roots (Pandey et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">2014</xref>), elicitor-mediated shoot apex and nodal segments (Panwar and Guru <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">2015</xref>), and germinated synthetic seeds (Gantait and Kundu <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">2017</xref>), etc. However, till date, to the best of our knowledge, the inclusive reports are very limited, since none of them covers all of these aspects on <italic>R. serpentina</italic> in one singular comprehensive report. Based on this backdrop, the present study deals with the optimization of in vitro direct multiple shoot and indirect (callus-mediated) multiple shoot regeneration system in <italic>R. serpentina</italic> for high biomass production and eventually to ameliorate the reserpine level among in vitro regenerants.</p></sec><sec id="Sec2"><title>Materials and methods</title><sec id="Sec3"><title>Explant collection and surface disinfection</title><p id="Par5">Shoot apices (1&#x02013;1.2&#x000a0;cm) were collected from the Medicinal Plant Garden, Bidhan Chandra Krishi Viswavidyalaya, Mohanpur, India. Surface disinfection of the shoot apex explants was done following a series of treatments using autoclaved (at 1.1&#x000a0;kg/cm<sup>2</sup> pressure and 121&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C for 15&#x000a0;min) solutions of 0.03% (w/v) bavistin, 10% (v/v) Tween-20, 20% (v/v) sodium hypochlorite (NaOCl), 1% (w/v) cetrimide, ethyl alcohol (C<sub>2</sub>H<sub>5</sub>OH), and 0.1% (w/v) mercuric chloride (HgCl<sub>2</sub>) (all these&#x000a0;were obtained from Merck Life Sciences. Pvt. Ltd., India), carried out in the Laminar Air Flow cabinet (LAF). All of the sterilants were used for 5&#x000a0;min with the&#x000a0;exception of ethyl alcohol, which was used for 30&#x000a0;s. After disinfection, the explants were taken out and the exposed basal portions of the shoot apices were trimmed and removed.</p></sec><sec id="Sec4"><title>Preparation of media and culture conditions</title><p id="Par6">The basal medium used for the experiments was the Murashige and Skoog (MS) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">1962</xref>) semisolid medium and the same was prepared by adding ready MS salt (Himedia laboratories Pvt. Ltd, India) 4.4&#x000a0;g/l supplemented with 30&#x000a0;g/l sucrose (Merck life Sciences Pvt. Ltd., India), 100&#x000a0;mg/l&#x000a0;m-inositol, and 7&#x000a0;g/l agar (both obtained from Sisco Research Laboratories Pvt. Ltd., India). For the different experiments on direct (shoot initiation and multiplication) and indirect (callus-mediated multiple shoot) regeneration, the media were supplemented with a choice and concentrations of plant growth regulators (PGRs). The pH of the media was adjusted to 5.7 by addition of 0.1&#x000a0;N HCl or 0.1&#x000a0;N NaOH following supplementation of PGRs but before addition of agar. The media were prepared in 55&#x000a0;ml culture tubes (Borosil, India) containing 20&#x000a0;ml media and were then sterilized using autoclave. For callus induction experiment, 55&#x000a0;ml culture tubes (each containing 10&#x000a0;ml of basal medium) were used, which were then tilted (before solidification, after autoclaving) at an angle of less than 45&#x000b0; (to increase the surface area for the explants inoculation). All the cultures were maintained at 25&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C temperature under cool white fluorescent lights (Phillips Champion, PHILLIPS, India), 50&#x000a0;&#x000b5;mol/m<sup>2</sup>/s photosynthetic photon flux density, under 16&#x000a0;h photoperiod, and at 60% RH; for callus induction experiment, the culture tubes were initially&#x000a0;kept under dark for 72&#x000a0;h and then transferred to 16&#x000a0;h photoperiod.</p></sec><sec id="Sec5"><title>Establishment of direct in vitro multiple shoot culture</title><p id="Par7">For the establishment of the in vitro shoot culture, shoot apices were inoculated in MS medium supplemented with the&#x000a0;following PGRs (at the rate of 0.5, 1, 1.5, 2, and 2.5&#x000a0;mg/l)&#x02014;<italic>N</italic><sup>6</sup>-benzyladenine (BA), Kinetin (KIN), thidiazuron (TDZ), zeatin (all obtained from Sisco Research Laboratories Pvt. Ltd., India), and meta-Topoline (mT) (Titan Biotech Ltd., India). Along with the above-mentioned PGRs, the shoot apices were also inoculated in PGR-free MS medium (served as the control). Data on response of explants to shoot induction (%) and days to fresh shoot induction were taken on a&#x000a0;daily basis, whereas number of shoots, shoot length (mm), and number of leaves, along with fresh weight (mg) and dry weight (mg), were recorded at 42&#x000a0;days of culture. Dry weight was taken after drying the shoot clumps under hot-air oven for 24&#x000a0;h at 50&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C.</p></sec><sec id="Sec6"><title>Proliferation of in vitro multiple shoot culture</title><p id="Par8">After final data collection, individual shoots (1&#x02013;1.2&#x000a0;cm size) having one inter-nodal region were isolated and transferred in shoot proliferation media wherein PGRs were used in combinations [BA, KIN, and TDZ, each of them supplemented with &#x003b1;-naphthalene acetic acid (NAA) (Sisco Research Laboratories Pvt. Ltd., India)]. The concentrations of the PGRs were: 0.5, 1, 1.5&#x000a0;mg/l each of them (cytokinin) supplemented with 0.2&#x000a0;mg/l NAA. Along with the above-mentioned PGRs, the shoots were also inoculated in PGR-free MS medium (served as the control). Data on response of shoots towards proliferation (%), days to initiation of multiple shoot proliferation were taken on&#x000a0;a daily basis, whereas number of shoots, shoot length (mm), and number of leaves, along with fresh weight (mg) and dry weight (mg), were recorded at 42&#x000a0;days of culture. Dry weight was taken after drying the shoot clumps under hot-air oven for 24&#x000a0;h at 50&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C.</p></sec><sec id="Sec7"><title>Establishment of in vitro callus culture</title><p id="Par9">For the in vitro callus induction experiment, the preferred explant was leaf, which was obtained from the previously optimized multiple shoot culture experiment. Three PGRs (at concentrations of 0.5, 1, 1.5, and 2&#x000a0;mg/l), viz., 2,4-dichlorophenoxy acetic acid (2,4-D) (Loba Chemie Pvt. Ltd., India), BA, and KIN were supplemented with MS basal medium. Before inoculation, the leaves were wounded horizontally against the leaf midrib with the help of scalpel, thereby increasing the chances of callus induction from the wounded sites. Along with the above-mentioned PGRs, the leaves were also inoculated in PGR-free MS medium (served as the control). Data on response of explants towards callus induction (%) and days to induction of the calli were recorded on a&#x000a0;daily basis, and finally, fresh weight (mg) and dry weight (mg) of the calli were taken after 56&#x000a0;days of culture. Dry weight was&#x000a0;taken after drying the calli under hot-air oven for 24&#x000a0;h at 50&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C.</p></sec><sec id="Sec8"><title>Establishment of in vitro indirect shoot regeneration from calli</title><p id="Par10">Organogenic calli obtained from the callus induction experiment involving the treatments of 1&#x02013;1.5&#x000a0;mg/l 2,4-D were used for indirect shoot regeneration purpose. Isolated calli (each weighing 300&#x000a0;mg) were inoculated in MS medium supplemented with BA, KIN and TDZ at the concentrations of 0.5, 1, and 1.5&#x000a0;mg/l, in combination with 0.2&#x000a0;mg/l NAA. Along with the above-mentioned PGRs, the calli were also inoculated in PGR-free MS medium (served as the control). Data on response of calli on regeneration (%), days to fresh shoot induction were taken on a&#x000a0;daily basis, whereas number of shoots, shoot length (mm), and number of leaves, along with fresh weight (mg) and dry weight (mg), were recorded at 56&#x000a0;days of culture.</p></sec><sec id="Sec9"><title>Estimation of reserpine</title><p id="Par11">For estimation of the key secondary metabolite reserpine from the in vitro regenerated multiple shoots and calli, the samples were oven-dried. For the purpose of&#x000a0;identification of&#x000a0;reserpine and its subsequent quantification, standard reserpine (Sigma-Aldrich<sup>&#x000ae;</sup>, Bangalore, India) was used as the reference material. 1&#x000a0;g of hot-air oven-dried powder was considered for the quantification of the secondary metabolite for each of the samples. The samples were extracted with high-performance liquid chromatography&#x000a0;(HPTLC)&#x02013;grade methanol (via vortexing) and were&#x000a0;then kept at room temperature (25&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C). The methanol extracted samples were then concentrated at a reduced pressure at 55&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;2&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C in rotary evaporator. Then extracts from the samples were mixed with methanol for liquefaction to arrive at a concentration of 0.1&#x000a0;g/ml. Finally, these were then subjected to HPLTC analysis. After analysis, the samples were smeared over pre-coated silica gel aluminium plate&#x000a0;60F<sub>254</sub>, in form of bands with the help of Camag microlitre syringe fixed on a Camag Linomat V (Switzerland) automated sample applicator with nitrogen flow. The plates were then dried and the chromatogram lane was developed with the mobile phase comprising of toluene: ethyl acetate: diethyleamine (7:2:1; v/v/v). With the&#x000a0;aid of Camag TLC scanner III (Switzerland), the plates were scanned at 200&#x02013;400&#x000a0;nm after their removal from the chamber and subsequent drying. Data regarding the peak area were noted and further assessments for the reserpine content were done with Camag Win CATS software.</p></sec><sec id="Sec10"><title>Data analysis</title><p id="Par12">For each of the experiments&#x000a0;(repeated thrice) involving multiple shoot initiation, proliferation, callus induction, and callus regeneration, three replications per treatment were considered. Each of the replications consisted of ten explants. The experiments were laid out following a Completely Randomized Design. Statistical analyses of the recorded data were done employing SPSS (version 17.0, SPSS Inc., Chicago, IL, USA) software. Subsequently, one-way analysis of variance (ANOVA) was formulated and statistical significance was calculated. Furthermore, statistical assessment of the data (mean&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;standard error), which differed significantly, was determined with Tukey&#x02019;s test (PC version Origin 7.0 Northampton, MA, USA) at <italic>P</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.05 using SPSS (Version 11, SPSS Inc. Chicago, USA) software.</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec11"><title>Results</title><sec id="Sec12"><title>Direct regeneration: multiple shoot initiation</title><p id="Par13">Five different cytokinins viz. BA, KIN, TDZ, zeatin, and mT were tested for their multiple shoot initiation capabilities. Maximum shoot induction was obtained in case of 1&#x000a0;mg/l BA that&#x000a0;exhibited the&#x000a0;earliest days to shoot initiation, maximum shoot multiplication, and maximum fresh and dry weights (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>). However, exceptionally, maximum response (~&#x02009;90%) and earliness to shooting were noticed even when&#x000a0;a higher dose of BA (2.5&#x000a0;mg/l)&#x000a0;was applied. As per the present study, it can be observed that the overall performances of the three PGRs viz. BA, KIN, and TDZ were much better than zeatin and mT, wherein the responses and the other growth attributes when studied showed less proliferation (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>). On one hand, where better multiplication rates and higher biomass production (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>) were observed with BA; on other hand, a better shoot elongation was observed in KIN-supplemented media formulations. Highest shoot elongation was seen in case of 1&#x000a0;mg/l KIN (~&#x02009;42&#x000a0;mm).<fig id="Fig1"><label>Fig.&#x000a0;1</label><caption><p>Influence of type and concentrations of plant growth regulators (cytokinins) on direct regeneration (multiple shoot initiation) in <italic>Rauvolfia serpentina</italic> (L.) Benth. ex Kurz. (Bar&#x02009;=&#x02009;5&#x000a0;mm)</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="13205_2020_2285_Fig1_HTML" id="MO1"/></fig><table-wrap id="Tab1"><label>Table&#x000a0;1</label><caption><p>Influence of plant growth regulators on multiple shoot initiation in <italic>Rauvolfia serpentina</italic> (L.) Benth. ex Kurz.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" colspan="5">Plant growth regulators (mg/l)</th><th align="left" colspan="7">Morphogenetic response</th></tr><tr><th align="left">BA</th><th align="left">KIN</th><th align="left">TDZ</th><th align="left">zeatin</th><th align="left">mT</th><th align="left">Frequency of response to multiple shoot initiation (%)</th><th align="left">Days to initiation of multiple shoot</th><th align="left">No. of shoots/explant</th><th align="left">Shoot length (mm)</th><th align="left">No. of leaves/explant</th><th align="left">FW (mg)</th><th align="left">DW (mg)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left">0.5</td><td align="left">&#x02013;</td><td align="left">&#x02013;</td><td align="left">&#x02013;</td><td align="left">&#x02013;</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">83.9&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;6.1ab</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">9.0&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.15c&#x02013;f</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">9.0&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;2.3cd</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">15.7&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.9d&#x02013;f</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">29.0&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;3.5a</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">290.0&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;19.7c&#x02013;f</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">27.0&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;9.2c&#x02013;e</td></tr><tr><td align="left">1</td><td align="left">&#x02013;</td><td align="left">&#x02013;</td><td align="left">&#x02013;</td><td align="left">&#x02013;</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">68.7&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;2.7b&#x02013;f</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">7.3&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;2.0f</td><td align="left">19.0&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.0a</td><td align="left">23.0&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.0b&#x02013;d</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">19.7&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.8cd</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">680.3&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;131.6a</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">55.0&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;11.5a</td></tr><tr><td align="left">1.5</td><td align="left">&#x02013;</td><td align="left">&#x02013;</td><td align="left">&#x02013;</td><td align="left">&#x02013;</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">72.3&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;8.8b&#x02013;e</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">10.7&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.3c&#x02013;e</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">7.7&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.5de</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">14.0&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.6f</td><td align="left">19.0&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.0cd</td><td align="left">370.0&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.0b&#x02013;e</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">30.0&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.6b&#x02013;e</td></tr><tr><td align="left">2</td><td align="left">&#x02013;</td><td align="left">&#x02013;</td><td align="left">&#x02013;</td><td align="left">&#x02013;</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">72.0&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;9.6b&#x02013;e</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">14.7&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.3b</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">6.3&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.3ef</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">25.3&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.3bc</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">22.3&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.3bc</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">300.0&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;40.4c&#x02013;f</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">30.0&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.6b&#x02013;e</td></tr><tr><td align="left">2.5</td><td align="left">&#x02013;</td><td align="left">&#x02013;</td><td align="left">&#x02013;</td><td align="left">&#x02013;</td><td align="left">90.0&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.0a</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">4.3&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;.3g</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">5.7&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.3e&#x02013;h</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">18.7&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;2.0c&#x02013;f</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">27.3&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;3.2ab</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">420.0&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;57.7bc</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">38.5&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.8bc</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x02013;</td><td align="left">0.5</td><td align="left">&#x02013;</td><td align="left">&#x02013;</td><td align="left">&#x02013;</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">68.8&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;2.7b&#x02013;f</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">11.7&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.5c</td><td align="left">6.0&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.0e&#x02013;g</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">37.0&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;3.5a</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">22.3&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.3bc</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">195.0&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;20.2f</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">22.7&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;2.6de</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x02013;</td><td align="left">1</td><td align="left">&#x02013;</td><td align="left">&#x02013;</td><td align="left">&#x02013;</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">77.7&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;6.1a&#x02013;c</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">10.3&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.3c&#x02013;f</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">6.0&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.6e&#x02013;g</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">42.3&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;4.3a</td><td align="left">19.0&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.0cd</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">230.0&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;11.5ef</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">26.0&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;3.5c&#x02013;e</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x02013;</td><td align="left">1.5</td><td align="left">&#x02013;</td><td align="left">&#x02013;</td><td align="left">&#x02013;</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">61.2&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;2.2d&#x02013;g</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">15.3&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.7b</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">6.3&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.8ef</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">41.7&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.8a</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">8.7&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.5h</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">290.0&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;51.9c&#x02013;f</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">27.0&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;3.7c&#x02013;e</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x02013;</td><td align="left">2</td><td align="left">&#x02013;</td><td align="left">&#x02013;</td><td align="left">&#x02013;</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">68.8&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;2.7b&#x02013;f</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">15.0&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.6b</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">10.7&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.3bc</td><td align="left">29.7&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;&#x000b1;0.3b</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">20.0&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.6cd</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">420.0&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;69.3bc</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">34.0&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;4.0b&#x02013;d</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x02013;</td><td align="left">2.5</td><td align="left">&#x02013;</td><td align="left">&#x02013;</td><td align="left">&#x02013;</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">77.7&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;6.1a&#x02013;c</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">14.7&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.7b</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">12.0&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.6b</td><td align="left">19.0&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.0c&#x02013;f</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">16.3&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.8c&#x02013;f</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">290.0&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;40.4c&#x02013;f</td><td align="left">20.0&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.0e</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x02013;</td><td align="left">&#x02013;</td><td align="left">0.5</td><td align="left">&#x02013;</td><td align="left">&#x02013;</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">77.7&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;6.1a&#x02013;c</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">8.0&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.0d&#x02013;f</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">7.0&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.5de</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">25.7&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.3bc</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">15.0&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.6d&#x02013;g</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">390.0&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;28.9b&#x02013;d</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">32.0&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.2b&#x02013;e</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x02013;</td><td align="left">&#x02013;</td><td align="left">1</td><td align="left">&#x02013;</td><td align="left">&#x02013;</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">77.7&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;6.1a&#x02013;c</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">10.3&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.2c&#x02013;f</td><td align="left">6.0&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.0e&#x02013;g</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">40.0&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;9.8a</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">18.3&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.3c&#x02013;e</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">455.0&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;66.4b</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">41.3&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;4.9b</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x02013;</td><td align="left">&#x02013;</td><td align="left">1.5</td><td align="left">&#x02013;</td><td align="left">&#x02013;</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">75.0&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;7.8a&#x02013;d</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">10.7&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.3c&#x02013;e</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">4.0&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.6f&#x02013;i</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">25.0&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.6bc</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">15.0&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;3.5d&#x02013;g</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">225.0&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;20.2ef</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">29.0&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;6.4b&#x02013;e</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x02013;</td><td align="left">&#x02013;</td><td align="left">2</td><td align="left">&#x02013;</td><td align="left">&#x02013;</td><td align="left">63.4&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.0c&#x02013;g</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">7.7&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.7ef</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">6.0&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.7e&#x02013;g</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">22.0&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.2b&#x02013;e</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">8.0&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.0h</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">365.0&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;77.9b&#x02013;e</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">30.0&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;6.4b&#x02013;e</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x02013;</td><td align="left">&#x02013;</td><td align="left">2.5</td><td align="left">&#x02013;</td><td align="left">&#x02013;</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">77.7&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;6.1a&#x02013;c</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">9.7&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.3c&#x02013;f</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">7.7&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.3de</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">24.0&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.2bc</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">22.3&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;5.5bc</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">260.0&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;5.8d&#x02013;f</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">25.3&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.5d&#x02013;e</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x02013;</td><td align="left">&#x02013;</td><td align="left">&#x02013;</td><td align="left">0.5</td><td align="left">&#x02013;</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">50.8&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.0g</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">8.3&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.3d&#x02013;f</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">2.3&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.7ij</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">11.3&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.3f</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">6.7&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.3h</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">16.7&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;3.3g</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">1.7&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.7f</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x02013;</td><td align="left">&#x02013;</td><td align="left">&#x02013;</td><td align="left">1</td><td align="left">&#x02013;</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">61.2&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;2.2d&#x02013;g</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">9.0&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.6c&#x02013;f</td><td align="left">3.0&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.0ij</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">13.0&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.6f</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">12.7&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;2.9e&#x02013;h</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">30.0&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;5.8g</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">3.3&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.2f</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x02013;</td><td align="left">&#x02013;</td><td align="left">&#x02013;</td><td align="left">1.5</td><td align="left">&#x02013;</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">57.0&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;3.6e&#x02013;g</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">10.0&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.1c&#x02013;f</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">3.7&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.3g&#x02013;i</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">13.7&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.5f</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">11.0&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.5f&#x02013;h</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">30.0&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;10.0g</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">3.0&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;2.0f</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x02013;</td><td align="left">&#x02013;</td><td align="left">&#x02013;</td><td align="left">2</td><td align="left">&#x02013;</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">55.0&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;4.2&#x000a0;fg</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">10.3&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.3c&#x02013;f</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">3.3&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.3h&#x02013;j</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">13.7&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.8f</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">9.7&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.3gh</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">10.0&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.0g</td><td align="left">1.0&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.0f</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x02013;</td><td align="left">&#x02013;</td><td align="left">&#x02013;</td><td align="left">2.5</td><td align="left">&#x02013;</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">55.0&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;4.2&#x000a0;fg</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">9.3&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.3c&#x02013;f</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">3.7&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.3g&#x02013;i</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">13.0&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.0f</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">8.7&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.8</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">13.3&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;3.3g</td><td align="left">1.0&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.0f</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x02013;</td><td align="left">&#x02013;</td><td align="left">&#x02013;</td><td align="left">&#x02013;</td><td align="left">0.5</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">61.2&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;2.2d&#x02013;g</td><td align="left">8.0&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.0d&#x02013;f</td><td align="left">3.0&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.0ij</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">12.3&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.8f</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">17.3&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;2.2c&#x02013;e</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">26.7&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;3.3g</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">1.7&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.3f</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x02013;</td><td align="left">&#x02013;</td><td align="left">&#x02013;</td><td align="left">&#x02013;</td><td align="left">1</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">59.0&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;2.2e&#x02013;g</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">10.0&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.2c&#x02013;f</td><td align="left">3.0&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.0ij</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">12.0&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.6f</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">14.7&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.8d&#x02013;g</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">23.3&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;6.7g</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">2.0&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.6f</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x02013;</td><td align="left">&#x02013;</td><td align="left">&#x02013;</td><td align="left">&#x02013;</td><td align="left">1.5</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">50.8&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.0g</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">10.3&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.3c&#x02013;f</td><td align="left">1.0&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.0j</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">15.3&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.2ef</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">6.7&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.3h</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">30.0&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;5.8g</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">2.7&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.8f</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x02013;</td><td align="left">&#x02013;</td><td align="left">&#x02013;</td><td align="left">&#x02013;</td><td align="left">2</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">57.0&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;3.6e&#x02013;g</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">10.7&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.7c&#x02013;e</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">1.7&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.3ij</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">13.7&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.7f</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">8.3&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.8h</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">18.3&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;6.0g</td><td align="left">1.0&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.0f</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x02013;</td><td align="left">&#x02013;</td><td align="left">&#x02013;</td><td align="left">&#x02013;</td><td align="left">2.5</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">54.8&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;2.0&#x000a0;fg</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">11.0&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.6cd</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">3.3&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.3h&#x02013;j</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">15.0&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.6ef</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">8.7&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.3h</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">26.7&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;3.3g</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">1.7&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.3f</td></tr><tr><td align="left">C</td><td align="left">&#x02013;</td><td align="left">&#x02013;</td><td align="left">&#x02013;</td><td align="left">&#x02013;</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">48.9&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.9g</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">18.7&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.3a</td><td align="left">3.0&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.0ij</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">11.3&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.8f</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">6.7&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.3h</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">9.0&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.0g</td><td align="left">1.0&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.0f</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>Data represent mean of three replicates with ten samples (shoot tip explants) per treatment. Growth period 42&#x000a0;days. (<italic>C</italic> Control)</p><p>Data for each column followed by the different letters are significantly different according to Tukey&#x02019;s test at <italic>P</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.05</p><p>Data expressed as percentage were transformed using arc sine prior to ANOVA and converted back to the original scale for demonstration in the table (Compton <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">1994</xref>)</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p></sec><sec id="Sec13"><title>Direct regeneration: multiple shoot proliferation</title><p id="Par14">In the current experiment on multiple shoot induction, the PGRs that gave better performances were chosen for further shoot and leaf proliferation studies. The PGRs, viz., BA, KIN, and TDZ, were used in combination with 0.2&#x000a0;mg/l NAA to study the proliferation rates. The effects of cytokinin&#x02009;+&#x02009;auxin combinations on direct multiple shoot proliferation were studied. Maximum shoot multiplication (~&#x02009;21 shoots) and highest fresh weight (~&#x02009;1990&#x000a0;mg) of the proliferated mass were obtained in case of 1&#x000a0;mg/l KIN&#x02009;+&#x02009;0.2&#x000a0;mg/l NAA (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>). Highest response percentage (~&#x02009;84%) and maximum amount of leaf proliferation was observed in case of 1.5&#x000a0;mg/l KIN&#x02009;+&#x02009;0.2&#x000a0;mg/l NAA (~&#x02009;47 nos.), thus depicting the effectiveness of KIN in inducing higher proliferation rates. Earliest response (~&#x02009;9&#x000a0;days), maximum shoot elongation (~&#x02009;26&#x000a0;mm), and increase in biomass with respect to dry weight (~&#x02009;160&#x000a0;mg) were obtained in 0.5&#x000a0;mg/l TDZ&#x02009;+&#x02009;0.2&#x000a0;mg/l NAA (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref>). Remarkably, 0.5 BA&#x02009;+&#x02009;0.2 NAA also exhibited the highest frequency of shoot proliferation (~&#x02009;84%). Across the different treatments, it was seen that an increase in PGR concentrations led to a&#x000a0;decrease in proliferation in case of TDZ&#x02009;+&#x02009;NAA, however,&#x000a0;for KIN&#x02009;+&#x02009;NAA combination an&#x000a0;opposite trend was noticed. In case of BA&#x02009;+&#x02009;NAA combinations, intermediate concentrations exhibited better results.<fig id="Fig2"><label>Fig.&#x000a0;2</label><caption><p>Influence of type, concentration, and combination of plant growth regulators (cytokinins:auxin) on direct regeneration (multiple shoot proliferation) in <italic>Rauvolfia serpentina</italic> (L.) Benth. ex Kurz. (Bar&#x02009;=&#x02009;5&#x000a0;mm)</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="13205_2020_2285_Fig2_HTML" id="MO2"/></fig><table-wrap id="Tab2"><label>Table&#x000a0;2</label><caption><p>Influence of plant growth regulators on multiple shoot proliferation in <italic>Rauvolfia serpentina</italic> (L.) Benth. ex Kurz.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" colspan="4">Plant growth regulators (mg/l)</th><th align="left" colspan="7">Morphogenetic response</th></tr><tr><th align="left">NAA</th><th align="left">BA</th><th align="left">KIN</th><th align="left">TDZ</th><th align="left">Frequency of response to shoot proliferation (%)</th><th align="left">Days to initiation of shoot proliferation</th><th align="left">No. of shoots/explant</th><th align="left">Shoot length (mm)</th><th align="left">No. of leaves/explant</th><th align="left">FW (mg)</th><th align="left">DW (mg)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left">0.2</td><td align="left">0.5</td><td align="left">&#x02013;</td><td align="left">&#x02013;</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">83.9&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;6.1a</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">12.7&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.8bc</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">15.7&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.4b</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">21.0&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.5ab</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">46.3&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.8a</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">1280.0&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;98.1c</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">90.0&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;5.8de</td></tr><tr><td align="left">0.2</td><td align="left">1</td><td align="left">&#x02013;</td><td align="left">&#x02013;</td><td align="left">71.6&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.0b</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">11.0&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.6b&#x02013;d</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">14.3&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.8bc</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">21.3&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;3.9ab</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">39.3&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.2b</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">1525.0&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;72.1bc</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">121.7&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;15.9bc</td></tr><tr><td align="left">0.2</td><td align="left">1.5</td><td align="left">&#x02013;</td><td align="left">&#x02013;</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">68.9&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;2.7bc</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">12.0&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.6b&#x02013;d</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">15.3&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;3.3b</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">21.0&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;2.0ab</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">39.0&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.5b</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">1415.0&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;37.5c</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">115.0&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;8.7cd</td></tr><tr><td align="left">0.2</td><td align="left">&#x02013;</td><td align="left">0.5</td><td align="left">&#x02013;</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">59.0&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;2.2cd</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">12.0&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.7b&#x02013;d</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">15.3&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.7b</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">20.7&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;2.9ab</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">28.7&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.7c</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">785.0&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;20.2d</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">65.0&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;2.9e</td></tr><tr><td align="left">0.2</td><td align="left">&#x02013;</td><td align="left">1</td><td align="left">&#x02013;</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">66.1&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;2.7bc</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">12.7&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.2bc</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">21.0&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.6a</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">19.3&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;3.8ab</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">34.0&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;3.0bc</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">1990.0&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;69.2a</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">145.0&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;14.4ab</td></tr><tr><td align="left">0.2</td><td align="left">&#x02013;</td><td align="left">1.5</td><td align="left">&#x02013;</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">83.9&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;6.1a</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">13.3&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.5b</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">16.7&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.8b</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">22.7&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;3.7ab</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">47.3&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;3.7a</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">1695.0&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;112.5b</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">145.0&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;2.9ab</td></tr><tr><td align="left">0.2</td><td align="left">&#x02013;</td><td align="left">&#x02013;</td><td align="left">0.5</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">68.9&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;2.7bc</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">9.3&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.9d</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">10.3&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.8cd</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">26.3&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;9.4a</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">37.7&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.2b</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">1955.0&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;31.7a</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">160.0&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;5.8a</td></tr><tr><td align="left">0.2</td><td align="left">&#x02013;</td><td align="left">&#x02013;</td><td align="left">1</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">68.9&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;2.7bc</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">10.0&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.6cd</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">7.0&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.0de</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">17.7&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;2.9ab</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">37.7&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.8b</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">1510.0&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;173.2bc</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">137.7&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;7.2a&#x02013;c</td></tr><tr><td align="left">0.2</td><td align="left">&#x02013;</td><td align="left"/><td align="left">1.5</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">66.1&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;2.7bc</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">12.3&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.3b&#x02013;d</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">14.7&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.3bc</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">15.7&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;2.0ab</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">34.3&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.8bc</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">645.0&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;43.3d</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">81.7&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;7.2e</td></tr><tr><td align="left">C</td><td align="left">&#x02013;</td><td align="left">&#x02013;</td><td align="left">&#x02013;</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">52.8&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;2.0d</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">19.7&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.3a</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">3.0&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.0e</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">10.3&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.3b</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">6.7&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.3d</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">13.3&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;3.3e</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">1.3&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.3f</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>Data represent mean of three replicates with ten samples (shoot tip explants) per treatment. Growth period 42&#x000a0;days (<italic>C</italic>&#x02009; control)</p><p>Data for each column followed by the different letters are significantly different according to Tukey&#x02019;s test at <italic>P</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.05</p><p>Data expressed as percentage were transformed using arc sine prior to ANOVA and converted back to the original scale for demonstration in the table (Compton <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">1994</xref>)</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p></sec><sec id="Sec14"><title>Indirect regeneration: callus induction and proliferation</title><p id="Par15">In most of the cases, calli were induced from the wounded portions of the leaf; in addition, induction of calli were also noticed at the leaf petiolar end (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>). The best callus induction response was obtained from 1.5&#x000a0;mg/l 2,4-D, wherein highest response percentages (~&#x02009;90%) and highest biomass yield with respect to fresh weight of calli (~&#x02009;830&#x000a0;mg) was obtained when compared to other treatments. Considering the biomass yield in terms of dry weight, 2&#x000a0;mg/l 2,4-D gave the&#x000a0;best results (~&#x02009;45&#x000a0;mg). However, earliest callus induction was observed in 2&#x000a0;mg/l BA. Across the different PGR concentrations, it was noticed that an increase in concentrations of PGR led to an&#x000a0;increase in callusing in case of 2,4-D, whereas in case of BA, callusing rates attained peak at 1&#x000a0;mg/l and then showed subsequent reduction. In case of KIN, even though callus induction responses fluctuated within the range&#x02009;~&#x02009;45&#x02013;49%, yet highest biomass yield in terms of fresh weight and dry weight were obtained from 0.5&#x000a0;mg/l KIN, indicating converse relation with PGR concentration (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab3" ref-type="table">3</xref>). All the calli obtained from 2,4-D were greenish white and friable, justifying their organogenic nature. The calli obtained from BA and KIN were light green in colour and compact to friable in form (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>).<fig id="Fig3"><label>Fig.&#x000a0;3</label><caption><p>Influence of type, concentration, and combination of plant growth regulators (cytokinins and auxin) on callus induction and its proliferation from leaf explants of <italic>Rauvolfia serpentina</italic> (L.) Benth. ex Kurz. (Bar&#x02009;=&#x02009;5&#x000a0;mm)</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="13205_2020_2285_Fig3_HTML" id="MO3"/></fig><table-wrap id="Tab3"><label>Table&#x000a0;3</label><caption><p>Influence of plant growth regulators on callus induction from leaf explants of <italic>Rauvolfia serpentina</italic> (L.) Benth. ex Kurz</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="3">Plant growth regulators (mg/l)</th><th align="left" colspan="4">Morphogenetic response</th></tr><tr><th align="left" rowspan="2">Frequency of response to callus induction (%)</th><th align="left" rowspan="2">Days to induction of callus</th><th align="left" rowspan="2">FW (mg)</th><th align="left" rowspan="2">DW (mg)</th></tr><tr><th align="left">2,4-D</th><th align="left">BA</th><th align="left">KIN</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left">0.5</td><td align="left">&#x02013;</td><td align="left">&#x02013;</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">50.8&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;3.4d</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">13.3&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.3cd</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">30.0&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;10.4de</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">6.7&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.7c</td></tr><tr><td align="left">1</td><td align="left">&#x02013;</td><td align="left">&#x02013;</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">68.8&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;2.7b</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">18.7&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.5cd</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">285.0&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;18.0c</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">26.0&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;2.6b</td></tr><tr><td align="left">1.5</td><td align="left">&#x02013;</td><td align="left">&#x02013;</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">90.0&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.0a</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">20.3&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.7b&#x02013;d</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">830.0&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;36.1a</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">40.7&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;5.8a</td></tr><tr><td align="left">2</td><td align="left">&#x02013;</td><td align="left">&#x02013;</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">90.0&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.0a</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">26.7&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;4.3ab</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">528.3&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;64.3b</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">45.3&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;8.1a</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x02013;</td><td align="left">0.5</td><td align="left">&#x02013;</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">46.9&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.9d</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">15.3&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.7cd</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">11.7&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.7e</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">2.0&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;2.3c</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x02013;</td><td align="left">1</td><td align="left">&#x02013;</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">59.0&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;2.2c</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">18.0&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;2.0cd</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">91.7&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;9.3d</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">7.2&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.6c</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x02013;</td><td align="left">1.5</td><td align="left">&#x02013;</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">48.8&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.9d</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">18.0&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;2.1cd</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">23.3&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;2.4e</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">4.2&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.5c</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x02013;</td><td align="left">2</td><td align="left">&#x02013;</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">46.9&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.9d</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">13.0&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.0d</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">13.7&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;2.0e</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">2.0&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.6c</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x02013;</td><td align="left">&#x02013;</td><td align="left">0.5</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">48.8&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.9d</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">20.3&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;3.8b&#x02013;d</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">30.7&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;6.9de</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">3.9&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.8c</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x02013;</td><td align="left">&#x02013;</td><td align="left">1</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">46.9&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.9d</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">21.0&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.0b&#x02013;d</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">18.7&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.8e</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">2.1&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.7c</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x02013;</td><td align="left">&#x02013;</td><td align="left">1.5</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">45.0&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.0d</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">14.3&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.3cd</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">9.3&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.2e</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">1.3&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.3c</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x02013;</td><td align="left">&#x02013;</td><td align="left">2</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">46.9&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.9d</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">21.3&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;3.9bc</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">14.3&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;2.8e</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">1.3&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.3c</td></tr><tr><td align="left">C</td><td align="left">&#x02013;</td><td align="left">&#x02013;</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">21.1&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;2.7e</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">33.3&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;3.3a</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">13.3&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;2.4e</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">1.3&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.3c</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>Data represent mean of three replicates with ten samples (leaf explants) per treatment. Growth period 56&#x000a0;days (<italic>C</italic> control)</p><p>Data for each column followed by the different letters are significantly different according to Tukey&#x02019;s test at <italic>P</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.05</p><p>Data expressed as percentage were transformed using arc sine prior to ANOVA and converted back to the original scale for demonstration in the table (Compton <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">1994</xref>)</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p></sec><sec id="Sec15"><title>Indirect regeneration: shoot regeneration from callus</title><p id="Par16">From the above-mentioned experiments on callus induction, it was found that the PGR treatments involving 1&#x02013;1.5&#x000a0;mg/l 2,4-D were highly proliferative and organogenic, and were thus used for indirect shoot regeneration purposes. Across the different concentrations of PGRs, 1&#x000a0;mg/l TDZ in combination with 0.2&#x000a0;mg/l NAA was found to be the best in terms of shoot and leaf proliferation (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>). The highest biomass yield with respect to fresh weight (~&#x02009;3080&#x000a0;mg) and maximum shoot length (~&#x02009;22&#x000a0;mm) was observed in case of 1&#x000a0;mg/l KIN&#x02009;+&#x02009;0.2&#x000a0;mg/l NAA when compared to other PGR combinations. However, the highest response percentage (shoot regeneration&#x02009;~&#x02009;75%) and earliness to shooting (~&#x02009;3&#x000a0;days) were recorded in case of 1.5&#x000a0;mg/l KIN&#x02009;+&#x02009;0.2&#x000a0;mg/l NAA. Biomass production, in terms of fresh weight and dry weights, had been impressive with 1.5&#x000a0;mg/l BA&#x02009;+&#x02009;0.2&#x000a0;mg/l NAA combination, thereby displaying the highest dry weight of the regenerated clumps (~&#x02009;275&#x000a0;mg). PGR-free control medium also exhibited regeneration but with&#x000a0;the least frequency. Proliferation rates showed converse responses with PGR concentrations in case of BA&#x02009;+&#x02009;KIN combinations, however, in case TDZ&#x02009;+&#x02009;NAA combinations, intermediate PGR level gave better response (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab4" ref-type="table">4</xref>). Hence, KIN at an intermediate dose proved to be an effective PGR for the purpose of shoot elongation in the present study.<fig id="Fig4"><label>Fig.&#x000a0;4</label><caption><p>Influence of type, concentration, and combination of plant growth regulators (cytokinins:auxin) on indirect regeneration (callus-mediated regeneration of multiple shoots)&#x000a0;in <italic>Rauvolfia serpentina</italic> (L.) Benth. ex Kurz. (Bar&#x02009;=&#x02009;5&#x000a0;mm)</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="13205_2020_2285_Fig4_HTML" id="MO4"/></fig><table-wrap id="Tab4"><label>Table&#x000a0;4</label><caption><p>Influence of plant growth regulators on indirect shoot regeneration from callus of <italic>Rauvolfia serpentina</italic> (L.) Benth. ex Kurz</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" colspan="4">Plant growth regulators (mg/l)</th><th align="left" colspan="7">Morphogenetic response</th></tr><tr><th align="left">NAA</th><th align="left">BA</th><th align="left">KIN</th><th align="left">TDZ</th><th align="left">Frequency of response to shoot initiation (%)</th><th align="left">Days to initiation of shoot initiation</th><th align="left">No. of shoots/explant</th><th align="left">Shoot length (mm)</th><th align="left">No. of leaves/explant</th><th align="left">FW (mg)</th><th align="left">DW (mg)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left">0.2</td><td align="left">0.5</td><td align="left">&#x02013;</td><td align="left">&#x02013;</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">70.1&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;10.1a</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">6.7&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.88bc</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">13.0&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;4.0a</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">13.3&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.8b</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">27.0&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;2.8a</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">2625.0&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;233.8ab</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">240.0&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;11.5a</td></tr><tr><td align="left">0.2</td><td align="left">1</td><td align="left">&#x02013;</td><td align="left">&#x02013;</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">61.2&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;2.2a</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">3.7&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.6c</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">9.3&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.5ab</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">18.3&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.3a</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">22.7&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;5.5a</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">2975.0&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;95.2ab</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">265.0&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;20.2a</td></tr><tr><td align="left">0.2</td><td align="left">1.5</td><td align="left">&#x02013;</td><td align="left">&#x02013;</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">61.2&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;2.2a</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">5.7&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.8bc</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">8.7&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.8ab</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">13.0&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;2.5b</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">27.7&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;5.8a</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">2920.0&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;115.5ab</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">275.0&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;14.4a</td></tr><tr><td align="left">0.2</td><td align="left">&#x02013;</td><td align="left">0.5</td><td align="left">&#x02013;</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">72.3&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;8.9a</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">5.0&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.5bc</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">15.0&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;4.0a</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">13.3&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.8b</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">26.7&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;5.2a</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">2885.0&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;453.2ab</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">255.0&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;20.2a</td></tr><tr><td align="left">0.2</td><td align="left">&#x02013;</td><td align="left">1</td><td align="left">&#x02013;</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">63.9&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;4.3a</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">8.7&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.7b</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">11.3&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.8ab</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">22.0&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.7a</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">25.3&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;7.2a</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">3080.0&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;103.9a</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">235.0&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;8.7a</td></tr><tr><td align="left">0.2</td><td align="left">&#x02013;</td><td align="left">1.5</td><td align="left">&#x02013;</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">75.0&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;7.8a</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">3.3&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.3c</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">14.3&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;2.0a</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">11.0&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.6b</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">17.0&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;2.1ab</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">2285.0&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;222.3ab</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">265.0&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;8.6a</td></tr><tr><td align="left">0.2</td><td align="left">&#x02013;</td><td align="left">&#x02013;</td><td align="left">0.5</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">68.8&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;13.1a</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">5.3&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.2bc</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">12.3&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;4.9a</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">12.0&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.7b</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">30.0&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;8.7a</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">2795.0&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;522.5ab</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">245.0&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;31.7a</td></tr><tr><td align="left">0.2</td><td align="left">&#x02013;</td><td align="left">&#x02013;</td><td align="left">1</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">72.3&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;8.8a</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">4.0&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.6c</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">16.7&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;2.0a</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">18.3&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.8a</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">32.3&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;4.1a</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">2115.0&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;210.7b</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">245.0&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;31.7a</td></tr><tr><td align="left">0.2</td><td align="left">&#x02013;</td><td align="left"/><td align="left">1.5</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">59.0&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;2.2a</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">5.7&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.7bc</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">8.3&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.8ab</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">12.3&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.5b</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">18.3&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.5ab</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">2460.0&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;40.4ab</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">225.0&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;2.8a</td></tr><tr><td align="left">C</td><td align="left">&#x02013;</td><td align="left">&#x02013;</td><td align="left">&#x02013;</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">21.1&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;2.7b</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">14.3&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.7a</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">2.7&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.3b</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">6.3&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.8c</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">3.7&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.3b</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">362.3&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;51.9c</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">42.0&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;5.1b</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>Data represent mean of three replicates with ten samples (callus explants) per treatment.*Growth period 56&#x000a0;days (<italic>C</italic> control)</p><p>Data for each column followed by the different letters are significantly different according to Tukey&#x02019;s test at <italic>P</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.05</p><p>Data expressed as percentage were transformed using arc sine prior to ANOVA and converted back to the original scale for demonstration in the table (Compton <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">1994</xref>)</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p></sec><sec id="Sec16"><title>Quantification of reserpine level</title><p id="Par17">During the conduction of the present experiment, the reserpine standard displayed a solitary peak in the HPLTC chromatogram. The maximum value of UV for the estimation of reserpine from the samples of <italic>R. serpentina</italic>, consisting of multiple shoots from direct regeneration, callus-mediated regeneration, and the mother plant, was selected with help of the UV spectrum of reserpine obtained before and after completion of the experiment. The chromatogram obtained from the standard reserpine exhibited the peak at 268&#x000a0;nm (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>). Calculation of the peak area from the obtained graph exhibited that in vitro shoots yielded 503&#x000a0;&#x003bc;g/g of reserpine on dry weight basis, whereas in vitro callus yielded 319&#x000a0;&#x003bc;g/g of reserpine. Shoots from mother plant yielded 184&#x000a0;&#x003bc;g/g of reserpine on dry weight basis. Thus, an enhancement in the reserpine content under in vitro culture via both direct shoot regeneration systems (~&#x02009;three folds) and indirect (callus-mediated) regeneration systems (~&#x02009;two folds) was achieved in the present study following this refined protocol.<fig id="Fig5"><label>Fig.&#x000a0;5</label><caption><p>Estimation of reserpine content in the extract from in vitro shoots (direct regeneration), calli (indirect regeneration), and shoots of mother plant of <italic>Rauvolfia serpentina</italic> (L.) Benth. ex Kurz. <bold>a</bold> HPTLC fingerprint of the extracts; <bold>b</bold> HPTLC 3D overlay densitogram of reserpine standard with that of the extracts obtained from in vitro shoots, calli and shoots of mother plant; chromatographs of <bold>c</bold> reserpine standard, <bold>d</bold> extract from in vitro shoot, <bold>e</bold> calli, and <bold>f</bold> mother plant (shoot)</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="13205_2020_2285_Fig5_HTML" id="MO5"/></fig></p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec17"><title>Discussion</title><p id="Par18">For in vitro multiple shoot initiation in <italic>R. serpentina</italic> in the present study, BA outperformed the other four cytokinins (namely, KIN, TDZ, zeatin and mT). Presumably, BA is effective in breaking apical dominance, thereby promoting more lateral bud initiation and subsequent growth (also confirmed by Bahuguna et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">2011</xref>). Such result justifies that this type and dose of PGR is optimum for the direct growth and development of meristematic tissues. Initiation and multiplication rates, including biomass enhancement, were much superior in case of BA than the other PGR types and concentrations, which was also established in the reports of Mishra et al. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">2010</xref>), Alatar et al. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">2012</xref>), George et al. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">2012</xref>), and Faisal et al. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">2012</xref>) in <italic>Rauvolfia</italic> spp. Irrespective of PGR type, lower concentrations exhibited better performance than the higher ones, with the exception of BA. Similar results were published in the reports of Mallick et al. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">2012</xref>) and Zafar et al. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">2019</xref>) wherein it was claimed that shoots were more responsive to higher concentrations of BA during shoot induction. Most likely, a higher dose of BA was effective in shoot initiation and lower concentrations of the same induced better shoot growth and proliferation. In <italic>Rauvolfia</italic>, across several published reports, it was detected that the effects of zeatin and mT on shoot multiplication were not explored (reviewed by Mukherjee et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">2019</xref>) till date, which has been duly addressed in the present study. It was further noticed that application of BA resulted in enhanced shoot multiplication and higher biomass content, whereas application of KIN resulted in elongation of shoots. Such findings are in homology with the reports of Shivaraj and Rao (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">2011</xref>) in eggplant (<italic>Solanum melongena</italic> L.), wherein the effectiveness of BA (in obtaining higher frequency of shooting) and KIN (in shoot elongation) were highlighted. In most of the published reports related to the direct regeneration (i.e., direct multiple shoot proliferation) in <italic>Rauvolfia</italic>, the effects of combination media, viz., BA&#x02009;+&#x02009;KIN&#x02009;+&#x02009;IAA or NAA, have been studied. During proliferation of initiated multiple shoots, TDZ in combination of NAA significantly outperformed the other cytokinins (BA or KIN). Such beneficial effects of TDZ on inducing shoot multiplication and elongation were also reported by Alatar (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2015</xref>). As per the reports of Mondal et al. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">2011</xref>), Alatar et al. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">2012</xref>), Rani et al. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">2014</xref>), and Ahmad et al. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">2015</xref>), it was confirmed that media containing cytokinin&#x02009;+&#x02009;auxin combinations were effective in direct shoot regeneration. However, contrary to their reports, wherein it was claimed that BA&#x02009;+&#x02009;NAA combinations were much more effective in shoot proliferation; the present experiment has revealed, otherwise, that KIN&#x02009;+&#x02009;NAA combinations yielded better results.</p><p id="Par19">Leaf explants chosen for callus induction were subjected to different PGRs, which exhibited differential rates of callus induction and proliferation. Efficiency of leaf explants during induction of callus in <italic>R. serpentina</italic> was reported by majority of the earlier studies (reviewed by Mukherjee et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">2019</xref>). Calli induced with the application of 2,4-D were organogenic and greenish white. Similar findings were reported by Bahuguna et al. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">2011</xref>), Mallick et al. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">2012</xref>), Rohela et al. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">2013</xref>), and Gantait et al. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">2017</xref>). On the other hand, BA- or KIN-induced calli were light green and compact to friable in nature. This is in accordance with the results that were&#x000a0;reported by Singh et al. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">2009</xref>) and Rohela et al. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">2013</xref>) on <italic>R. serpentina</italic>. Contrary to our results, whitish calli from BA&#x02009;+&#x02009;IAA were obtained by Rani et al. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">2014</xref>) and friable calli from BA alone were reported by Zafar et al. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">2019</xref>). In comparison to control, wherein minute callus was observed to have formed from the petiolar end, it could be clearly stated that in&#x000a0;PGR-supplemented media, especially auxins like 2,4-D&#x000a0;were utilized for inducing friable calli, and cytokinins (BA and KIN) employed for inducing green embryogenic calli, proved to be&#x000a0;much more efficient. The above findings are in conformity with the reports of Mallick et al. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">2012</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">2013</xref>), and Rashmi and Trivedi (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">2016</xref>) on <italic>R. serpentina</italic>, where solely 2,4-D was responsible for callus formation, although the dose of PGR had been higher (2.5&#x000a0;mg/l) than the present report. However, Rashmi and Trivedi (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">2016</xref>) further reported the use of BA&#x02009;+&#x02009;2,4-D combination for callus induction. In the reports of Pandey et al. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">2007</xref>), Bahuguna et al. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">2011</xref>), Panwar et al. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">2011</xref>), Rohela et al. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">2013</xref>), and Zafar et al. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">2019</xref>), it was stated that 1&#x02013;2&#x000a0;mg/l 2,4-D along NAA or BA or KIN was effective in higher callus inductions. However, Gantait et al. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">2017</xref>) reported the use of a higher dose of 2,4-D (5&#x000a0;mg/l) along with 2&#x000a0;mg/l NAA for callus induction in <italic>R. serpentina</italic>. Contrary to the present study, Singh et al. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">2009</xref>), Saravanan et al. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">2011</xref>), Rani et al. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">2014</xref>), Kaur (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">2018</xref>), and Pant and Joshi (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">2018</xref>) had obtained maximum callus induction using PGRs like BA, KIN, NAA, IBA, and IAA, instead of using 2,4-D.</p><p id="Par20">Interaction between cytokinins and auxins in shoot regeneration from callus cultures was explored in the present study. Shoot regeneration from calli, employing TDZ alone, has also been reported by Pandey et al. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">2007</xref>), although a dose that was as high as 4&#x000a0;mg/l was used. Reports of Rohela et al. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">2013</xref>) also highlighted the use of TDZ (2.27&#x000a0;&#x000b5;M) for successful shoot regeneration. In the same way, Kaur (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">2018</xref>) also reported high callus induction using solely BA or KIN. Contrary to the result of the present study, in most of the other reports related to shoot regeneration from calli, BA&#x02009;+&#x02009;NAA combinations were frequently used (Panwar et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">2011</xref>, Mallick et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">2012</xref>, Rashmi and Trivedi <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">2016</xref>). However, Uikey et al. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">2016</xref>) mentioned the usage of three PGRs interventions such as BA, TDZ, and NAA (each at a dose of 0.5&#x000a0;mg/l) for shoot regeneration from embryogenic callus-derived somatic embryos. In some cases, indirect (callus-mediated) shoot regeneration was obtained in the media supplemented with GA<sub>3</sub> along with the presence of BA (Singh et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">2009</xref>; Bahuguna et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">2011</xref>; Gantait et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">2017</xref>). However, unlike the present experiment, not a single study (related to callus regeneration in <italic>Rauvolfia</italic>) reported the use of KIN&#x02009;+&#x02009;NAA and TDZ&#x02009;+&#x02009;NAA combinations, solely (reviewed by Mukherjee et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">2019</xref>). In majority of the reports, KIN was used in combination with BA, NAA, or IAA individually (Rohela et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">2013</xref>; Rani et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">2014</xref>).</p><p id="Par21">Based on the HPTLC analysis of the samples, multiple shoots (via direct regeneration) exhibited higher reserpine content than calli. Possible explanation to this could be that the cells and tissues under direct regeneration have a definite organization, so the cells are oriented towards a defined biological development, which leads to a uniform biosynthesis of secondary metabolites. On the other hand, calli have an unorganized constitution, wherein not all cells might be active and hence are&#x000a0;oriented towards a defined development and secondary metabolite production. The obtained result (reserpine content of the mother plant) of the present experiment corresponds with the reports of Panigrahi et al. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">2017</xref>), wherein it was mentioned that in vitro cultured plant parts contain significantly higher secondary metabolites than that of the same ex vitro plant parts. For instance, a lower value of reserpine from ex vitro leaves (13.77&#x000a0;&#x003bc;g) was reported by Panda et al. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">2010</xref>). Contrary to our results, much higher values of secondary metabolite content were reported in the findings of Panwar and Guru (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">2011</xref>), where the crude alkaloid contents in various parts of in vitro regenerants through HPTLC were quantified. It was mentioned in their report that in vitro leaves yielded 2.35&#x000a0;mg/g reserpine&#x000a0;and stem and leaf-derived calli yielded 6.81&#x000a0;mg/g and 8.98&#x000a0;mg/g reserpine, respectively. In addition, the afore-mentioned report stated the richness of reserpine content in de-differentiated calli than well-organized shoot and leaf structures, which differs from the findings of the present study. As per the report of Panwar and Guru (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">2015</xref>), it was stated that in vitro regenerants produced 55.67&#x000a0;mg/g reserpine on dry weight basis. However, such enhancement was obtained only through salicylic acid and tryptamine elicitations. Similar usage of elicitors for reserpine enhancement was reported by Nurcahyani et al. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">2008</xref>), Harisaranraj et al. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">2009</xref>), Zafar et al. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">2017</xref>); thus, differing from the results of the present experiment, wherein enhancement of the secondary metabolite was affected without the use of any elicitor. There are multiple reports related to reserpine estimation from in vitro shoot or calli or cell suspension culture or synthetic seeds or hairy roots individually (reviewed by Mukherjee et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">2019</xref>). Investigations of Gantait and Kundu (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">2017</xref>) reported 249.37&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.21&#x000a0;&#x000b5;g/gm reserpine content from germinated synthetic seeds that were kept under storage at 8&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C, whereas Faisal et al. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">2013</xref>) reported a homogeneity in reserpine levels between the germinated synthetic seeds (that were stored under 4&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C storage) and ex vitro grown mother plant. Nonetheless, the present report is the first one of its kind that provides a comparative analysis of reserpine production between mother plants and regenerants from in vitro cultures, raised via direct (shoot multiplication) and indirect (callus-mediated) pathways.</p></sec><sec id="Sec18"><title>Conclusion</title><p id="Par22">In the present study, a comprehensive regeneration protocol using both direct (multiple shoot) and indirect (callus-mediated) systems, under in vitro condition, has been developed. This is the only report wherein a comparative study regarding shoot initiation and its subsequent proliferation under the influence of five different PGRs viz. BA, KIN, TDZ, zeatin, and mT have been studied. Additionally, contrary to most other reports, wherein either BA&#x02009;+&#x02009;NAA or KIN&#x02009;+&#x02009;NAA combinations had been used to study shoot proliferation and/or indirect shoot regeneration from calli; the present report explores the influence of the above-mentioned PGR combinations along with TDZ&#x02009;+&#x02009;NAA to further bring about a significant enhancement in shoot multiplications and indirect shoot regenerations from calli. Similarly, the PGR type and concentration for better callus induction, using leaf explants, has also been studied in this experiment. This report exclusively provides an estimation of the enhanced (two&#x02013;three folds) reserpine content from in vitro shoot and callus cultures in comparison to the ex vitro grown mother plant. Thus, in vitro direct regeneration system&#x000a0;proved to be a&#x000a0;more effective and efficient&#x000a0;approach in ameliorating reserpine content.</p></sec></body><back><fn-group><fn><p>Eashan Mukherjee and Saikat Gantait have contributed equally to this work.</p></fn></fn-group><ack><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>The authors acknowledge the experimental assistance from Plant Tissue Culture laboratory at Regional Nuclear Agricultural Research Centre, Bidhan Chandra Krishi Viswavidyalaya, West Bengal, India.</p></ack><notes notes-type="author-contribution"><title>Author contributions</title><p>Conceptualization: SG; methodology: SG; formal analysis and investigation: EM, SG; writing&#x02014;original draft preparation: EM, SG; writing&#x02014;review and editing critically for important intellectual content: SG, SS, and SB; supervision: SG.</p></notes><notes notes-type="funding-information"><title>Funding</title><p>This research did not obtain any specific grant from funding agencies in the public, commercial, or not-for-profit sectors.</p></notes><notes notes-type="ethics"><title>Compliance with ethical standards</title><notes id="FPar1" notes-type="COI-statement"><title>Conflict of interest</title><p id="Par23">All the authors declare that he has no conflict of interest.</p></notes><notes id="FPar2"><title>Ethical approval</title><p id="Par24">This article does not contain any studies with human participants or animals performed by any of the authors.</p></notes></notes><ref-list id="Bib1"><title>References</title><ref id="CR1"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ahmad</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Alatar</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name><name><surname>Faisal</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Khan</surname><given-names>MI</given-names></name><name><surname>Fatima</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Anis</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Hagezy</surname><given-names>AK</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effect of copper and zinc on the in vitro regeneration of <italic>Rauvolfia serpentina</italic></article-title><source>Biol Plant</source><year>2015</year><volume>59</volume><fpage>11</fpage><lpage>17</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR2"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Alatar</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Thidiazuron induced efficient in vitro multiplication and ex vitro conservation of <italic>Rauvolfia serpentina</italic> a potent antihypertensive drug producing plant</article-title><source>Biotechnol Equip</source><year>2015</year><volume>29</volume><fpage>489</fpage><lpage>497</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR3"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Alatar</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name><name><surname>Faisal</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Hegazy</surname><given-names>AK</given-names></name><name><surname>Hend</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>High frequency shoot regeneration and plant establishment of <italic>Rauvolfia serpentina:</italic> an endangered medicinal plant</article-title><source>J Med Plant Res</source><year>2012</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>3324</fpage><lpage>3329</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR4"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bahuguna</surname><given-names>RN</given-names></name><name><surname>Joshi</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Shukla</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Gupta</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Bains</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Micropropagation and total alkaloid extraction of Indian snake root (<italic>Rauwolfia serpentina</italic>)</article-title><source>Indian J Agric Sci</source><year>2011</year><volume>81</volume><fpage>1124</fpage><lpage>1129</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR5"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bunkar</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Therapeutic uses of <italic>Rauwolfia serpentina</italic></article-title><source>Int J Adv Sci Res</source><year>2017</year><volume>2</volume><fpage>23</fpage><lpage>26</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR6"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Compton</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Statistical methods suitable for the analysis of plant tissue culture data</article-title><source>Plant Cell Tissue Organ Cult</source><year>1994</year><volume>37</volume><fpage>217</fpage><lpage>242</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR7"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Faisal</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Alatar</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name><name><surname>Ahmed</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Anis</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Hegazy</surname><given-names>AK</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>An efficient and reproducible method for in vitro clonal multiplication of <italic>Rauvolfia tetraphylla</italic> L. and evaluation of genetic stability using DNA-based markers</article-title><source>Appl Biochem Biotechnol</source><year>2012</year><volume>168</volume><fpage>1739</fpage><lpage>1752</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22968591</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR8"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Faisal</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Alatar</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name><name><surname>Hegazy</surname><given-names>AK</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Molecular and biochemical characterization in <italic>Rauvolfia tetraphylla</italic> plantlets grown from synthetic seeds following in vitro cold storage</article-title><source>Appl Biochem Biotechnol</source><year>2013</year><volume>169</volume><fpage>408</fpage><lpage>417</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23212849</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR9"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gantait</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Kundu</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Does synthetic seed storage at higher temperature reduce reserpine content of <italic>Rauvolfia serpentina</italic> (L.) Benth. Ex Kurz.?</article-title><source>Rend Lincei Sci Fis Nat</source><year>2017</year><volume>28</volume><fpage>679</fpage><lpage>686</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR10"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gantait</surname><given-names>SS</given-names></name><name><surname>Dutta</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Majumdar</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>In vitro regeneration and conservation of endangered medicinal plant sarpagandha (<italic>Rauvolfia serpentina</italic>)</article-title><source>J Hortic Sci</source><year>2017</year><volume>12</volume><fpage>71</fpage><lpage>77</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR11"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>George</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Geetha</surname><given-names>SP</given-names></name><name><surname>Balachandran</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>In vitro multiplication of <italic>Rauvolfia serpentina</italic> (L.) Benth. ex Kurz&#x02014;an endangered medicinal plant</article-title><source>Med Plant</source><year>2012</year><volume>4</volume><fpage>45</fpage><lpage>48</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR12"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ghate</surname><given-names>VU</given-names></name><name><surname>Gajendragadkar</surname><given-names>MP</given-names></name><name><surname>Jadhav</surname><given-names>AB</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Review of <italic>Rauvolfia serpentina</italic> (L.) Benth. Ex Kurz.</article-title><source>Int J Res</source><year>2019</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>414</fpage><lpage>421</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR13"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Harisaranraj</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Suresh</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Babu</surname><given-names>SS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Production of reserpine in somatic embryos of <italic>Rauwolfia serpentina</italic> cultured in bioreactors by the induction of elicitor (Methyl Jasmonate)</article-title><source>Glob J Biotechnol Biochem</source><year>2009</year><volume>4</volume><fpage>143</fpage><lpage>147</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR14"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kaur</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title><italic>In vitro</italic> callus induction in inflorescence segments of medicinally important endangered plant <italic>Rauwolfia serpentina</italic> (L.) Benth. ex Kurz&#x02014;a step towards ex situ conservation</article-title><source>Ann Plant Sci</source><year>2018</year><volume>7</volume><fpage>1988</fpage><lpage>1991</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR15"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Khan</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Banu</surname><given-names>TA</given-names></name><name><surname>Akhter</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Goswami</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Islam</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Hani</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><name><surname>Habib</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>In vitro regeneration protocol of <italic>Rauvolfia serpentina</italic> L.</article-title><source>Bangladesh J Sci Ind Res</source><year>2018</year><volume>53</volume><fpage>133</fpage><lpage>138</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR16"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lobay</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title><italic>Rauwolfia</italic>&#x000a0;in the treatment of hypertension</article-title><source>Integr Med (Encinitas)</source><year>2015</year><volume>14</volume><fpage>40</fpage><lpage>46</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR17"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mallick</surname><given-names>SR</given-names></name><name><surname>Jena</surname><given-names>RC</given-names></name><name><surname>Samal</surname><given-names>KC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Rapid in vitro multiplication of an endangered medicinal plant sarpgandha (<italic>Rauwolfia serpentina</italic>)</article-title><source>Am J Plant Sci</source><year>2012</year><volume>3</volume><fpage>437</fpage><lpage>442</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR18"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mallick</surname><given-names>SR</given-names></name><name><surname>Samal</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Jena</surname><given-names>RC</given-names></name><name><surname>Samal</surname><given-names>KC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Alkaloid profiling of conventionally propagated and in vitro raised plants of Indian snake plant (<italic>Rauwolfia serpentina</italic> L.)</article-title><source>Asian J Chem</source><year>2013</year><volume>25</volume><fpage>6584</fpage><lpage>6586</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR19"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mishra</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Usmani</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Mandal</surname><given-names>AK</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>In vitro cloning of <italic>Rauvolfia serpentina</italic> (L.) Benth. var. CIM-Sheel and evaluation of its field performance</article-title><source>J Biol Res-Thessalon</source><year>2010</year><volume>13</volume><fpage>85</fpage><lpage>92</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR20"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mondal</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Texeirada Silva</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Ghosh</surname><given-names>PD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>In vitro flowering in <italic>Rauvolfia serpentina</italic> (L.) Benth. ex. Kurz</article-title><source>Int J Plant Dev Biol</source><year>2011</year><volume>5</volume><fpage>75</fpage><lpage>77</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR21"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mukherjee</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Gantait</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Kundu</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Sarkar</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Bhattacharyya</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Biotechnological interventions in the genus <italic>Rauvolfia</italic>: recent trends and imminent prospects</article-title><source>Appl Microbiol Biotechnol</source><year>2019</year><volume>103</volume><fpage>7325</fpage><lpage>7354</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31363825</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR22"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Murashige</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Skoog</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A revised medium for rapid growth and bio assays with tobacco tissue cultures</article-title><source>Physiol Plant</source><year>1962</year><volume>15</volume><fpage>473</fpage><lpage>495</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR23"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nurcahyani</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Solichatun</surname></name><name><surname>Anggarwulan</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The reserpine production and callus growth of Indian snake root (<italic>Rauvolfia serpentina</italic> (L.) Benth. Ex Kurz) culture by addition of Cu<sup>2+</sup></article-title><source>Biodiversitas</source><year>2008</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>177</fpage><lpage>179</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR24"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Panda</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></name><name><surname>Pattanayak</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Oraon</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Parh</surname><given-names>PK</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Quantitative estimation of reserpine in different pars of <italic>R. serpentina</italic> and <italic>R. tetraphylla</italic> by using HPTLC</article-title><source>Der Pharm Lett</source><year>2010</year><volume>2</volume><fpage>363</fpage><lpage>370</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR25"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pandey</surname><given-names>VP</given-names></name><name><surname>Kudakasseril</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Cherian</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Patani</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Comparison of two methods for in vitro propagation of <italic>Rauwolfia serpentina</italic> from nodal explants</article-title><source>Indian Drugs</source><year>2007</year><volume>44</volume><fpage>514</fpage><lpage>519</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR26"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pandey</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Kaur</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Chattopadhyay</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></name><name><surname>Srivastava</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></name><name><surname>Banerjee</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Long-term stability in biomass and production of terpene indole alkaloids by hairy root culture of <italic>Rauvolfia serpentina</italic> and cost approximation to endorse commercial realism</article-title><source>Biotechnol Lett</source><year>2014</year><volume>36</volume><fpage>1523</fpage><lpage>1528</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24658738</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR27"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Panigrahi</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Gantait</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Patel</surname><given-names>IC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Concurrent production and relative quantification of vasicinone from in vivo and in vitro plant parts of Malabar nut (<italic>Adhatoda vasica</italic> Nees)</article-title><source>3Biotech</source><year>2017</year><volume>7</volume><fpage>280</fpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR28"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pant</surname><given-names>KK</given-names></name><name><surname>Joshi</surname><given-names>SD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>In-vitro somatic embryogenesis and organogenesis from the node induced calli of <italic>Rauvolfia serpentina</italic> Benth. ex Kurz</article-title><source>Nep J Agric Sci</source><year>2018</year><volume>17</volume><fpage>167</fpage><lpage>173</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR29"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Panwar</surname><given-names>GS</given-names></name><name><surname>Guru</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Alkaloid profiling and estimation of reserpine in <italic>Rauwolfia serpentina</italic> plant by TLC, HP-TLC and HPLC</article-title><source>Asian J Plant Sci</source><year>2011</year><volume>10</volume><fpage>393</fpage><lpage>400</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR30"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Panwar</surname><given-names>GS</given-names></name><name><surname>Guru</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Stimulation of reserpine production in the whole plant culture of <italic>Rauwolfia serpentina</italic> L. by elicitors and precursor feeding</article-title><source>J Plant Biochem Biotechnol</source><year>2015</year><volume>24</volume><fpage>49</fpage><lpage>55</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR31"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Panwar</surname><given-names>GS</given-names></name><name><surname>Attitalla</surname><given-names>IH</given-names></name><name><surname>Guru</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>An efficient in vitro clonal propagation and estimation of reserpine content in different plant parts of <italic>Rauwolfia serpentina</italic> L</article-title><source>Am-Eur J Sci Res</source><year>2011</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>217</fpage><lpage>222</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR32"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pillai</surname><given-names>PP</given-names></name><name><surname>Sajan</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name><name><surname>Menon</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></name><name><surname>Jayakumar</surname><given-names>KSP</given-names></name><name><surname>Subramoniam</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>ISSR analysis reveals high intraspecific variation in <italic>Rauvolfia serpentina</italic> L.&#x02014;a high value medicinal plant</article-title><source>Biochem Syst Ecol</source><year>2012</year><volume>40</volume><fpage>192</fpage><lpage>197</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR33"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rani</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Kumar</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Kumar</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Micropropagation of serpgandha (<italic>Rauvolfia serpentina</italic> L. Benth). An endangered medicinal plant</article-title><source>Appl Biol Res</source><year>2014</year><volume>16</volume><fpage>114</fpage><lpage>118</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR34"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rashmi</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Trivedi</surname><given-names>MP</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Rapid in vitro regeneration of an endangered medicinal plant sarpagandha (<italic>Rauvolfia serpentina</italic> L.)</article-title><source>Eur J Pharm Med Res</source><year>2016</year><volume>3</volume><fpage>276</fpage><lpage>284</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR35"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rohela</surname><given-names>GK</given-names></name><name><surname>Bylla</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Kota</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Abbagani</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Chithakari</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Reuben</surname><given-names>TC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title><italic>In vitro</italic> plantlet regeneration from leaf and stem calluses of <italic>Rauwolfia tetraphylla</italic> (<italic>R. canescens</italic>) and confirmation of genetic fidelity of plantlets using the ISSR-PCR method</article-title><source>J Herb Spice Med Plant</source><year>2013</year><volume>19</volume><fpage>66</fpage><lpage>75</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR36"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Saravanan</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Sarvesan</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Vinod</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Identification of DNA elements involved in somaclonal variants of <italic>Rauvolfia serpentina</italic> (L.) arising from indirect organogenesis as evaluated by ISSR analysis</article-title><source>Indian J Sci Technol</source><year>2011</year><volume>4</volume><fpage>1241</fpage><lpage>1245</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR37"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shivaraj</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Rao</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Rapid and efficient plant regeneration of eggplant (<italic>Solanum melongena</italic> L.) from cotyledonary leaf explants</article-title><source>Indian J Biotechnol</source><year>2011</year><volume>10</volume><fpage>125</fpage><lpage>129</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR42"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Shukla</surname><given-names>AK</given-names></name><name><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Pande</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Nailwal</surname><given-names>TK</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Somatic embryogenesis and in vitro regeneration of an endangered medicinal plant sarpgandha (<italic>Rauvolfia serpentina</italic> L.)</article-title><source>Life Sci J</source><year>2009</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>57</fpage><lpage>62</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR38"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Soni</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Jaiswal</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Bara</surname><given-names>JK</given-names></name><name><surname>Saksena</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The use of <italic>Rauwolfia serpentina</italic> in hypertensive patients</article-title><source>IOSR J Biotech Biochem</source><year>2016</year><volume>2</volume><fpage>28</fpage><lpage>32</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR39"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Uikey</surname><given-names>DS</given-names></name><name><surname>Tripathi</surname><given-names>MK</given-names></name><name><surname>Tiwari</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Patel</surname><given-names>RP</given-names></name><name><surname>Ahuja</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Embryogenic cell suspension culture induction and plantlet regeneration of <italic>Rauvolfia serpentina</italic> (L.) Benth.: influence of different plant growth regulator concentrations and combinations</article-title><source>Med Plant</source><year>2016</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>153</fpage><lpage>162</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR40"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zafar</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Mujib</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Ali</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Tonk</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Gulzar</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Aluminium chloride elicitation (amendment) improves callus biomass growth and reserpine yield in <italic>Rauvolfia serpentina</italic> leaf callus</article-title><source>Plant Cell Tissue Organ Cult</source><year>2017</year><volume>130</volume><fpage>357</fpage><lpage>368</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR41"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zafar</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Mujib</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Ali</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Tonk</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Gulzar</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Malik</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Sayeed</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Mamgain</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Genome size analysis of field grown and tissue culture regenerated <italic>Rauvolfia serpentina</italic> (L) by flow cytometry: histology and scanning electron microscopic study for in vitro morphogenesis</article-title><source>Ind Crop Prod</source><year>2019</year><volume>128</volume><fpage>545</fpage><lpage>555</lpage></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>